<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="configureJob">
  <title>Configuring and Running a Job</title>

  <para>In the <link linkend="domain">domain section</link> , the overall
  architecture design was discussed, using the following diagram as a
  guide:</para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata align="center"
                 fileref="images/spring-batch-reference-model.png"
                 format="PNG" scale="100" />
    </imageobject>

    <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata align="center"
                 fileref="images/spring-batch-reference-model.png"
                 format="PNG" scale="55" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>While the <classname>Job</classname> object may seem like a simple
  container for steps, there are many configuration options of which a
  developers must be aware . Furthermore, there are many considerations for
  how a <classname>Job</classname> will be run and how its meta-data will be
  stored during that run. This chapter will explain the various configuration
  options and runtime concerns of a <classname>Job</classname> .</para>

  <section id="configuringAJob">
    <title>Configuring a Job</title>

    <para>There are multiple implementations of the <link linkend="job">
    <classname>Job</classname> </link> interface, however, the namespace
    abstracts away the differences in configuration. It has only three
    required dependencies: a name, <classname>JobRepository</classname> , and
    a list of <classname>Step</classname>s.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="footballJob">
    <step id="playerload"          parent="s1" next="gameLoad"/>
    <step id="gameLoad"            parent="s2" next="playerSummarization"/>
    <step id="playerSummarization" parent="s3"/>
</job>]]></programlisting>

    <para>The examples here use a parent bean definition to create the steps;
    see the section on <link linkend="configureStep">step configuration</link>
    for more options declaring specific step details inline. The XML namespace
    defaults to referencing a repository with an id of 'jobRepository', which
    is a sensible default. However, this can be overridden explicitly:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="footballJob" ]]><emphasis role="bold">job-repository="specialRepository"</emphasis><![CDATA[>
    <step id="playerload"          parent="s1" next="gameLoad"/>
    <step id="gameLoad"            parent="s3" next="playerSummarization"/>
    <step id="playerSummarization" parent="s3"/>
</job>]]></programlisting>

    <para>In addition to steps a job configuration can contain other elements
    that help with parallelisation (<literal>&lt;split/&gt;</literal>),
    declarative flow control (<literal>&lt;decision/&gt;</literal>) and
    externalization of flow definitions
    (<literal>&lt;flow/&gt;</literal>).</para>

    <section id="restartability">
      <title>Restartability</title>

      <para>One key issue when executing a batch job concerns the behavior of
      a <classname>Job</classname> when it is restarted. The launching of a
      <classname>Job</classname> is considered to be a 'restart' if a
      <classname>JobExecution</classname> already exists for the particular
      <classname>JobInstance</classname>. Ideally, all jobs should be able to
      start up where they left off, but there are scenarios where this is not
      possible. <emphasis role="bold">It is entirely up to the developer to
      ensure that a new <classname>JobInstance</classname> is created in this
      scenario</emphasis>. However, Spring Batch does provide some help. If a
      <classname>Job</classname> should never be restarted, but should always
      be run as part of a new <classname>JobInstance</classname>, then the
      restartable property may be set to 'false':</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="footballJob" ]]><emphasis role="bold">restartable="false"</emphasis><![CDATA[>
    ...
</job>]]></programlisting>

      <para>To phrase it another way, setting restartable to false means "this
      Job does not support being started again". Restarting a Job that is not
      restartable will cause a <classname>JobRestartException</classname> to
      be thrown:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[Job job = new SimpleJob();
job.setRestartable(false);

JobParameters jobParameters = new JobParameters();

JobExecution firstExecution = jobRepository.createJobExecution(job, jobParameters);
jobRepository.saveOrUpdate(firstExecution);

try {
    jobRepository.createJobExecution(job, jobParameters);
    fail();
}
catch (JobRestartException e) {
    // expected
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>This snippet of JUnit code shows how attempting to create a
      <classname>JobExecution</classname> the first time for a non restartable
      <classname>job</classname> will cause no issues. However, the second
      attempt will throw a <classname>JobRestartException</classname>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="interceptingJobExecution">
      <title>Intercepting Job Execution</title>

      <para>During the course of the execution of a
      <classname>Job</classname>, it may be useful to be notified of various
      events in its lifecycle so that custom code may be executed. The
      <classname>SimpleJob</classname> allows for this by calling a
      <classname>JobListener</classname> at the appropriate time:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface JobExecutionListener {

    void beforeJob(JobExecution jobExecution);

    void afterJob(JobExecution jobExecution);

}]]></programlisting>

      <para><classname>JobListener</classname>s can be added to a
      <classname>SimpleJob</classname> via the listeners element on the
      job:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="footballJob">
    <step id="playerload"          parent="s1" next="gameLoad"/>
    <step id="gameLoad"            parent="s2" next="playerSummarization"/>
    <step id="playerSummarization" parent="s3"/>
]]><emphasis role="bold">    &lt;listeners&gt;
        &lt;listener ref="sampleListener"/&gt;
    &lt;/listeners&gt;
</emphasis><![CDATA[</job>]]></programlisting>

      <para>It should be noted that <methodname>afterJob</methodname> will be
      called regardless of the success or failure of the
      <classname>Job</classname>. If success or failure needs to be determined
      it can be obtained from the <classname>JobExecution</classname>:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public void afterJob(JobExecution jobExecution){
    if( jobExecution.getStatus() == BatchStatus.COMPLETED ){
        //job success
    }
    else if(jobExecution.getStatus() == BatchStatus.FAILED){
        //job failure
    }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>The annotations corresponding to this interface are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>@BeforeJob</classname></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>@AfterJob</classname></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="inheritingFromAParentJob">
      <title>Inheriting from a Parent Job</title>

      <para>If a group of <classname>Job</classname>s share similar, but not
      identical, configurations, then it may be helpful to define a "parent"
      <classname>Job</classname> from which the concrete
      <classname>Job</classname>s may inherit properties. Similar to class
      inheritance in Java, the "child" <classname>Job</classname> will combine
      its elements and attributes with the parent's.</para>

      <para>In the following example, "baseJob" is an abstract
      <classname>Job</classname> definition that defines only a list of
      listeners. The <classname>Job</classname> "job1" is a concrete
      definition that inherits the list of listeners from "baseJob" and merges
      it with its own list of listeners to produce a
      <classname>Job</classname> with two listeners and one
      <classname>Step</classname>, "step1".</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="baseJob" abstract="true">
    <listeners>
        <listener ref="listenerOne"/>
    <listeners>
</job>

<job id="job1" parent="baseJob">
    <step id="step1" parent="standaloneStep"/>

    <listeners merge="true">
        <listener ref="listenerTwo"/>
    <listeners>
</job>]]></programlisting>

      <para>Please see the section on <link
      linkend="InheritingFromParentStep">Inheriting from a Parent Step</link>
      for more detailed information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JobParametersValidator</title>

      <para>A job declared in the XML namespace or using any subclass of
      AbstractJob can optionally declare a validator for the job parameters at
      runtime. This is useful when for instance you need to assert that a job
      is started with all its mandatory parameters. There is a
      DefaultJobParametersValidator that can be used to constrain combinations
      of simple mandatory and optional parameters, and for more complex
      constraints you can implement the interface yourself. The configuration
      of a validator is supported through the XML namespace through a child
      element of the job, e.g:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="job1" parent="baseJob3">
    <step id="step1" parent="standaloneStep"/>
    <validator ref="paremetersValidator"/>
</job>]]></programlisting>

      <para>The validator can be specified as a reference (as above) or as a
      nested bean definition in the beans namespace.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="configuringJobRepository">
     

    <title>Configuring a JobRepository</title>

     

    <para>As described in earlier, the <link linkend="jobRepository">
        <classname>JobRepository</classname>
      </link> is used for basic CRUD operations of the various persisted
    domain objects within Spring Batch, such as
    <classname>JobExecution</classname> and
    <classname>StepExecution</classname>. It is required by many of the major
    framework features, such as the <classname>JobLauncher</classname>,
    <classname>Job</classname>, and <classname>Step</classname>. The batch
    namespace abstracts away many of the implementation details of the
    <classname>JobRepository</classname> implementations and their
    collaborators. However, there are still a few configuration options
    available:</para>

     

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<job-repository id="jobRepository"
    data-source="dataSource"
    transaction-manager="transactionManager"
    isolation-level-for-create="SERIALIZABLE"
    table-prefix="BATCH_"
	max-varchar-length="1000"
/>]]></programlisting>

     

    <para>None of the configuration options listed above are required except
    the id. If they are not set, the defaults shown above will be used. They
    are shown above for awareness purposes. The
    <literal>max-varchar-length</literal> defaults to 2500, which is the
    length of the long <literal>VARCHAR</literal> columns in the <link
    linkend="metaDataSchemaOverview">sample schema scripts</link></para>

     used to store things like exit code descriptions. If you don't modify the schema and you don't use multi-byte characters you shouldn't need to change it. 

    <section id="txConfigForJobRepository">
      <title>Transaction Configuration for the JobRepository</title>

      <para>If the namespace is used, transactional advice will be
      automatically created around the repository. This is to ensure that the
      batch meta data, including state that is necessary for restarts after a
      failure, is persisted correctly. The behavior of the framework is not
      well defined if the repository methods are not transactional. The
      isolation level in the <code>create*</code> method attributes is
      specified separately to ensure that when jobs are launched, if two
      processes are trying to launch the same job at the same time, only one
      will succeed. The default isolation level for that method is
      SERIALIZABLE, which is quite aggressive: READ_COMMITTED would work just
      as well; READ_UNCOMMITTED would be fine if two processes are not likely
      to collide in this way. However, since a call to the
      <classname>create*</classname> method is quite short, it is unlikely
      that the SERIALIZED will cause problems, as long as the database
      platform supports it. However, this can be overridden:</para>

      <para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<job-repository id="jobRepository"
                ]]><emphasis role="bold">isolation-level-for-create="REPEATABLE_READ"</emphasis><![CDATA[ />]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>If the namespace or factory beans aren't used then it is also
      essential to configure the transactional behavior of the repository
      using AOP:</para>

      <para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<aop:config>
    <aop:advisor 
           pointcut="execution(* org.springframework.batch.core..*Repository+.*(..))"/>
    <advice-ref="txAdvice" />
</aop:config>

<tx:advice id="txAdvice" transaction-manager="transactionManager">
    <tx:attributes>
        <tx:method name="*" />
    </tx:attributes>
</tx:advice>]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>This fragment can be used as is, with almost no changes. Remember
      also to include the appropriate namespace declarations and to make sure
      spring-tx and spring-aop (or the whole of spring) are on the
      classpath.</para>
    </section>

     

    <section id="repositoryTablePrefix">
      <title>Changing the Table Prefix</title>

      <para>Another modifiable property of the
      <classname>JobRepository</classname> is the table prefix of the
      meta-data tables. By default they are all prefaced with BATCH_.
      BATCH_JOB_EXECUTION and BATCH_STEP_EXECUTION are two examples. However,
      there are potential reasons to modify this prefix. If the schema names
      needs to be prepended to the table names, or if more than one set of
      meta data tables is needed within the same schema, then the table prefix
      will need to be changed:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job-repository id="jobRepository"
                ]]><emphasis role="bold">table-prefix="SYSTEM.TEST_"</emphasis><![CDATA[ />]]></programlisting>

      <para>Given the above changes, every query to the meta data tables will
      be prefixed with "SYSTEM.TEST_". BATCH_JOB_EXECUTION will be referred to
      as SYSTEM.TEST_JOB_EXECUTION.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Only the table prefix is configurable. The table and column
        names are not.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

     

    <section id="inMemoryRepository">
      <title>In-Memory Repository</title>

      <para>There are scenarios in which you may not want to persist your
      domain objects to the database. One reason may be speed; storing domain
      objects at each commit point takes extra time. Another reason may be
      that you just don't need to persist status for a particular job. For
      this reason, Spring batch provides an in-memory Map version of the job
      repository:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobRepository" 
  class="org.springframework.batch.core.repository.support.MapJobRepositoryFactoryBean">
    <property name="transactionManager" ref="transactionManager"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>

      <para>Note that the in-memory repository is volatile and so does not
      allow restart between JVM instances. It also cannot guarantee that two
      job instances with the same parameters are launched simultaneously, and
      is not suitable for use in a multi-threaded Job, or a locally
      partitioned Step. So use the database version of the repository wherever
      you need those features.</para>

      <para>However it does require a transaction manager to be defined
      because there are rollback semantics within the repository, and because
      the business logic might still be transactional (e.g. RDBMS access). For
      testing purposes many people find the
      <classname>ResourcelessTransactionManager</classname> useful.</para>
    </section>

     

    <section id="nonStandardDatabaseTypesInRepository">
      <title>Non-standard Database Types in a Repository</title>

      <para>If you are using a database platform that is not in the list of
      supported platforms, you may be able to use one of the supported types,
      if the SQL variant is close enough. To do this you can use the raw
      <classname>JobRepositoryFactoryBean</classname> instead of the namespace
      shortcut and use it to set the database type to the closest
      match:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobRepository" class="org...JobRepositoryFactoryBean">
    <property name="databaseType" value="db2"/>
    <property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>

      <para>(The <classname>JobRepositoryFactoryBean</classname> tries to
      auto-detect the database type from the <classname>DataSource</classname>
      if it is not specified.) The major differences between platforms are
      mainly accounted for by the strategy for incrementing primary keys, so
      often it might be necessary to override the
      <literal>incrementerFactory</literal> as well (using one of the standard
      implementations from the Spring Framework).</para>

      <para>If even that doesn't work, or you are not using an RDBMS, then the
      only option may be to implement the various <classname>Dao</classname>
      interfaces that the <classname>SimpleJobRepository</classname> depends
      on and wire one up manually in the normal Spring way.</para>
    </section>

     
  </section>

  <section id="configuringJobLauncher">
    <title>Configuring a JobLauncher</title>

    <para>The most basic implementation of the
    <classname>JobLauncher</classname> interface is the
    <classname>SimpleJobLauncher</classname>. Its only required dependency is
    a <classname>JobRepository</classname>, in order to obtain an
    execution:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobLauncher"
      class="org.springframework.batch.core.launch.support.SimpleJobLauncher">
    <property name="jobRepository" ref="jobRepository" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Once a <link
    linkend="jobExecution"><classname>JobExecution</classname></link> is
    obtained, it is passed to the execute method of
    <classname>Job</classname>, ultimately returning the
    <classname>JobExecution</classname> to the caller:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/job-launcher-sequence-sync.png" scale="90" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/job-launcher-sequence-sync.png" scale="35" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The sequence is straightforward and works well when launched from a
    scheduler. However, issues arise when trying to launch from an HTTP
    request. In this scenario, the launching needs to be done asynchronously
    so that the <classname>SimpleJobLauncher</classname> returns immediately
    to its caller. This is because it is not good practice to keep an HTTP
    request open for the amount of time needed by long running processes such
    as batch. An example sequence is below:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/job-launcher-sequence-async.png" scale="90" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/job-launcher-sequence-async.png" scale="35" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The <classname>SimpleJobLauncher</classname> can easily be
    configured to allow for this scenario by configuring a
    <classname>TaskExecutor</classname>:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobLauncher"
      class="org.springframework.batch.core.launch.support.SimpleJobLauncher">
    <property name="jobRepository" ref="jobRepository" />
    <property name="taskExecutor">
        <bean class="org.springframework.core.task.SimpleAsyncTaskExecutor" />
    </property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Any implementation of the spring <classname>TaskExecutor</classname>
    interface can be used to control how jobs are asynchronously
    executed.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="runningAJob">
    <title>Running a Job</title>

    <para>At a minimum, launching a batch job requires two things: the
    <classname>Job</classname> to be launched and a
    <classname>JobLauncher</classname>. Both can be contained within the same
    context or different contexts. For example, if launching a job from the
    command line, a new JVM will be instantiated for each Job, and thus every
    job will have its own <classname>JobLauncher</classname>. However, if
    running from within a web container within the scope of an
    <classname>HttpRequest</classname>, there will usually be one
    <classname>JobLauncher</classname>, configured for asynchronous job
    launching, that multiple requests will invoke to launch their jobs.</para>

    <section id="runningJobsFromCommandLine">
      <title>Running Jobs from the Command Line</title>

      <para>For users that want to run their jobs from an enterprise
      scheduler, the command line is the primary interface. This is because
      most schedulers (with the exception of Quartz unless using the
      <classname>NativeJob</classname>) work directly with operating system
      processes, primarily kicked off with shell scripts. There are many ways
      to launch a Java process besides a shell script, such as Perl, Ruby, or
      even 'build tools' such as ant or maven. However, because most people
      are familiar with shell scripts, this example will focus on them.</para>

      <section id="commandLineJobRunner">
        <title>The CommandLineJobRunner</title>

        <para>Because the script launching the job must kick off a Java
        Virtual Machine, there needs to be a class with a main method to act
        as the primary entry point. Spring Batch provides an implementation
        that serves just this purpose:
        <classname>CommandLineJobRunner</classname>. It's important to note
        that this is just one way to bootstrap your application, but there are
        many ways to launch a Java process, and this class should in no way be
        viewed as definitive. The <classname>CommandLineJobRunner</classname>
        performs four tasks:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Load the appropriate
            <classname>ApplicationContext</classname></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Parse command line arguments into
            <classname>JobParameters</classname></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Locate the appropriate job based on arguments</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use the <classname>JobLauncher</classname> provided in the
            application context to launch the job.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>All of these tasks are accomplished using only the arguments
        passed in. The following are required arguments:</para>

        <table>
          <title>CommandLineJobRunner arguments</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>jobPath</entry>

                <entry>The location of the XML file that will be used to
                create an <classname>ApplicationContext</classname>. This file
                should contain everything needed to run the complete
                <classname>Job</classname></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>jobName</entry>

                <entry>The name of the job to be run.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>These arguments must be passed in with the path first and the
        name second. All arguments after these are considered to be
        JobParameters and must be in the format of 'name=value':</para>

        <screen><prompt>bash$</prompt><![CDATA[ java CommandLineJobRunner endOfDayJob.xml endOfDay schedule.date(date)=2007/05/05]]></screen>

        <para>In most cases you would want to use a manifest to declare your
        main class in a jar, but for simplicity, the class was used directly.
        This example is using the same 'EndOfDay' example from the <link
        linkend="domain">domain section</link>. The first argument is
        'endOfDayJob.xml', which is the Spring
        <classname>ApplicationContext</classname> containing the
        <classname>Job</classname>. The second argument, 'endOfDay' represents
        the job name. The final argument, 'schedule.date(date)=2007/05/05'
        will be converted into <classname>JobParameters</classname>. An
        example of the XML configuration is below:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="endOfDay">
    <step id="step1" parent="simpleStep" />
</job>

<!-- Launcher details removed for clarity -->
<beans:bean id="jobLauncher"
         class="org.springframework.batch.core.launch.support.SimpleJobLauncher" />]]></programlisting>

        <para>This example is overly simplistic, since there are many more
        requirements to a run a batch job in Spring Batch in general, but it
        serves to show the two main requirements of the
        <classname>CommandLineJobRunner</classname>:
        <classname>Job</classname> and
        <classname>JobLauncher</classname></para>
      </section>

      <section id="exitCodes">
        <title>ExitCodes</title>

        <para>When launching a batch job from the command-line, an enterprise
        scheduler is often used. Most schedulers are fairly dumb and work only
        at the process level. This means that they only know about some
        operating system process such as a shell script that they're invoking.
        In this scenario, the only way to communicate back to the scheduler
        about the success or failure of a job is through return codes. A
        return code is a number that is returned to a scheduler by the process
        that indicates the result of the run. In the simplest case: 0 is
        success and 1 is failure. However, there may be more complex
        scenarios: If job A returns 4 kick off job B, and if it returns 5 kick
        off job C. This type of behavior is configured at the scheduler level,
        but it is important that a processing framework such as Spring Batch
        provide a way to return a numeric representation of the 'Exit Code'
        for a particular batch job. In Spring Batch this is encapsulated
        within an <classname>ExitStatus</classname>, which is covered in more
        detail in Chapter 5. For the purposes of discussing exit codes, the
        only important thing to know is that an
        <classname>ExitStatus</classname> has an exit code property that is
        set by the framework (or the developer) and is returned as part of the
        <classname>JobExecution</classname> returned from the
        <classname>JobLauncher</classname>. The
        <classname>CommandLineJobRunner</classname> converts this string value
        to a number using the <classname>ExitCodeMapper</classname>
        interface:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface ExitCodeMapper {

    public int intValue(String exitCode);

}]]></programlisting>

        <para>The essential contract of an
        <classname>ExitCodeMapper</classname> is that, given a string exit
        code, a number representation will be returned. The default
        implementation used by the job runner is the SimpleJvmExitCodeMapper
        that returns 0 for completion, 1 for generic errors, and 2 for any job
        runner errors such as not being able to find a
        <classname>Job</classname> in the provided context. If anything more
        complex than the 3 values above is needed, then a custom
        implementation of the <classname>ExitCodeMapper</classname> interface
        must be supplied. Because the
        <classname>CommandLineJobRunner</classname> is the class that creates
        an <classname>ApplicationContext</classname>, and thus cannot be
        'wired together', any values that need to be overwritten must be
        autowired. This means that if an implementation of
        <classname>ExitCodeMapper</classname> is found within the BeanFactory,
        it will be injected into the runner after the context is created. All
        that needs to be done to provide your own
        <classname>ExitCodeMapper</classname> is to declare the implementation
        as a root level bean and ensure that it is part of the
        <classname>ApplicationContext</classname> that is loaded by the
        runner.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="runningJobsFromWebContainer">
      <title>Running Jobs from within a Web Container</title>

      <para>Historically, offline processing such as batch jobs have been
      launched from the command-line, as described above. However, there are
      many cases where launching from an <classname>HttpRequest</classname> is
      a better option. Many such use cases include reporting, ad-hoc job
      running, and web application support. Because a batch job by definition
      is long running, the most important concern is ensuring to launch the
      job asynchronously:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/launch-from-request.png"
                       scale="75" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/launch-from-request.png"
                       scale="35" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para>The controller in this case is a Spring MVC controller. More
      information on Spring MVC can be found here: <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/mvc.html">http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/mvc.html</ulink>.
      The controller launches a <classname>Job</classname> using a
      <classname>JobLauncher</classname> that has been configured to launch
      <link linkend="configureJobLauncher">asynchronously</link>, which
      immediately returns a <classname>JobExecution</classname>. The
      <classname>Job</classname> will likely still be running, however, this
      nonblocking behaviour allows the controller to return immediately, which
      is required when handling an <classname>HttpRequest</classname>. An
      example is below:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[@Controller
public class JobLauncherController {

    @Autowired
    JobLauncher jobLauncher;

    @Autowired
    Job job;

    @RequestMapping("/jobLauncher.html")
    public void handle() throws Exception{
        jobLauncher.run(job, new JobParameters());
    }
}]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="advancedMetaData">
    <title>Advanced Meta-Data Usage</title>

    <para>So far, both the JobLauncher and JobRepository interfaces have been
    discussed. Together, they represent simple launching of a job, and basic
    CRUD operations of batch domain objects:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/job-repository.png"
                   scale="60" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/job-repository.png"
                   scale="50" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>A <classname>JobLauncher</classname> uses the
    <classname>JobRepository</classname> to create new
    <classname>JobExecution</classname> objects and run them.
    <classname>Job</classname> and <classname>Step</classname> implementations
    later use the same <classname>JobRepository</classname> for basic updates
    of the same executions during the running of a <classname>Job</classname>.
    The basic operations suffice for simple scenarios, but in a large batch
    environment with hundreds of batch jobs and complex scheduling
    requirements, more advanced access of the meta data is required:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/job-repository-advanced.png"
                   role="70" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/job-repository-advanced.png"
                   scale="45" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The <classname>JobExplorer</classname> and
    <classname>JobOperator</classname> interfaces, which will be discussed
    below, add additional functionality for querying and controlling the meta
    data.</para>

    <section id="queryingRepository">
      <title>Querying the Repository</title>

      <para>The most basic need before any advanced features is the ability to
      query the repository for existing executions. This functionality is
      provided by the <classname>JobExplorer</classname> interface:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface JobExplorer {

    List<JobInstance> getJobInstances(String jobName, int start, int count);

    JobExecution getJobExecution(Long executionId);

    StepExecution getStepExecution(Long jobExecutionId, Long stepExecutionId);

    JobInstance getJobInstance(Long instanceId);

    List<JobExecution> getJobExecutions(JobInstance jobInstance);

    Set<JobExecution> findRunningJobExecutions(String jobName);
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>As is evident from the method signatures above,
      <classname>JobExplorer</classname> is a read-only version of the
      <classname>JobRepository</classname>, and like the
      <classname>JobRepository</classname>, it can be easily configured via a
      factory bean:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobExplorer" class="org.spr...JobExplorerFactoryBean" 
      p:dataSource-ref="dataSource" />]]></programlisting>

      <para><link linkend="repositoryTablePrefix">Earlier in this
      chapter</link>, it was mentioned that the table prefix of the
      <classname>JobRepository</classname> can be modified to allow for
      different versions or schemas. Because the
      <classname>JobExplorer</classname> is working with the same tables, it
      too needs the ability to set a prefix:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobExplorer" class="org.spr...JobExplorerFactoryBean" 
      p:dataSource-ref="dataSource" ]]><emphasis role="bold">p:tablePrefix="BATCH_" </emphasis><![CDATA[/>]]></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JobRegistry</title>

      <para>A JobRegistry (and its parent interface JobLocator) is not
      mandatory, but it can be useful if you want to keep track of which jobs
      are available in the context. It is also useful for collecting jobs
      centrally in an application context when they have been created
      elsewhere (e.g. in child contexts). Custom JobRegistry implementations
      can also be used to manipulate the names and other properties of the
      jobs that are registered. There is only one implementation provided by
      the framework and this is based on a simple map from job name to job
      instance. It is configured simply like this:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobRegistry" class="org.spr...MapJobRegistry" />]]></programlisting>

      <para>There are two ways to populate a JobRegistry automatically: using
      a bean post processor and using a registrar lifecycle component. These
      two mechanisms are described in the following sections.</para>

      <section>
        <title>JobRegistryBeanPostProcessor</title>

        <para>This is a bean post-processor that can register all jobs as they
        are created:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobRegistryBeanPostProcessor" class="org.spr...JobRegistryBeanPostProcessor">
    <property name="jobRegistry" ref="jobRegistry"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>

        <para>Athough it is not strictly necessary the post-processor in the
        example has been given an id so that it can be included in child
        contexts (e.g. as a parent bean definition) and cause all jobs created
        there to also be regsistered automatically.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>AutomaticJobRegistrar</title>

        <para>This is a lifecycle component that creates child contexts and
        registers jobs from those contexts as they are created. One advantage
        of doing this is that, while the job names in the child contexts still
        have to be globally unique in the registry, their dependencies can
        have "natural" names. So for example, you can create a set of XML
        configuration files each having only one <classname>Job</classname>,
        but all having different definitions of an
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> with the same bean name, e.g.
        "reader". If all those files were imported into the same context, the
        reader definitions would clash and override one another, but with the
        automatic regsistrar this is avoided. This makes it easier to
        integrate jobs contributed from separate modules of an
        application.</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean class="org.spr...AutomaticJobRegistrar">
   <property name="applicationContextFactories">
      <bean class="org.spr...ClasspathXmlApplicationContextsFactoryBean">
         <property name="resources" value="classpath*:/config/job*.xml" />
      </bean>
   </property>
   <property name="jobLoader">
      <bean class="org.spr...DefaultJobLoader">
         <property name="jobRegistry" ref="jobRegistry" />
      </bean>
   </property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>

        <para>The registrar has two mandatory properties, one is an array of
        <classname>ApplicationContextFactory</classname> (here created from a
        convenient factory bean), and the other is a
        <classname>JobLoader</classname>. The <classname>JobLoader</classname>
        is responsible for managing the lifecycle of the child contexts and
        registering jobs in the <classname>JobRegistry</classname>.</para>

        <para>The <classname>ApplicationContextFactory</classname> is
        responsible for creating the child context and the most common usage
        would be as above using a
        <classname>ClassPathXmlApplicationContextFactory</classname>. One of
        the features of this factory is that by default it copies some of the
        configuration down from the parent context to the child. So for
        instance you don't have to re-define the
        <classname>PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer</classname> or AOP
        configuration in the child, if it should be the same as the
        parent.</para>

        <para>The <classname>AutomaticJobRegistrar</classname> can be used in
        conjunction with a <classname>JobRegistryBeanPostProcessor</classname>
        if desired (as long as the <classname>DefaultJobLoader</classname> is
        used as well). For instance this might be desirable if there are jobs
        defined in the main parent context as well as in the child
        locations.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="JobOperator">
      <title>JobOperator</title>

      <para>As previously discussed, the <classname>JobRepository</classname>
      provides CRUD operations on the meta-data, and the
      <classname>JobExplorer</classname> provides read-only operations on the
      meta-data. However, those operations are most useful when used together
      to perform common monitoring tasks such as stopping, restarting, or
      summarizing a Job, as is commonly done by batch operators. Spring Batch
      provides for these types of operations via the
      <classname>JobOperator</classname> interface:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface JobOperator {

    List<Long> getExecutions(long instanceId) throws NoSuchJobInstanceException;

    List<Long> getJobInstances(String jobName, int start, int count) 
          throws NoSuchJobException;

    Set<Long> getRunningExecutions(String jobName) throws NoSuchJobException;

    String getParameters(long executionId) throws NoSuchJobExecutionException;

    Long start(String jobName, String parameters) 
          throws NoSuchJobException, JobInstanceAlreadyExistsException;

    Long restart(long executionId) 
          throws JobInstanceAlreadyCompleteException, NoSuchJobExecutionException,
                  NoSuchJobException, JobRestartException;

    Long startNextInstance(String jobName) 
          throws NoSuchJobException, JobParametersNotFoundException, JobRestartException, 
                 JobExecutionAlreadyRunningException, JobInstanceAlreadyCompleteException;

    boolean stop(long executionId) 
          throws NoSuchJobExecutionException, JobExecutionNotRunningException;

    String getSummary(long executionId) throws NoSuchJobExecutionException;

    Map<Long, String> getStepExecutionSummaries(long executionId) 
          throws NoSuchJobExecutionException;

    Set<String> getJobNames();

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>The above operations represent methods from many different
      interfaces, such as <classname>JobLauncher</classname>,
      <classname>JobRepository</classname>,
      <classname>JobExplorer</classname>, and
      <classname>JobRegistry</classname>. For this reason, the provided
      implementation of <classname>JobOperator</classname>,
      <classname>SimpleJobOperator</classname>, has many dependencies:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="jobOperator" class="org.spr...SimpleJobOperator">
    <property name="jobExplorer">
        <bean class="org.spr...JobExplorerFactoryBean">
            <property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource" />
        </bean>
    </property>
    <property name="jobRepository" ref="jobRepository" />
    <property name="jobRegistry" ref="jobRegistry" />
    <property name="jobLauncher" ref="jobLauncher" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>

      <note>
        If you set the table prefix on the job repository, don't forget to set it on the job explorer as well.
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="JobParametersIncrementer">
      <title>JobParametersIncrementer</title>

      <para>Most of the methods on <classname>JobOperator</classname> are
      self-explanatory, and more detailed explanations can be found on the
      <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring-batch/apidocs/org/springframework/batch/core/launch/JobOperator.html">javadoc
      of the interface</ulink>. However, the
      <methodname>startNextInstance</methodname> method is worth noting. This
      method will always start a new instance of a <classname>Job</classname>.
      This can be extremely useful if there are serious issues in a
      <classname>JobExecution</classname> and the <classname>Job</classname>
      needs to be started over again from the beginning. Unlike
      <classname>JobLauncher</classname> though, which requires a new
      <classname>JobParameters</classname> object that will trigger a new
      <classname>JobInstance</classname> if the parameters are different from
      any previous set of parameters, the
      <methodname>startNextInstance</methodname> method will use the
      <classname>JobParametersIncrementer</classname> tied to the
      <classname>Job</classname> to force the <classname>Job</classname> to a
      new instance:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface JobParametersIncrementer {

    JobParameters getNext(JobParameters parameters);

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>The contract of <classname>JobParametersIncrementer</classname> is
      that, given a <link
      linkend="jobParameters"><classname>JobParameters</classname></link>
      object, it will return the 'next' <classname>JobParameters</classname>
      object by incrementing any necessary values it may contain. This
      strategy is useful because the framework has no way of knowing what
      changes to the <classname>JobParameters</classname> make it the 'next'
      instance. For example, if the only value in
      <classname>JobParameters</classname> is a date, and the next instance
      should be created, should that value be incremented by one day? Or one
      week (if the job is weekly for instance)? The same can be said for any
      numerical values that help to identify the <classname>Job</classname>,
      as shown below:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[public class SampleIncrementer implements JobParametersIncrementer {
  
    public JobParameters getNext(JobParameters parameters) { 
        if (parameters==null || parameters.isEmpty()) {
            return new JobParametersBuilder().addLong("run.id", 1L).toJobParameters();
        }
        long id = parameters.getLong("run.id",1L) + 1;
        return new JobParametersBuilder().addLong("run.id", id).toJobParameters();
    }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>In this example, the value with a key of 'run.id' is used to
      discriminate between <classname>JobInstances</classname>. If the
      <classname>JobParameters</classname> passed in is null, it can be
      assumed that the <classname>Job</classname> has never been run before
      and thus its initial state can be returned. However, if not, the old
      value is obtained, incremented by one, and returned. An incrementer can
      be associated with <classname>Job</classname> via the 'incrementer'
      attribute in the namespace:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[<job id="footballJob" ]]><emphasis role="bold">incrementer="sampleIncrementer"</emphasis><![CDATA[>
    ...
</job>]]></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="stoppingAJob">
      <title>Stopping a Job</title>

      <para>One of the most common use cases of
      <classname>JobOperator</classname> is gracefully stopping a
      <classname>Job:</classname></para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[Set<Long> executions = jobOperator.getRunningExecutions("sampleJob");
jobOperator.stop(executions.iterator().next());  ]]></programlisting>

      <para>The shutdown is not immediate, since there is no way to force
      immediate shutdown, especially if the execution is currently in
      developer code that the framework has no control over, such as a
      business service. However, as soon as control is returned back to the
      framework, it will set the status of the current
      <classname>StepExecution</classname> to
      <classname>BatchStatus.STOPPED</classname>, save it, then do the same
      for the <classname>JobExecution</classname> before finishing.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Aborting a Job</title>

      <para>A job execution which is <classname>FAILED</classname> can be
      restarted (if the Job is restartable). A job execution whose status is
      <classname>ABORTED</classname> will not be restarted by the framework.
      The <classname>ABORTED</classname> status is also used in step
      executions to mark them as skippable in a restarted job execution: if a
      job is executing and encounters a step that has been marked
      <classname>ABORTED</classname> in the previous failed job execution, it
      will move on to the next step (as determined by the job flow definition
      and the step execution exit status).</para>

      <para>If the process died (<literal>"kill -9"</literal> or server
      failure) the job is, of course, not running, but the JobRepository has
      no way of knowing because no-one told it before the process died. You
      have to tell it manually that you know that the execution either failed
      or should be considered aborted (change its status to
      <classname>FAILED</classname> or <classname>ABORTED</classname>) - it's
      a business decision and there is no way to automate it. Only change the
      status to <classname>FAILED</classname> if it is not restartable, or if
      you know the restart data is valid. There is a utility in Spring Batch
      Admin <classname>JobService</classname> to abort a job execution.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
