<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="jsr-352" xreflabel="JSR-352 Support">
	<title>JSR-352 Support</title>

	<para>As of Spring Batch 3.0 support for JSR-352 has been fully implemented. This section is not a replacement for
        the spec itself and instead, intends to explain how the JSR-352 specific concepts apply to Spring Batch.
        Additional information on JSR-352 can be found via the
        JCP here: <ulink url="https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=352">https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=352</ulink></para>

    <section id="jsrGeneralNotes">
        <title>General Notes Spring Batch and JSR-352</title>

        <para>Spring Batch and JSR-352 are structurally the same.  They both have jobs that are made up of steps.  They
            both have readers, processors, writers, and listeners.  However, their interactions are subtly different.
            For example, the <code>org.springframework.batch.core.SkipListener#onSkipInWrite(S item, Throwable t)</code>
            within Spring Batch receives two parameters: the item that was skipped and the Exception that caused the
            skip.  The JSR-352 version of the same method
            (<classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.listener.SkipWriteListener#onSkipWriteItem(List&lt;Object&gt; items, Exception ex)</classname>)
            also receives two parameters.  However the first one is a <classname>List</classname> of all the items
            within the current chunk with the second being the <classname>Exception</classname> that caused the skip.
            Because of these differences, it is important to note that there are two paths to execute a job within
            Spring Batch: either a traditional Spring Batch job or a JSR-352 based job.  While the use of Spring Batch
            artifacts (readers, writers, etc) will work within a job configured via JSR-352's JSL and executed via the
            <classname>JsrJobOperator</classname>, they will behave according to the rules of JSR-352.  It is also
            important to note that batch artifacts that have been developed against the JSR-352 interfaces will not work
            within a traditional Spring Batch job.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencyInjection">
        <title>Dependency Injection</title>

        <para>JSR-352 is based heavily on the Spring Batch programming model.  As such, while not explicitly requiring a
            formal dependency injection implementation, DI of some kind implied.  Spring Batch supports all three
            methods for loading batch artifacts defined by JSR-352:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Implementation Specific Loader - Spring Batch is built upon Spring and so supports Spring
                    dependency injection within JSR-352 batch jobs.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Archive Loader - JSR-352 defines the existing of a batch.xml file that provides mappings between a
                    logical name and a class name.  This file must be found within the /META-INF/ directory if it is
                    used.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Thread Context Class Loader - JSR-352 allows configurations to specify batch artifact
                    implementations in their JSL by providing the fully qualified class name inline.  Spring Batch
                    supports this as well in JSR-352 configured jobs.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To use Spring dependency injection within a JSR-352 based batch job consists of configuring batch
            artifacts using a Spring application context as beans.  Once the beans have been defined, a job can refer to
            them as it would any bean defined within the batch.xml.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
                              http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
                              http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee
                              http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/jobXML_1_0.xsd"&gt;

    &lt;!-- javax.batch.api.Batchlet implementation --&gt;
    &lt;bean id="fooBatchlet" class="io.spring.FooBatchlet"&gt;
            &lt;property name="prop" value="bar"/&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;

    &lt;!-- Job is defined using the JSL schema provided in JSR-352 --&gt;
    &lt;job id="fooJob" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee" version="1.0"&gt;
        &lt;step id="step1"&gt;
            &lt;batchlet ref="fooBatchlet"/&gt;
        &lt;/step&gt;
    &lt;/job&gt;
&lt;/beans&gt;
        </programlisting>

        <para>The assembly of Spring contexts (imports, etc) works with JSR-352 jobs just as it would with any other
            Spring based application.  The only difference with a JSR-352 based job is that the entry point for the
            context definition will be the job definition found in /META-INF/batch-jobs/.</para>

        <para>To use the thread context class loader approach, all you need to do is provide the fully qualified class
            name as the ref.  It is important to note that when using this approach or the batch.xml approach, the class
            referenced requires a no argument constructor which will be used to create the bean.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;job id="fooJob" xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee" version="1.0"&gt;
    &lt;step id="step1" &gt;
        &lt;batchlet ref="io.spring.FooBatchlet" /&gt;
    &lt;/step&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;
        </programlisting>

    </section>

    <section id="jsrJobProperties">
        <title>Batch Properties</title>

        <section id="jsrPropertySupport">
            <title>Property Support</title>

            <para>JSR-352 allows for properties to be defined at the Job, Step and batch artifact level by way of
                configuration in the JSL. Batch properties are configured at each level in the following way:</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;properties&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;propertyName1&quot; value=&quot;propertyValue1&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;propertyName2&quot; value=&quot;propertyValue2&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/properties&gt;</programlisting>
            <para>
                Properties may be configured on any batch artifact.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="jsrBatchPropertyAnnotation">
            <title><classname>@BatchProperty</classname> annotation</title>

            <para>Properties are referenced in batch artifacts by annotating class fields with the
                <classname>@BatchProperty</classname> and <classname>@Inject</classname> annotations (both annotations
                are required by the spec). As defined by JSR-352, fields for properties must be String typed. Any type
                conversion is up to the implementing developer to perform.</para>

            <para>An <classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.ItemReader</classname> artifact could be configured with a
                properties block such as the one described above and accessed as such:</para>
                <programlisting language="java">public class MyItemReader extends AbstractItemReader {
    @Inject
    @BatchProperty
    private String propertyName1;

    ...
}</programlisting>
            <para>
                The value of the field "propertyName1" will be "propertyValue1"</para>
        </section>
        <section id="jsrPropertySubstitution">
            <title>Property Substitution</title>

            <para>Property substitution is provided by way of operators and simple conditional expressions. The general
                usage is #{operator['key']}.</para>
            <para>Supported operators:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>jobParameters - access job parameter values that the job was started/restarted with.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>jobProperties - access properties configured at the job level of the JSL.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>systemProperties - access named system properties.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>partitionPlan - access named property from the partition plan of a partitioned step.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <programlisting>#{jobParameters['unresolving.prop']}?:#{systemProperties['file.separator']}</programlisting>
            <para>
                The left hand side of the assignment is the expected value, the right hand side is the default value. In
                this example, the result will resolve to a value of the system property file.separator as
                #{jobParameters['unresolving.prop']} is assumed to not be resolvable. If neither expressions can be
                resolved, an empty String will be returned. Multiple conditions can be used, which are separated by a
                ';'.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrProcessingModels">
        <title>Processing Models</title>

        <para>JSR-352 provides the same two basic processing models that Spring Batch does:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Item based processing - Using an <classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.ItemReader</classname>, an
                        optional <classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.ItemProcessor</classname>, and an
                        <classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.ItemWriter</classname>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Task based processing - Using a <classname>javax.batch.api.Batchlet</classname>
                        implementation.  This processing model is the same as the
                        <classname>org.springframework.batch.core.step.tasklet.Tasklet</classname> based processing
                        currently available.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Item based processing</title>
            <para>Item based processing in this context is a chunk size being set by the number of items read by an
                <classname>ItemReader</classname>.  To configure a step this way, specify the
                <classname>item-count</classname> (which defaults to 10) and optionally configure the
                <classname>checkpoint-policy</classname> as item (this is the default).
            </para>
            <programlisting language="xml">...
&lt;step id="step1"&gt;
    &lt;chunk checkpoint-policy="item" item-count="3"&gt;
        &lt;reader ref="fooReader"/&gt;
        &lt;processor ref="fooProcessor"/&gt;
        &lt;writer ref="fooWriter"/&gt;
    &lt;/chunk&gt;
&lt;/step&gt;
...</programlisting>
            <para>
                If item based checkpointing is chosen, an additional attribute <classname>time-limit</classname> is
                supported.  This sets a time limit for how long the number of items specified has to be processed.  If
                the timeout is reached, the chunk will complete with however many items have been read by then
                regardless of what the <classname>item-count</classname> is configured to be.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Custom checkpointing</title>
            <para>JSR-352 calls the process around the commit interval within a step "checkpointing".  Item based
                checkpointing is one approach as mentioned above.  However, this will not be robust enough in many
                cases.  Because of this, the spec allows for the implementation of a custom checkpointing algorithm by
                implementing the <classname>javax.batch.api.chunk.CheckpointAlgorithm</classname> interface.  This
                functionality is functionally the same as Spring Batch's custom completion policy.  To use an
                implementation of <classname>CheckpointAlgorithm</classname>, configure your step with the custom
                <classname>checkpoint-policy</classname> as shown below where fooCheckpointer refers to an
                implementation of <classname>CheckpointAlgorithm</classname>.
            </para>
            <programlisting language="xml">...
&lt;step id="step1"&gt;
    &lt;chunk checkpoint-policy="custom"&gt;
        &lt;checkpoint-algorithm ref="fooCheckpointer"/&gt;
        &lt;reader ref="fooReader"/&gt;
        &lt;processor ref="fooProcessor"/&gt;
        &lt;writer ref="fooWriter"/&gt;
    &lt;/chunk&gt;
&lt;/step&gt;
...</programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrRunningAJob">
        <title>Running a job</title>

        <para>The entrance to executing a JSR-352 based job is through the
            <classname>javax.batch.operations.JobOperator</classname>.  Spring Batch provides our own implementation to
            this interface (<classname>org.springframework.batch.core.jsr.launch.JsrJobOperator</classname>).  This
            implementation is loaded via the <classname>javax.batch.runtime.BatchRuntime</classname>.  Launching a
            JSR-352 based batch job is implemented as follows:</para>

        <programlisting language="java">
JobOperator jobOperator = BatchRuntime.getJobOperator();
long jobExecutionId = jobOperator.start("fooJob", new Properties());
        </programlisting>

        <para>The above code does the following:</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bootstraps a base ApplicationContext - In order to provide batch functionality, the framework
                        needs some infrastructure bootstrapped.  This occurs once per JVM.  The components that are
                        bootstrapped are similar to those provided by <classname>@EnableBatchProcessing</classname>.
                        Specific details can be found in the javadoc for the <classname>JsrJobOperator</classname>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Loads an <classname>ApplicationContext</classname> for the job requested - In the example
                        above, the framework will look in /META-INF/batch-jobs for a file named fooJob.xml and load a
                        context that is a child of the shared context mentioned previously.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Launch the job - The job defined within the context will be executed asynchronously.  The
                        <classname>JobExecution</classname>'s id will be returned.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <note><para>All JSR-352 based batch jobs are executed asynchronously.</para></note>

        <para>When <classname>JobOperator#start</classname> is called using <classname>SimpleJobOperator</classname>,
            Spring Batch determines if the call is an initial run or a retry of a previously executed run.  Using the
            JSR-352 based <classname>JobOpeator#start(String jobXMLName, Properties jobParameters)</classname>, the
            framework will always create a new <classname>JobInstance</classname> (JSR-352 job parameters are
            non-identifying).  In order to restart a job, a call to
            <classname>JobOperator#restart(long executionId, Properties restartParameters)</classname> is required.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrContexts">
        <title>Contexts</title>

        <para>JSR-352 defines two context objects that are used to interact with the meta-data of a job or step from
            within a batch artifact: <classname>javax.batch.runtime.context.JobContext</classname> and
            <classname>javax.batch.runtime.context.StepContext</classname>.  Both of these are available in any step
            level artifact (<classname>Batchlet</classname>, <classname>ItemReader</classname>, etc) with the
            <classname>JobContext</classname> being available to job level artifacts as well
            (<classname>JobListener</classname> for example).</para>

        <para>To obtain a reference to the <classname>JobContext</classname> or <classname>StepContext</classname>
            within the current scope, simply use the <classname>@Inject</classname> annotation:</para>

        <programlisting language="java">@Inject
JobContext jobContext;
        </programlisting>

        <note>
            <title>@Autowire for JSR-352 contexts</title>
            <para>Using Spring's @Autowire is not supported for the injection of these contexts.</para>
        </note>

        <para>In Spring Batch, the <classname>JobContext</classname> and <classname>StepContext</classname> wrap their
            corresponding execution objects (<classname>JobExecution</classname> and
            <classname>StepExecution</classname> respectively).  Data stored via
            <classname>StepContext#persistent#setPersistentUserData(Serializable data)</classname> is stored in the
            Spring Batch <classname>StepExecution#executionContext</classname>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrStepFlow">
        <title>Step Flow</title>
        <para>Within a JSR-352 based job, the flow of steps works similarly as it does within Spring Batch.
            However, there are a few subtle differences:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Decision's are steps - In a regular Spring Batch job, a decision is a state that does not
                        have an independent <classname>StepExecution</classname> or any of the rights and
                        responsibilities that go along with being a full step..  However, with JSR-352, a decision
                        is a step just like any other and will behave just as any other steps (transactionality,
                        it gets a <classname>StepExecution</classname>, etc).  This means that they are treated the
                        same as any other step on restarts as well.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><classname>next</classname> attribute and step transitions - In a regular job, these are
                        allowed to appear together in the same step.  JSR-352 allows them to both be used in the
                        same step with the next attribute taking precedence in evaluation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Transition element ordering - In a standard Spring Batch job, transition elements are
                        sorted from most specific to least specific and evaluated in that order.  JSR-352 jobs
                        evaluate transition elements in the order they are specified in the XML.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrScaling">
        <title>Scaling a JSR-352 batch job</title>

        <para>Traditional Spring Batch jobs have four ways of scaling (the last two capable of being executed across
            multiple JVMs):
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Split - Running multiple steps in parallel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Multiple threads - Executing a single step via multiple threads.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partitioning - Dividing the data up for parallel processing (master/slave).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Remote Chunking - Executing the processor piece of logic remotely.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>JSR-352 provides two options for scaling batch jobs.  Both options support only a single JVM:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Split - Same as Spring Batch</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partitioning - Conceptually the same as Spring Batch however implemented slightly different.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <section id="jsrPartitioning">
            <title>Partitioning</title>
            <para>Conceptually, partitioning in JSR-352 is the same as it is in Spring Batch.  Meta-data is provided
                to each slave to identify the input to be processed with the slaves reporting back to the master the
                results upon completion.  However, there are some important differences:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Partitioned <classname>Batchlet</classname> - This will run multiple instances of the
                            configured <classname>Batchlet</classname> on multiple threads.  Each instance will have
                            it's own set of properties as provided by the JSL or the
                            <classname>PartitionPlan</classname></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><classname>PartitionPlan</classname> - With Spring Batch's partitioning, an
                            <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> is provided for each partition.  With JSR-352, a
                            single <classname>javax.batch.api.partition.PartitionPlan</classname> is provided with an
                            array of <classname>Properties</classname> providing the meta-data for each partition.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><classname>PartitionMapper</classname> - JSR-352 provides two ways to generate partition
                            meta-data.  One is via the JSL (partition properties).  The second is via an implementation
                            of the <classname>javax.batch.api.partition.PartitionMapper</classname> interface.
                            Functionally, this interface is similar to the
                            <classname>org.springframework.batch.core.partition.support.Partitioner</classname>
                            interface provided by Spring Batch in that it provides a way to programmaticaly generate
                            meta-data for partitioning.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><classname>StepExecution</classname>s - In Spring Batch, partitioned steps are run as
                            master/slave. Within JSR-352, the same configuration occurs.  However, the slave steps do
                            not get official <classname>StepExecution</classname>s.  Because of that, calls to
                            <classname>JsrJobOperator#getStepExecutions(long jobExecutionId)</classname> will only
                            return the <classname>StepExecution</classname> for the master.  <note><para>The child
                            <classname>StepExecution</classname>s still exist in the job repository and are available
                            via the <classname>JobExplorer</classname> and Spring Batch Admin.</para></note>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Compensating logic - Since Spring Batch implements the master/slave logic of
                            partitioning using steps, <classname>StepExecutionListener</classname>s can be used to
                            handle compensating logic if something goes wrong.  However, since the slaves JSR-352
                            provides a collection of other components for the ability to provide compensating logic when
                            errors occur and to dynamically set the exit status.  These components include the following:
                            <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                                <tgroup cols="2">
                                    <colspec align="left"/>
                                    <colspec align="left"/>
                                    <tbody>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry>
                                                <emphasis role="bold">Artifact Interface</emphasis>
                                            </entry>
                                            <entry>
                                                <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
                                            </entry>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry><classname>javax.batch.api.partition.PartitionCollector</classname></entry>
                                            <entry>Provides a way for slave steps to send information back to the
                                                master.  There is one instance per slave thread.</entry>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry><classname>javax.batch.api.partition.PartitionAnalyzer</classname></entry>
                                            <entry>End point that receives the information collected by the
                                                <classname>PartitionCollector</classname> as well as the resulting
                                                statuses from a completed partition.</entry>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry><classname>javax.batch.api.partition.PartitionReducer</classname></entry>
                                            <entry>Provides the ability to provide compensating logic for a partitioned
                                                step.</entry>
                                        </row>
                                    </tbody>
                                </tgroup>
                            </informaltable>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="jsrTesting">
        <title>Testing</title>

        <para>Since all JSR-352 based jobs are executed asynchronously, it can be difficult to determine when a job has
            completed.  To help with testing, Spring Batch provides the
            <classname>org.springframework.batch.core.jsr.JsrTestUtils</classname>.  This utility class provides the
            ability to start a job and restart a job and wait for it to complete.  Once the job completes, the
            associated <classname>JobExecution</classname> is returned.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>
