<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="readersAndWriters">
  <title>ItemReaders and ItemWriters</title>

  <para>All batch processing can be described in its most simple form as
  reading in large amounts of data, performing some type of calculation or
  transformation, and writing the result out. Spring Batch provides three key
  interfaces to help perform bulk reading and writing:
  <classname>ItemReader</classname>, <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> and
  <classname>ItemWriter</classname>.</para>

  <section id="itemReader">
    <title id="infrastructure.1">ItemReader</title>

    <para>Although a simple concept, an <classname>ItemReader</classname> is
    the means for providing data from many different types of input. The most
    general examples include: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flat File- Flat File Item Readers read lines of data from a
          flat file that typically describe records with fields of data
          defined by fixed positions in the file or delimited by some special
          character (e.g. Comma).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XML - XML ItemReaders process XML independently of
          technologies used for parsing, mapping and validating objects. Input
          data allows for the validation of an XML file against an XSD
          schema.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Database - A database resource is accessed to return
          resultsets which can be mapped to objects for processing. The
          default SQL ItemReaders invoke a <classname>RowMapper</classname> to
          return objects, keep track of the current row if restart is
          required, store basic statistics, and provide some transaction
          enhancements that will be explained later.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>There are many more possibilities, but we'll focus on the
    basic ones for this chapter. A complete list of all available ItemReaders
    can be found in Appendix A.</para>

    <para><classname>ItemReader</classname> is a basic interface for generic
    input operations:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemReader&lt;T&gt; {

    T read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException, ParseException;

}</programlisting>

    <para>The <methodname>read</methodname> method defines the most essential
    contract of the <classname>ItemReader</classname>; calling it returns one
    Item or null if no more items are left. An item might represent a line in
    a file, a row in a database, or an element in an XML file. It is generally
    expected that these will be mapped to a usable domain object (i.e. Trade,
    Foo, etc) but there is no requirement in the contract to do so.</para>

    <para>It is expected that implementations of the
    <classname>ItemReader</classname> interface will be forward only. However,
    if the underlying resource is transactional (such as a JMS queue) then
    calling read may return the same logical item on subsequent calls in a
    rollback scenario. It is also worth noting that a lack of items to process
    by an <classname>ItemReader</classname> will not cause an exception to be
    thrown. For example, a database <classname>ItemReader</classname> that is
    configured with a query that returns 0 results will simply return null on
    the first invocation of <methodname>read</methodname>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="itemWriter">
    <title id="infrastructure.1.4">ItemWriter</title>

    <para><classname>ItemWriter</classname> is similar in functionality to an
    <classname>ItemReader</classname>, but with inverse operations. Resources
    still need to be located, opened and closed but they differ in that an
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> writes out, rather than reading in. In
    the case of databases or queues these may be inserts, updates, or sends.
    The format of the serialization of the output is specific to each batch
    job.</para>

    <para>As with <classname>ItemReader</classname>,
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> is a fairly generic interface:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; {

    void write(List&lt;? extends T&gt; items) throws Exception;

}</programlisting>

    <para>As with <methodname>read</methodname> on
    <classname>ItemReader</classname>, <methodname>write</methodname> provides
    the basic contract of <classname>ItemWriter</classname>; it will attempt
    to write out the list of items passed in as long as it is open. Because it
    is generally expected that items will be 'batched' together into a chunk
    and then output, the interface accepts a list of items, rather than an
    item by itself. After writing out the list, any flushing that may be
    necessary can be performed before returning from the write method. For
    example, if writing to a Hibernate DAO, multiple calls to write can be
    made, one for each item. The writer can then call close on the hibernate
    Session before returning.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="itemProcessor">
    <title>ItemProcessor</title>

    <para>The <classname>ItemReader</classname> and
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> interfaces are both very useful for
    their specific tasks, but what if you want to insert business logic before
    writing? One option for both reading and writing is to use the composite
    pattern: create an <classname>ItemWriter</classname> that contains another
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname>, or an <classname>ItemReader</classname>
    that contains another <classname>ItemReader</classname>. For
    example:</para>

    <programlisting>public class CompositeItemWriter&lt;T&gt; implements ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; {

    ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; itemWriter;

    public CompositeItemWriter(ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; itemWriter) {
        this.itemWriter = itemWriter;
    }

    public void write(List&lt;? extends T&gt; items) throws Exception {
        //Add business logic here
       itemWriter.write(item);
    }

    public void setDelegate(ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; itemWriter){
        this.itemWriter = itemWriter;
    }
}</programlisting>

    <para>The class above contains another <classname>ItemWriter</classname>
    to which it delgates after having provided some business logic. This
    pattern could easily be used for an <classname>ItemReader</classname> as
    well, perhaps to obtain more reference data based upon the input that was
    provided by the main <classname>ItemReader</classname>. It is also useful
    if you need to control the call to <classname>write</classname> yourself.
    However, if you only want to 'transform' the item passed in for writing
    before it is actually written, there isn't much need to call
    <methodname>write</methodname> yourself: you just want to modify the item.
    For this scenario, Spring Batch provides the
    <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> interface:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemProcessor&lt;I, O&gt; {

    O process(I item) throws Exception;
}</programlisting>

    <para>An <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> is very simple; given one
    object, transform it and return another. The provided object may or may
    not be of the same type. The point is that business logic may be applied
    within process, and is completely up to the developer to create. An
    <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> can be wired directly into a step,
    For example, assuming an <classname>ItemReader</classname> provides a
    class of type Foo, and it needs to be converted to type Bar before being
    written out. An <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> can be written that
    performs the conversion:</para>

    <programlisting>public class Foo {}

public class Bar {
    public Bar(Foo foo) {}
}

public class FooProcessor implements ItemProcessor&lt;Foo,Bar&gt;{
    public Bar process(Foo foo) throws Exception {
        //Perform simple transformation, convert a Foo to a Bar
        return new Bar(foo);
    }
}

public class BarWriter implements ItemWriter&lt;Bar&gt;{
    public void write(List&lt;? extends Bar&gt; bars) throws Exception {
        //write bars
    }
}</programlisting>

    <para>In the very simple example above, there is a class
    <classname>Foo</classname>, a class <classname>Bar</classname>, and a
    class <classname>FooProcessor</classname> that adheres to the
    <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> interface. The transformation is
    simple, but any type of transformation could be done here. The
    <classname>BarWriter</classname> will be used to write out
    <classname>Bar</classname> objects, throwing an exception if any other
    type is provided. Similarly, the <classname>FooProcessor</classname> will
    throw an exception if anything but a <classname>Foo</classname> is
    provided. The <classname>FooProcessor</classname> can then be injected
    into a <classname>Step</classname>:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;job id="ioSampleJob"&gt;
    &lt;step name="step1"&gt;
        &lt;tasklet&gt;
            &lt;chunk reader="fooReader" processor="fooProcessor" writer="barWriter" 
                   commit-interval="2"/&gt;
        &lt;/tasklet&gt;
    &lt;/step&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;</programlisting>

    <section id="chainingItemProcessors">
      <title>Chaining ItemProcessors</title>

      <para>Performing a single transformation is useful in many scenarios,
      but what if you want to 'chain' together multiple
      <classname>ItemProcessor</classname>s? This can be accomplished using
      the composite pattern mentioned previously. To update the previous,
      single transformation, example, <classname>Foo</classname> will be
      transformed to <classname>Bar</classname>, which will be transformed to
      <classname>Foobar</classname> and written out:</para>

      <programlisting>public class Foo {}

public class Bar {
    public Bar(Foo foo) {}
}

public class Foobar{
    public Foobar(Bar bar) {}
}

public class FooProcessor implements ItemProcessor&lt;Foo,Bar&gt;{
    public Bar process(Foo foo) throws Exception {
        //Perform simple transformation, convert a Foo to a Bar
        return new Bar(foo);
    }
}

public class BarProcessor implements ItemProcessor&lt;Bar,FooBar&gt;{
    public FooBar process(Bar bar) throws Exception {
        return new Foobar(bar);
    }
}

public class FoobarWriter implements ItemWriter&lt;FooBar&gt;{
    public void write(List&lt;? extends FooBar&gt; items) throws Exception {
        //write items
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>A <classname>FooProcessor</classname> and
      <classname>BarProcessor</classname> can be 'chained' together to give
      the resultant <classname>Foobar</classname>:</para>

      <programlisting>CompositeItemProcessor&lt;Foo,Foobar&gt; compositeProcessor = 
                                      new CompositeItemProcessor&lt;Foo,Foobar&gt;();
List itemProcessors = new ArrayList();
itemProcessors.add(new FooTransformer());
itemProcessors.add(new BarTransformer());
compositeProcessor.setDelegates(itemProcessors);</programlisting>

      <para>Just as with the previous example, the composite processor can be
      configured into the <classname>Step</classname>:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;job id="ioSampleJob"&gt;
    &lt;step name="step1"&gt;
        &lt;tasklet&gt;
            &lt;chunk reader="fooReader" processor="compositeProcessor" writer="foobarWriter" 
                   commit-interval="2"/&gt;
        &lt;/tasklet&gt;
    &lt;/step&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;

&lt;bean id="compositeItemProcessor" 
      class="org.springframework.batch.item.support.CompositeItemProcessor"&gt;
    &lt;property name="delegates"&gt;
        &lt;list&gt;
            &lt;bean class="..FooProcessor" /&gt;
            &lt;bean class="..BarProcessor" /&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="filiteringRecords">
      <title>Filtering Records</title>

      <para>One typical use for an item processor is to filter out records
      before they are passed to the ItemWriter. Filtering is an action
      distinct from skipping; skipping indicates that a record is invalid
      whereas filtering simply indicates that a record should not be
      written.</para>

      <para>For example, consider a batch job that reads a file containing
      three different types of records: records to insert, records to update,
      and records to delete. If record deletion is not supported by the
      system, then we would not want to send any "delete" records to the
      <classname>ItemWriter</classname>. But, since these records are not
      actually bad records, we would want to filter them out, rather than
      skip. As a result, the ItemWriter would receive only "insert" and
      "update" records.</para>

      <para>To filter a record, one simply returns "null" from the
      <classname>ItemProcessor</classname>. The framework will detect that the
      result is "null" and avoid adding that item to the list of records
      delivered to the <classname>ItemWriter</classname>. As usual, an
      exception thrown from the <classname>ItemProcessor</classname> will
      result in a skip.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="itemStream">
    <title>ItemStream</title>

    <para>Both <classname>ItemReader</classname>s and
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname>s serve their individual purposes well,
    but there is a common concern among both of them that necessitates another
    interface. In general, as part of the scope of a batch job, readers and
    writers need to be opened, closed, and require a mechanism for persisting
    state:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemStream {

    void open(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException;

    void update(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException;
  
    void close() throws ItemStreamException;
}</programlisting>

    <para>Before describing each method, we should mention the
    <classname>ExecutionContext</classname>. Clients of an
    <classname>ItemReader</classname> that also implement
    <classname>ItemStream</classname> should call
    <methodname>open</methodname> before any calls to
    <methodname>read</methodname> in order to open any resources such as files
    or to obtain connections. A similar restriction applies to an
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> that implements
    <classname>ItemStream</classname>. As mentioned in Chapter 2, if expected
    data is found in the <classname>ExecutionContext</classname>, it may be
    used to start the <classname>ItemReader</classname> or
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> at a location other than its initial
    state. Conversely, <methodname>close</methodname> will be called to ensure
    that any resources allocated during <methodname>open</methodname> will be
    released safely. <methodname>update</methodname> is called primarily to
    ensure that any state currently being held is loaded into the provided
    <classname>ExecutionContext</classname>. This method will be called before
    committing, to ensure that the current state is persisted in the database
    before commit.</para>

    <para>In the special case where the client of an
    <classname>ItemStream</classname> is a <classname>Step</classname> (from
    the Spring Batch Core), an <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> is
    created for each <classname>StepExecution</classname> to allow users to
    store the state of a particular execution, with the expectation that it
    will be returned if the same <classname>JobInstance</classname> is started
    again. For those familiar with Quartz, the semantics are very similar to a
    Quartz <classname>JobDataMap</classname>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="delegatePatternAndRegistering">
    <title>The Delegate Pattern and Registering with the Step</title>

    <para>Note that the <classname>CompositeItemWriter</classname> is an
    example of the delegation pattern, which is common in Spring Batch. The
    delegates themselves might implement callback interfaces like
    <classname>ItemStream</classname> or <classname>StepListener</classname>.
    If they do, and they are being used in conjunction with Spring Batch Core
    as part of a <classname>Step</classname> in a <classname>Job</classname>,
    then they almost certainly need to be registered manually with the
    <classname>Step</classname>. A reader, writer, or processor that is
    directly wired into the Step will be registered automatically if it
    implements <classname>ItemStream</classname> or a
    <classname>StepListener</classname> interface. But because the delegates
    are not known to the <classname>Step</classname>, they need to be injected
    as listeners or streams (or both if appropriate):</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;job id="ioSampleJob"&gt;
    &lt;step name="step1"&gt;
        &lt;tasklet&gt;
            &lt;chunk reader="fooReader" processor="fooProcessor" writer="compositeItemWriter" 
                   commit-interval="2"&gt;
                    &lt;streams&gt;
                    &lt;stream ref="barWriter" /&gt;
                &lt;/streams&gt;
            &lt;/chunk&gt;
        &lt;/tasklet&gt;
    &lt;/step&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;

&lt;bean id="compositeItemWriter" class="...CompositeItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="delegate" ref="barWriter" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="barWriter" class="...BarWriter" /&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="flatFiles">
    <title id="infrastructure.1.2">Flat Files</title>

    <para>One of the most common mechanisms for interchanging bulk data has
    always been the flat file. Unlike XML, which has an agreed upon standard
    for defining how it is structured (XSD), anyone reading a flat file must
    understand ahead of time exactly how the file is structured. In general,
    all flat files fall into two types: Delimited and Fixed Length. Delimited
    files are those in which fields are separated by a delimiter, such as a
    comma. Fixed Length files have fields that are a set length.</para>

    <section id="fieldSet">
      <title>The FieldSet</title>

      <para>When working with flat files in Spring Batch, regardless of
      whether it is for input or output, one of the most important classes is
      the <classname>FieldSet</classname>. Many architectures and libraries
      contain abstractions for helping you read in from a file, but they
      usually return a String or an array of Strings. This really only gets
      you halfway there. A <classname>FieldSet</classname> is Spring Batch’s
      abstraction for enabling the binding of fields from a file resource. It
      allows developers to work with file input in much the same way as they
      would work with database input. A <classname>FieldSet</classname> is
      conceptually very similar to a Jdbc <classname>ResultSet</classname>.
      FieldSets only require one argument, a <classname>String</classname>
      array of tokens. Optionally, you can also configure in the names of the
      fields so that the fields may be accessed either by index or name as
      patterned after <classname>ResultSet</classname>:</para>

      <programlisting>String[] tokens = new String[]{"foo", "1", "true"};
FieldSet fs = new DefaultFieldSet(tokens);
String name = fs.readString(0);
int value = fs.readInt(1);
boolean booleanValue = fs.readBoolean(2);</programlisting>

      <para>There are many more options on the <classname>FieldSet</classname>
      interface, such as <classname>Date</classname>, long,
      <classname>BigDecimal</classname>, etc. The biggest advantage of the
      <classname>FieldSet</classname> is that it provides consistent parsing
      of flat file input. Rather than each batch job parsing differently in
      potentially unexpected ways, it can be consistent, both when handling
      errors caused by a format exception, or when doing simple data
      conversions.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="flatFileItemReader">
      <title id="infrastructure.1.2.1">FlatFileItemReader</title>

      <para>A flat file is any type of file that contains at most
      two-dimensional (tabular) data. Reading flat files in the Spring Batch
      framework is facilitated by the class
      <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname>, which provides basic
      functionality for reading and parsing flat files. The two most important
      required dependencies of <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname> are
      <classname>Resource</classname> and <classname>LineMapper.
      </classname>The <classname>LineMapper</classname> interface will be
      explored more in the next sections. The resource property represents a
      Spring Core <classname>Resource</classname>. Documentation explaining
      how to create beans of this type can be found in <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/resources.html"><citetitle>Spring
      Framework, Chapter 4.Resources</citetitle></ulink>. Therefore, this
      guide will not go into the details of creating
      <classname>Resource</classname> objects. However, a simple example of a
      file system resource can be found below: <programlisting>Resource resource = new FileSystemResource("resources/trades.csv");</programlisting></para>

      <para>In complex batch environments the directory structures are often
      managed by the EAI infrastructure where drop zones for external
      interfaces are established for moving files from ftp locations to batch
      processing locations and vice versa. File moving utilities are beyond
      the scope of the spring batch architecture but it is not unusual for
      batch job streams to include file moving utilities as steps in the job
      stream. It is sufficient that the batch architecture only needs to know
      how to locate the files to be processed. Spring Batch begins the process
      of feeding the data into the pipe from this starting point. However,
      <ulink
      url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-integration"><citetitle>Spring
      Integration</citetitle></ulink> provides many of these types of
      services.</para>

      <para>The other properties in <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname>
      allow you to further specify how your data will be interpreted: <table>
          <title>FlatFileItemReader Properties</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="center" />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Property</entry>

                <entry align="center">Type</entry>

                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">comments</entry>

                <entry align="left">String[]</entry>

                <entry align="left">Specifies line prefixes that indicate
                comment rows</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">encoding</entry>

                <entry align="left">String</entry>

                <entry align="left">Specifies what text encoding to use -
                default is "ISO-8859-1"</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">lineMapper</entry>

                <entry align="left">LineMapper</entry>

                <entry align="left">Converts a <classname>String</classname>
                to an <classname>Object</classname> representing the
                item.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">linesToSkip</entry>

                <entry align="left">int</entry>

                <entry align="left">Number of lines to ignore at the top of
                the file</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">recordSeparatorPolicy</entry>

                <entry align="left">RecordSeparatorPolicy</entry>

                <entry align="left">Used to determine where the line endings
                are and do things like continue over a line ending if inside a
                quoted string.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">resource</entry>

                <entry align="left">Resource</entry>

                <entry align="left">The resource from which to read.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">skippedLinesCallback</entry>

                <entry align="left">LineCallbackHandler</entry>

                <entry align="left">Interface which passes the raw line
                content of the lines in the file to be skipped. If linesToSkip
                is set to 2, then this interface will be called twice.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">strict</entry>

                <entry align="left">boolean</entry>

                <entry align="left">In strict mode, the reader will throw an
                exception on ExecutionContext if the input resource does not
                exist.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>

      <section id="lineMapper">
        <title>LineMapper</title>

        <para>As with <classname>RowMapper</classname>, which takes a low
        level construct such as <classname>ResultSet</classname> and returns
        an <classname>Object</classname>, flat file processing requires the
        same construct to convert a <classname>String</classname> line into an
        <classname>Object</classname>:<programlisting>public interface LineMapper&lt;T&gt; {

    T mapLine(String line, int lineNumber) throws Exception;

}</programlisting></para>

        <para>The basic contract is that, given the current line and the line
        number with which it is associated, the mapper should return a
        resulting domain object. This is similar to
        <classname>RowMapper</classname> in that each line is associated with
        its line number, just as each row in a
        <classname>ResultSet</classname> is tied to its row number. This
        allows the line number to be tied to the resulting domain object for
        identity comparison or for more informative logging. However, unlike
        <classname>RowMapper</classname>, the
        <classname>LineMapper</classname> is given a raw line which, as
        discussed above, only gets you halfway there. The line must be
        tokenized into a <classname>FieldSet</classname>, which can then be
        mapped to an object, as described below.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="lineTokenizer">
        <title>LineTokenizer</title>

        <para>An abstraction for turning a line of input into a line into a
        <classname>FieldSet</classname> is necessary because there can be many
        formats of flat file data that need to be converted to a
        <classname>FieldSet</classname>. In Spring Batch, this interface is
        the <classname>LineTokenizer</classname>:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface LineTokenizer {
  
    FieldSet tokenize(String line);

}</programlisting>

        <para>The contract of a <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> is such
        that, given a line of input (in theory the
        <classname>String</classname> could encompass more than one line), a
        <classname>FieldSet</classname> representing the line will be
        returned. This <classname>FieldSet</classname> can then be passed to a
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>. Spring Batch contains the
        following <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> implementations:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><classname>DelmitedLineTokenizer</classname> - Used for
            files where fields in a record are separated by a delimiter. The
            most common delimiter is a comma, but pipes or semicolons are
            often used as well.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><classname>FixedLengthTokenizer</classname> - Used for files
            where fields in a record are each a 'fixed width'. The width of
            each field must be defined for each record type.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><classname>PatternMatchingCompositeLineTokenizer</classname>
            - Determines which among a list of
            <classname>LineTokenizer</classname>s should be used on a
            particular line by checking against a pattern.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="fieldSetMapper">
        <title>FieldSetMapper</title>

        <para>The <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> interface defines a
        single method, <methodname>mapFieldSet</methodname>, which takes a
        <classname>FieldSet</classname> object and maps its contents to an
        object. This object may be a custom DTO, a domain object, or a simple
        array, depending on the needs of the job. The
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> is used in conjunction with the
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> to translate a line of data from
        a resource into an object of the desired type:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface FieldSetMapper&lt;T&gt; {
  
    T mapFieldSet(FieldSet fieldSet);

}</programlisting>

        <para>The pattern used is the same as the
        <classname>RowMapper</classname> used by
        <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="defaultLineMapper">
        <title>DefaultLineMapper</title>

        <para>Now that the basic interfaces for reading in flat files have
        been defined, it becomes clear that three basic steps are
        required:<orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Read one line from the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Pass the string line into the
              <methodname>LineTokenizer#tokenize</methodname>() method, in
              order to retrieve a <classname>FieldSet</classname>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Pass the <classname>FieldSet</classname> returned from
              tokenizing to a <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>, returning
              the result from the <methodname>ItemReader#read</methodname>()
              method.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>

        <para>The two interfaces described above represent two separate tasks:
        converting a line into a <classname>FieldSet</classname>, and mapping
        a <classname>FieldSet</classname> to a domain object. Because the
        input of a <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> matches the input of
        the <classname>LineMapper</classname> (a line), and the output of a
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> matches the output of the
        <classname>LineMapper</classname>, a default implementation that uses
        both a <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> and
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> is provided. The
        <classname>DefaultLineMapper</classname> represents the behavior most
        users will need:</para>

        <programlisting>public class DefaultLineMapper&lt;T&gt; implements LineMapper&lt;T&gt;, InitializingBean {

    private LineTokenizer tokenizer;

    private FieldSetMapper&lt;T&gt; fieldSetMapper;

    public T mapLine(String line, int lineNumber) throws Exception {
        <emphasis role="bold">return fieldSetMapper.mapFieldSet(tokenizer.tokenize(line));</emphasis>
    }

    public void setLineTokenizer(LineTokenizer tokenizer) {
        this.tokenizer = tokenizer;
    }

    public void setFieldSetMapper(FieldSetMapper&lt;T&gt; fieldSetMapper) { 
        this.fieldSetMapper = fieldSetMapper;
    }
}</programlisting>

        <para>The above functionality is provided in a default implementation,
        rather than being built into the reader itself (as was done in
        previous versions of the framework) in order to allow users greater
        flexibility in controlling the parsing process, especially if access
        to the raw line is needed.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="simpleDelimitedFileReadingExample">
        <title>Simple Delimited File Reading Example</title>

        <para>The following example will be used to illustrate this using an
        actual domain scenario. This particular batch job reads in football
        players from the following file:<programlisting>ID,lastName,firstName,position,birthYear,debutYear
"AbduKa00,Abdul-Jabbar,Karim,rb,1974,1996",
"AbduRa00,Abdullah,Rabih,rb,1975,1999",
"AberWa00,Abercrombie,Walter,rb,1959,1982",
"AbraDa00,Abramowicz,Danny,wr,1945,1967",
"AdamBo00,Adams,Bob,te,1946,1969",
"AdamCh00,Adams,Charlie,wr,1979,2003"        </programlisting></para>

        <para>The contents of this file will be mapped to the following
        <classname>Player</classname> domain object: <programlisting>public class Player implements Serializable {
        
    private String ID; 
    private String lastName; 
    private String firstName; 
    private String position; 
    private int birthYear; 
    private int debutYear;
        
    public String toString() {
        return "PLAYER:ID=" + ID + ",Last Name=" + lastName + 
            ",First Name=" + firstName + ",Position=" + position + 
            ",Birth Year=" + birthYear + ",DebutYear=" + 
            debutYear;
    }
   
    // setters and getters...
}
          </programlisting></para>

        <para>In order to map a <classname>FieldSet</classname> into a
        <classname>Player</classname> object, a
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> that returns players needs to be
        defined:</para>

        <para><programlisting>protected static class PlayerFieldSetMapper implements FieldSetMapper&lt;Player&gt; {
    public Player mapFieldSet(FieldSet fieldSet) {
        Player player = new Player();

        player.setID(fieldSet.readString(0));
        player.setLastName(fieldSet.readString(1));
        player.setFirstName(fieldSet.readString(2)); 
        player.setPosition(fieldSet.readString(3));
        player.setBirthYear(fieldSet.readInt(4));
        player.setDebutYear(fieldSet.readInt(5));

        return player;
    }
}   </programlisting></para>

        <para>The file can then be read by correctly constructing a
        <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname> and calling
        <methodname>read</methodname>:</para>

        <programlisting>FlatFileItemReader&lt;Player&gt; itemReader = new FlatFileItemReader&lt;Player&gt;();
itemReader.setResource(new FileSystemResource("resources/players.csv"));
//DelimitedLineTokenizer defaults to comma as its delimiter
LineMapper&lt;Player&gt; lineMapper = new DefaultLineMapper&lt;Player&gt;();
lineMapper.setLineTokenizer(new DelimitedLineTokenizer());
lineMapper.setFieldSetMapper(new PlayerFieldSetMapper());
itemReader.setLineMapper(lineMapper);
itemReader.open(new ExecutionContext());
Player player = itemReader.read();</programlisting>

        <para>Each call to <methodname>read</methodname> will return a new
        Player object from each line in the file. When the end of the file is
        reached, null will be returned.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="mappingFieldsByName">
        <title>Mapping Fields by Name</title>

        <para>There is one additional piece of functionality that is allowed
        by both <classname>DelimitedLineTokenizer</classname> and
        <classname>FixedLengthTokenizer</classname> that is similar in
        function to a Jdbc <classname>ResultSet</classname>. The names of the
        fields can be injected into either of these
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> implementations to increase the
        readability of the mapping function. First, the column names of all
        fields in the flat file are injected into the tokenizer:</para>

        <para><programlisting>tokenizer.setNames(new String[] {"ID", "lastName","firstName","position","birthYear","debutYear"});          </programlisting></para>

        <para>A <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> can use this information
        as follows:</para>

        <para><programlisting>public class PlayerMapper implements FieldSetMapper&lt;Player&gt; {
    public Player mapFieldSet(FieldSet fs) {
                        
       if(fs == null){
           return null;
       }
                        
       Player player = new Player();
       player.setID(fs.readString(<emphasis role="bold">"ID"</emphasis>));
       player.setLastName(fs.readString(<emphasis role="bold">"lastName"</emphasis>));
       player.setFirstName(fs.readString(<emphasis role="bold">"firstName"</emphasis>));
       player.setPosition(fs.readString(<emphasis role="bold">"position"</emphasis>));
       player.setDebutYear(fs.readInt(<emphasis role="bold">"debutYear"</emphasis>));
       player.setBirthYear(fs.readInt(<emphasis role="bold">"birthYear"</emphasis>));
                       
       return player;
   }
}</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section id="beanWrapperFieldSetMapper">
        <title>Automapping FieldSets to Domain Objects</title>

        <para>For many, having to write a specific
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> is equally as cumbersome as
        writing a specific <classname>RowMapper</classname> for a
        <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>. Spring Batch makes this easier by
        providing a <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> that automatically
        maps fields by matching a field name with a setter on the object using
        the JavaBean specification. Again using the football example, the
        <classname>BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper</classname> configuration looks
        like the following:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="fieldSetMapper"
      class="org.springframework.batch.item.file.mapping.BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper"&gt;
    &lt;property name="prototypeBeanName" value="player" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="player"
      class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Player"
      scope="prototype" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>For each entry in the <classname>FieldSet</classname>, the
        mapper will look for a corresponding setter on a new instance of the
        <classname>Player</classname> object (for this reason, prototype scope
        is required) in the same way the Spring container will look for
        setters matching a property name. Each available field in the
        <classname>FieldSet</classname> will be mapped, and the resultant
        <classname>Player</classname> object will be returned, with no code
        required.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="fixedLengthFileFormats">
        <title>Fixed Length File Formats</title>

        <para>So far only delimited files have been discussed in much detail,
        however, they represent only half of the file reading picture. Many
        organizations that use flat files use fixed length formats. An example
        fixed length file is below:</para>

        <programlisting>UK21341EAH4121131.11customer1
UK21341EAH4221232.11customer2
UK21341EAH4321333.11customer3
UK21341EAH4421434.11customer4
UK21341EAH4521535.11customer5</programlisting>

        <para>While this looks like one large field, it actually represent 4
        distinct fields:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>ISIN: Unique identifier for the item being order - 12
            characters long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Quantity: Number of this item being ordered - 3 characters
            long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Price: Price of the item - 5 characters long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Customer: Id of the customer ordering the item - 9
            characters long.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>When configuring the
        <classname>FixedLengthLineTokenizer</classname>, each of these lengths
        must be provided in the form of ranges:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="fixedLengthLineTokenizer"
      class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.transform.FixedLengthTokenizer"&gt;
    &lt;property name="names" value="ISIN,Quantity,Price,Customer" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="columns" value="1-12, 13-15, 16-20, 21-29" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Because the <classname>FixedLengthLineTokenizer</classname> uses
        the same <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> interface as discussed
        above, it will return the same <classname>FieldSet</classname> as if a
        delimiter had been used. This allows the same approaches to be used in
        handling its output, such as using the
        <classname>BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper</classname>.</para>

        <para><note>
            <para>Supporting the above syntax for ranges requires that a
            specialized property editor,
            <classname>RangeArrayPropertyEditor</classname>, be configured in
            the <classname>ApplicationContext</classname>. However, this bean
            is automatically declared in an
            <classname>ApplicationContext</classname> where the batch
            namespace is used.</para>
          </note></para>
      </section>

      <section id="prefixMatchingLineMapper">
        <title>Multiple Record Types within a Single File</title>

        <para>All of the file reading examples up to this point have all made
        a key assumption for simplicity's sake: all of the records in a file
        have the same format. However, this may not always be the case. It is
        very common that a file might have records with different formats that
        need to be tokenized differently and mapped to different objects. The
        following excerpt from a file illustrates this:</para>

        <programlisting>USER;Smith;Peter;;T;20014539;F
LINEA;1044391041ABC037.49G201XX1383.12H
LINEB;2134776319DEF422.99M005LI</programlisting>

        <para>In this file we have three types of records, "USER", "LINEA",
        and "LINEB". A "USER" line corresponds to a User object. "LINEA" and
        "LINEB" both correspond to Line objects, though a "LINEA" has more
        information than a "LINEB".</para>

        <para>The <classname>ItemReader </classname>will read each line
        individually, but we must specify different
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> and
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname> objects so that the
        <classname>ItemWriter</classname> will receive the correct items. The
        <classname>PatternMatchingCompositeLineMapper</classname> makes this
        easy by allowing maps of patterns to
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname>s and patterns to
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>s to be configured:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="orderFileLineMapper"
      class="org.spr...PatternMatchingCompositeLineMapper"&gt;
    &lt;property name="tokenizers"&gt;
        &lt;map&gt;
            &lt;entry key="USER*" value-ref="userTokenizer" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="LINEA*" value-ref="lineATokenizer" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="LINEB*" value-ref="lineBTokenizer" /&gt;
        &lt;/map&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="fieldSetMappers"&gt;
        &lt;map&gt;
            &lt;entry key="USER*" value-ref="userFieldSetMapper" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="LINE*" value-ref="lineFieldSetMapper" /&gt;
        &lt;/map&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, "LINEA" and "LINEB" have separate
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname>s but they both use the same
        <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>.</para>

        <para>The <classname>PatternMatchingCompositeLineMapper</classname>
        makes use of the <classname>PatternMatcher</classname>'s
        <classname>match</classname> method in order to select the correct
        delegate for each line. The <classname>PatternMatcher</classname>
        allows for two wildcard characters with special meaning: the question
        mark ("?") will match exactly one character, while the asterisk ("*")
        will match zero or more characters. Note that in the configuration
        above, all patterns end with an asterisk, making them effectively
        prefixes to lines. The <classname>PatternMatcher</classname> will
        always match the most specific pattern possible, regardless of the
        order in the configuration. So if "LINE*" and "LINEA*" were both
        listed as patterns, "LINEA" would match pattern "LINEA*", while
        "LINEB" would match pattern "LINE*". Additionally, a single asterisk
        ("*") can serve as a default by matching any line not matched by any
        other pattern.</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;entry key="*" value-ref="defaultLineTokenizer" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>There is also a
        <classname>PatternMatchingCompositeLineTokenizer</classname> that can
        be used for tokenization alone.</para>

        <para>It is also common for a flat file to contain records that each
        span multiple lines. To handle this situation, a more complex strategy
        is required. A demonstration of this common pattern can be found in
        <xref linkend="multiLineRecords" />.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="exceptionHandlingInFlatFiles">
        <title>Exception Handling in Flat Files</title>

        <para>There are many scenarios when tokenizing a line may cause
        exceptions to be thrown. Many flat files are imperfect and contain
        records that aren't formatted correctly. Many users choose to skip
        these erroneous lines, logging out the issue, original line, and line
        number. These logs can later be inspected manually or by another batch
        job. For this reason, Spring Batch provides a hierarchy of exceptions
        for handling parse exceptions:
        <classname>FlatFileParseException</classname> and
        <classname>FlatFileFormatException</classname>.
        <classname>FlatFileParseException</classname> is thrown by the
        <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname> when any errors are
        encountered while trying to read a file.
        <classname>FlatFileFormatException</classname> is thrown by
        implementations of the <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> interface,
        and indicates a more specific error encountered while
        tokenizing.</para>

        <section id="incorrectTokenCountException">
          <title>IncorrectTokenCountException</title>

          <para>Both <classname>DelimitedLineTokenizer</classname> and
          <classname>FixedLengthLineTokenizer</classname> have the ability to
          specify column names that can be used for creating a
          <classname>FieldSet</classname>. However, if the number of column
          names doesn't match the number of columns found while tokenizing a
          line the <classname>FieldSet</classname> can't be created, and a
          <classname>IncorrectTokenCountException</classname> is thrown, which
          contains the number of tokens encountered, and the number
          expected:</para>

          <programlisting>tokenizer.setNames(new String[] {"A", "B", "C", "D"});
  
try{
    tokenizer.tokenize("a,b,c");
}
catch(IncorrectTokenCountException e){
    assertEquals(4, e.getExpectedCount());
    assertEquals(3, e.getActualCount());
}</programlisting>

          <para>Because the tokenizer was configured with 4 column names, but
          only 3 tokens were found in the file, an
          <classname>IncorrectTokenCountException</classname> was
          thrown.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="incorrectLineLengthException">
          <title>IncorrectLineLengthException</title>

          <para>Files formatted in a fixed length format have additional
          requirements when parsing because, unlike a delimited format, each
          column must strictly adhere to its predefined width. If the total
          line length doesn't add up to the widest value of this column, an
          exception is thrown:</para>

          <programlisting>tokenizer.setColumns(new Range[] { new Range(1, 5), 
                                   new Range(6, 10), 
                                   new Range(11, 15) });
try {
    tokenizer.tokenize("12345");
    fail("Expected IncorrectLineLengthException");
}
catch (IncorrectLineLengthException ex) {
    assertEquals(15, ex.getExpectedLength());
    assertEquals(5, ex.getActualLength());
}</programlisting>

          <para>The configured ranges for the tokenizer above are: 1-5, 6-10,
          and 11-15, thus the total length of the line expected is 15.
          However, in this case a line of length 5 was passed in, causing an
          <classname>IncorrectLineLengthException</classname> to be thrown.
          Throwing an exception here rather than only mapping the first column
          allows the processing of the line to fail earlier, and with more
          information than it would if it failed while trying to read in
          column 2 in a <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>. However, there
          are scenarios where the length of the line isn't always constant.
          For this reason, validation of line length can be turned off via the
          'strict' property:</para>

          <programlisting>tokenizer.setColumns(new Range[] { new Range(1, 5), new Range(6, 10) });
<emphasis role="bold">tokenizer.setStrict(false);</emphasis>
FieldSet tokens = tokenizer.tokenize("12345");
assertEquals("12345", tokens.readString(0));
assertEquals("", tokens.readString(1));</programlisting>

          <para>The above example is almost identical to the one before it,
          except that tokenizer.setStrict(false) was called. This setting
          tells the tokenizer to not enforce line lengths when tokenizing the
          line. A <classname>FieldSet</classname> is now correctly created and
          returned. However, it will only contain empty tokens for the
          remaining values.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="flatFileItemWriter">
      <title>FlatFileItemWriter</title>

      <para>Writing out to flat files has the same problems and issues that
      reading in from a file must overcome. A step must be able to write out
      in either delimited or fixed length formats in a transactional
      manner.</para>

      <section id="lineAggregator">
        <title>LineAggregator</title>

        <para>Just as the <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> interface is
        necessary to take an item and turn it into a
        <classname>String</classname>, file writing must have a way to
        aggregate multiple fields into a single string for writing to a file.
        In Spring Batch this is the
        <classname>LineAggregator</classname>:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface LineAggregator&lt;T&gt; {

    public String aggregate(T item);

}</programlisting>

        <para>The <classname>LineAggregator</classname> is the opposite of a
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname>.
        <classname>LineTokenizer</classname> takes a
        <classname>String</classname> and returns a
        <classname>FieldSet</classname>, whereas
        <classname>LineAggregator</classname> takes an
        <classname>item</classname> and returns a
        <classname>String</classname>.</para>

        <section id="PassThroughLineAggregator">
          <title>PassThroughLineAggregator</title>

          <para>The most basic implementation of the LineAggregator interface
          is the <classname>PassThroughLineAggregator</classname>, which
          simply assumes that the object is already a string, or that its
          string representation is acceptable for writing:</para>

          <programlisting>public class PassThroughLineAggregator&lt;T&gt; implements LineAggregator&lt;T&gt; {

    public String aggregate(T item) {
        return item.toString();
    }
}</programlisting>

          <para>The above implementation is useful if direct control of
          creating the string is required, but the advantages of a
          <classname>FlatFileItemWriter</classname>, such as transaction and
          restart support, are necessary.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="SimplifiedFileWritingExample">
        <title>Simplified File Writing Example</title>

        <para>Now that the <classname>LineAggregator</classname> interface and
        its most basic implementation,
        <classname>PassThroughLineAggregator</classname>, have been defined,
        the basic flow of writing can be explained:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The object to be written is passed to the
            <classname>LineAggregator</classname> in order to obtain a
            <classname>String</classname>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The returned <classname>String</classname> is written to the
            configured file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The following excerpt from the
        <classname>FlatFileItemWriter</classname> expresses this in
        code:</para>

        <programlisting>public void write(T item) throws Exception {
    write(lineAggregator.aggregate(item) + LINE_SEPARATOR);
}</programlisting>

        <para>A simple configuration would look like the following:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.spr...FlatFileItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="resource" value="file:target/test-outputs/output.txt" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="lineAggregator"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.spr...PassThroughLineAggregator"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section id="FieldExtractor">
        <title>FieldExtractor</title>

        <para>The above example may be useful for the most basic uses of a
        writing to a file. However, most users of the
        <classname>FlatFileItemWriter</classname> will have a domain object
        that needs to be written out, and thus must be converted into a line.
        In file reading, the following was required:<orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Read one line from the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Pass the string line into the
              <methodname>LineTokenizer#tokenize</methodname>() method, in
              order to retrieve a <classname>FieldSet</classname></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Pass the <classname>FieldSet</classname> returned from
              tokenizing to a <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>, returning
              the result from the <methodname>ItemReader#read</methodname>()
              method</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>

        <para>File writing has similar, but inverse steps:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pass the item to be written to the writer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>convert the fields on the item into an array</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>aggregate the resulting array into a line</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Because there is no way for the framework to know which fields
        from the object need to be written out, a
        <classname>FieldExtractor</classname> must be written to accomplish
        the task of turning the item into an array:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface FieldExtractor&lt;T&gt; {

    Object[] extract(T item);

}</programlisting>

        <para>Implementations of the <classname>FieldExtractor</classname>
        interface should create an array from the fields of the provided
        object, which can then be written out with a delimiter between the
        elements, or as part of a field-width line.</para>

        <section id="PassThroughFieldExtractor">
          <title>PassThroughFieldExtractor</title>

          <para>There are many cases where a collection, such as an array,
          <classname>Collection</classname>, or
          <classname>FieldSet</classname>, needs to be written out.
          "Extracting" an array from a one of these collection types is very
          straightforward: simply convert the collection to an array.
          Therefore, the <classname>PassThroughFieldExtractor</classname>
          should be used in this scenario. It should be noted, that if the
          object passed in is not a type of collection, then the
          <classname>PassThroughFieldExtractor</classname> will return an
          array containing solely the item to be extracted.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="BeanWrapperFieldExtractor">
          <title>BeanWrapperFieldExtractor</title>

          <para>As with the <classname>BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper</classname>
          described in the file reading section, it is often preferable to
          configure how to convert a domain object to an object array, rather
          than writing the conversion yourself. The
          <classname>BeanWrapperFieldExtractor</classname> provides just this
          type of functionality:</para>

          <programlisting>BeanWrapperFieldExtractor&lt;Name&gt; extractor = new BeanWrapperFieldExtractor&lt;Name&gt;();
extractor.setNames(new String[] { "first", "last", "born" });

String first = "Alan";
String last = "Turing";
int born = 1912;

Name n = new Name(first, last, born);
Object[] values = extractor.extract(n);

assertEquals(first, values[0]);
assertEquals(last, values[1]);
assertEquals(born, values[2]);</programlisting>

          <para>This extractor implementation has only one required property,
          the names of the fields to map. Just as the
          <classname>BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper</classname> needs field names
          to map fields on the <classname>FieldSet</classname> to setters on
          the provided object, the
          <classname>BeanWrapperFieldExtractor</classname> needs names to map
          to getters for creating an object array. It is worth noting that the
          order of the names determines the order of the fields within the
          array.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="delimitedFileWritingExample">
        <title>Delimited File Writing Example</title>

        <para>The most basic flat file format is one in which all fields are
        separated by a delimiter. This can be accomplished using a
        <classname>DelimitedLineAggregator</classname>. The example below
        writes out a simple domain object that represents a credit to a
        customer account:</para>

        <programlisting>public class CustomerCredit {

    private int id;
    private String name;
    private BigDecimal credit;

    //getters and setters removed for clarity
}</programlisting>

        <para>Because a domain object is being used, an implementation of the
        FieldExtractor interface must be provided, along with the delimiter to
        use:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.springframework.batch.item.file.FlatFileItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="resource" ref="outputResource" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="lineAggregator"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.spr...DelimitedLineAggregator"&gt;
            &lt;property name="delimiter" value=","/&gt;
            &lt;property name="fieldExtractor"&gt;
                &lt;bean class="org.spr...BeanWrapperFieldExtractor"&gt;
                    &lt;property name="names" value="name,credit"/&gt;
                &lt;/bean&gt;
            &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>In this case, the
        <classname>BeanWrapperFieldExtractor</classname> described earlier in
        this chapter is used to turn the name and credit fields within
        <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> into an object array, which is
        then written out with commas between each field.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="fixedWidthFileWritingExample">
        <title>Fixed Width File Writing Example</title>

        <para>Delimited is not the only type of flat file format. Many prefer
        to use a set width for each column to delineate between fields, which
        is usually referred to as 'fixed width'. Spring Batch supports this in
        file writing via the <classname>FormatterLineAggregator</classname>.
        Using the same <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> domain object
        described above, it can be configured as follows:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.springframework.batch.item.file.FlatFileItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="resource" ref="outputResource" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="lineAggregator"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.spr...FormatterLineAggregator"&gt;
            &lt;property name="fieldExtractor"&gt;
                &lt;bean class="org.spr...BeanWrapperFieldExtractor"&gt;
                    &lt;property name="names" value="name,credit" /&gt;
                &lt;/bean&gt;
            &lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;property name="format" value="%-9s%-2.0f" /&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Most of the above example should look familiar. However, the
        value of the format property is new:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;property name="format" value="%-9s%-2.0f" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>The underlying implementation is built using the same
        <classname>Formatter</classname> added as part of Java 5. The Java
        <classname>Formatter</classname> is based on the
        <methodname>printf</methodname> functionality of the C programming
        language. Most details on how to configure a formatter can be found in
        the javadoc of <ulink
        url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/Formatter.html"><citetitle>Formatter</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="handlingFileCreation">
        <title>Handling File Creation</title>

        <para><classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname> has a very simple
        relationship with file resources. When the reader is initialized, it
        opens the file if it exists, and throws an exception if it does not.
        File writing isn't quite so simple. At first glance it seems like a
        similar straight forward contract should exist for
        <classname>FlatFileItemWriter</classname>: if the file already exists,
        throw an exception, and if it does not, create it and start writing.
        However, potentially restarting a <classname>Job</classname> can cause
        issues. In normal restart scenarios, the contract is reversed: if the
        file exists, start writing to it from the last known good position,
        and if it does not, throw an exception. However, what happens if the
        file name for this job is always the same? In this case, you would
        want to delete the file if it exists, unless it's a restart. Because
        of this possibility, the <classname>FlatFileItemWriter</classname>
        contains the property, <methodname>shouldDeleteIfExists</methodname>.
        Setting this property to true will cause an existing file with the
        same name to be deleted when the writer is opened.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="xmlReadingWriting">
    <title id="infrastructure.2.3">XML Item Readers and Writers</title>

    <para>Spring Batch provides transactional infrastructure for both reading
    XML records and mapping them to Java objects as well as writing Java
    objects as XML records.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Constraints on streaming XML</title>

      <para>The StAX API is used for I/O as other standard XML parsing APIs do
      not fit batch processing requirements (DOM loads the whole input into
      memory at once and SAX controls the parsing process allowing the user
      only to provide callbacks).</para>
    </note>

    <para>Lets take a closer look how XML input and output works in Spring
    Batch. First, there are a few concepts that vary from file reading and
    writing but are common across Spring Batch XML processing. With XML
    processing, instead of lines of records (FieldSets) that need to be
    tokenized, it is assumed an XML resource is a collection of 'fragments'
    corresponding to individual records:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/xmlinput.png" format="PNG"
                     scale="65" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/xmlinput.png" format="PNG"
                     scale="45" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Figure 3.1: XML Input</para></caption>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The 'trade' tag is defined as the 'root element' in the scenario
    above. Everything between '&lt;trade&gt;' and '&lt;/trade&gt;' is
    considered one 'fragment'. Spring Batch uses Object/XML Mapping (OXM) to
    bind fragments to objects. However, Spring Batch is not tied to any
    particular XML binding technology. Typical use is to delegate to <ulink
    url="http://static.springframework.org/spring-ws/site/reference/html/oxm.html"><citetitle>Spring
    OXM</citetitle></ulink>, which provides uniform abstraction for the most
    popular OXM technologies. The dependency on Spring OXM is optional and you
    can choose to implement Spring Batch specific interfaces if desired. The
    relationship to the technologies that OXM supports can be shown as the
    following:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/oxm-fragments.png"
                     format="PNG" scale="60" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/oxm-fragments.png"
                     format="PNG" scale="45" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Figure 3.2: OXM Binding</para></caption>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Now with an introduction to OXM and how one can use XML fragments to
    represent records, let's take a closer look at readers and writers.</para>

    <section id="StaxEventItemReader">
      <title>StaxEventItemReader</title>

      <para>The <classname>StaxEventItemReader</classname> configuration
      provides a typical setup for the processing of records from an XML input
      stream. First, lets examine a set of XML records that the
      <classname>StaxEventItemReader</classname> can process.</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;records&gt;
    &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
        &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0001&lt;/isin&gt;
        &lt;quantity&gt;5&lt;/quantity&gt;
        &lt;price&gt;11.39&lt;/price&gt;
        &lt;customer&gt;Customer1&lt;/customer&gt;
    &lt;/trade&gt;
    &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
        &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0002&lt;/isin&gt;
        &lt;quantity&gt;2&lt;/quantity&gt;
        &lt;price&gt;72.99&lt;/price&gt;
        &lt;customer&gt;Customer2c&lt;/customer&gt;
    &lt;/trade&gt;
    &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
        &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0003&lt;/isin&gt;
        &lt;quantity&gt;9&lt;/quantity&gt;
        &lt;price&gt;99.99&lt;/price&gt;
        &lt;customer&gt;Customer3&lt;/customer&gt;
    &lt;/trade&gt;
&lt;/records&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para>To be able to process the XML records the following is needed:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Root Element Name - Name of the root element of the fragment
            that constitutes the object to be mapped. The example
            configuration demonstrates this with the value of trade.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Resource - Spring Resource that represents the file to be
            read.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><classname>FragmentDeserializer</classname> - Unmarshalling
            facility provided by Spring OXM for mapping the XML fragment to an
            object.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.xml.StaxEventItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="fragmentRootElementName" value="trade" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="resource" value="data/iosample/input/input.xml" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="unmarshaller" ref="tradeMarshaller" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>Notice that in this example we have chosen to use an
      <classname>XStreamMarshaller</classname> which accepts an alias passed
      in as a map with the first key and value being the name of the fragment
      (i.e. root element) and the object type to bind. Then, similar to a
      <classname>FieldSet</classname>, the names of the other elements that
      map to fields within the object type are described as key/value pairs in
      the map. In the configuration file we can use a Spring configuration
      utility to describe the required alias as follows:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="tradeMarshaller" 
      class="org.springframework.oxm.xstream.XStreamMarshaller"&gt;
    &lt;property name="aliases"&gt;
<emphasis role="bold">        &lt;util:map id="aliases"&gt;
            &lt;entry key="trade"
                   value="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Trade" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="price" value="java.math.BigDecimal" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="name" value="java.lang.String" /&gt;
        &lt;/util:map&gt;</emphasis>
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para>On input the reader reads the XML resource until it recognizes
      that a new fragment is about to start (by matching the tag name by
      default). The reader creates a standalone XML document from the fragment
      (or at least makes it appear so) and passes the document to a
      deserializer (typically a wrapper around a Spring OXM
      <classname>Unmarshaller</classname>) to map the XML to a Java
      object.</para>

      <para>In summary, this procedure is analogous to the following scripted
      Java code which uses the injection provided by the Spring
      configuration:</para>

      <para><programlisting>StaxEventItemReader xmlStaxEventItemReader = new StaxEventItemReader()
Resource resource = new ByteArrayResource(xmlResource.getBytes()) 

Map aliases = new HashMap();
aliases.put("trade","org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Trade");
aliases.put("price","java.math.BigDecimal");
aliases.put("customer","java.lang.String");
Marshaller marshaller = new XStreamMarshaller();
marshaller.setAliases(aliases);
xmlStaxEventItemReader.setUnmarshaller(marshaller);
xmlStaxEventItemReader.setResource(resource);
xmlStaxEventItemReader.setFragmentRootElementName("trade");
xmlStaxEventItemReader.open(new ExecutionContext());

boolean hasNext = true

CustomerCredit credit = null;

while (hasNext) {
    credit = xmlStaxEventItemReader.read();
    if (credit == null) {
        hasNext = false;
    }
    else {
        System.out.println(credit);
    }
}</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section id="StaxEventItemWriter">
      <title>StaxEventItemWriter</title>

      <para>Output works symmetrically to input. The
      <classname>StaxEventItemWriter</classname> needs a
      <classname>Resource</classname>, a marshaller, and a <literal>rootTagName</literal>. A Java
      object is passed to a marshaller (typically a standard Spring OXM
      <classname>Marshaller</classname>) which writes to a
      <classname>Resource</classname> using a custom event writer that filters
      the <classname>StartDocument</classname> and
      <classname>EndDocument</classname> events produced for each fragment by
      the OXM tools. We'll show this in an example using the
      <classname>MarshallingEventWriterSerializer</classname>. The Spring
      configuration for this setup looks as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.springframework.batch.item.xml.StaxEventItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="resource" ref="outputResource" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="marshaller" ref="customerCreditMarshaller" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="rootTagName" value="customers" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="overwriteOutput" value="true" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The configuration sets up the three required properties and
      optionally sets the overwriteOutput=true, mentioned earlier in the
      chapter for specifying whether an existing file can be overwritten. It
      should be noted the marshaller used for the writer is the exact same as
      the one used in the reading example from earlier in the chapter:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;bean id="customerCreditMarshaller" 
      class="org.springframework.oxm.xstream.XStreamMarshaller"&gt;
    &lt;property name="aliases"&gt;
        &lt;util:map id="aliases"&gt;
            &lt;entry key="customer"
                   value="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCredit" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="credit" value="java.math.BigDecimal" /&gt;
            &lt;entry key="name" value="java.lang.String" /&gt;
        &lt;/util:map&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>To summarize with a Java example, the following code illustrates
      all of the points discussed, demonstrating the programmatic setup of the
      required properties:</para>

      <programlisting>StaxEventItemWriter staxItemWriter = new StaxEventItemWriter()
FileSystemResource resource = new FileSystemResource("data/outputFile.xml")

Map aliases = new HashMap();
aliases.put("customer","org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCredit");
aliases.put("credit","java.math.BigDecimal");
aliases.put("name","java.lang.String");
Marshaller marshaller = new XStreamMarshaller();
marshaller.setAliases(aliases);

staxItemWriter.setResource(resource);
staxItemWriter.setMarshaller(marshaller);
staxItemWriter.setRootTagName("trades");
staxItemWriter.setOverwriteOutput(true);

ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
staxItemWriter.open(executionContext);
CustomerCredit Credit = new CustomerCredit();
trade.setPrice(11.39); 
credit.setName("Customer1");
staxItemWriter.write(trade);</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="multiFileInput">
    <title>Multi-File Input</title>

    <para>It is a common requirement to process multiple files within a single
    <classname>Step</classname>. Assuming the files all have the same
    formatting, the <classname>MultiResourceItemReader</classname> supports
    this type of input for both XML and flat file processing. Consider the
    following files in a directory:</para>

    <programlisting>file-1.txt  file-2.txt  ignored.txt</programlisting>

    <para>file-1.txt and file-2.txt are formatted the same and for business
    reasons should be processed together. The
    <classname>MuliResourceItemReader</classname> can be used to read in both
    files by using wildcards:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;bean id="multiResourceReader" class="org.spr...MultiResourceItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="resources" value="classpath:data/input/file-*.txt" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="delegate" ref="flatFileItemReader" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The referenced delegate is a simple
    <classname>FlatFileItemReader</classname>. The above configuration will
    read input from both files, handling rollback and restart scenarios. It
    should be noted that, as with any <classname>ItemReader</classname>,
    adding extra input (in this case a file) could cause potential issues when
    restarting. It is recommended that batch jobs work with their own
    individual directories until completed successfully.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="database">
    <title id="infrastructure.2.2">Database</title>

    <para>Like most enterprise application styles, a database is the central
    storage mechanism for batch. However, batch differs from other application
    styles due to the sheer size of the datasets with which the system must
    work. If a SQL statement returns 1 million rows, the result set probably
    holds all returned results in memory until all rows have been read. Spring
    Batch provides two types of solutions for this problem: Cursor and Paging
    database ItemReaders.</para>

    <section id="cursorBasedItemReaders">
      <title>Cursor Based ItemReaders</title>

      <para>Using a database cursor is generally the default approach of most
      batch developers, because it is the database's solution to the problem
      of 'streaming' relational data. The Java
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> class is essentially an object
      orientated mechanism for manipulating a cursor. A
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> maintains a cursor to the current row
      of data. Calling <methodname>next</methodname> on a
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> moves this cursor to the next row.
      Spring Batch cursor based ItemReaders open the a cursor on
      initialization, and move the cursor forward one row for every call to
      <methodname>read</methodname>, returning a mapped object that can be
      used for processing. The <methodname>close</methodname> method will then
      be called to ensure all resources are freed up. The Spring core
      <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> gets around this problem by using
      the callback pattern to completely map all rows in a
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> and close before returning control back
      to the method caller. However, in batch this must wait until the step is
      complete. Below is a generic diagram of how a cursor based
      <classname>ItemReader</classname> works, and while a SQL statement is
      used as an example since it is so widely known, any technology could
      implement the basic approach:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/cursorExample.png"
                     scale="65" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/cursorExample.png"
                     scale="35" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>This example illustrates the basic pattern. Given a 'FOO' table,
      which has three columns: ID, NAME, and BAR, select all rows with an ID
      greater than 1 but less than 7. This puts the beginning of the cursor
      (row 1) on ID 2. The result of this row should be a completely mapped
      Foo object. Calling <methodname>read</methodname>() again moves the
      cursor to the next row, which is the Foo with an ID of 3. The results of
      these reads will be written out after each
      <methodname>read</methodname>, thus allowing the objects to be garbage
      collected (assuming no instance variables are maintaining references to
      them).</para>

      <section id="JdbcCursorItemReader">
        <title>JdbcCursorItemReader</title>

        <para><classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname> is the Jdbc
        implementation of the cursor based technique. It works directly with a
        <classname>ResultSet</classname> and requires a SQL statement to run
        against a connection obtained from a
        <classname>DataSource</classname>. The following database schema will
        be used as an example:</para>

        <programlisting>CREATE TABLE CUSTOMER (
   ID BIGINT IDENTITY PRIMARY KEY,  
   NAME VARCHAR(45),
   CREDIT FLOAT
);</programlisting>

        <para>Many people prefer to use a domain object for each row, so we'll
        use an implementation of the <classname>RowMapper</classname>
        interface to map a <classname>CustomerCredit</classname>
        object:</para>

        <programlisting>public class CustomerCreditRowMapper implements RowMapper {

    public static final String ID_COLUMN = "id";
    public static final String NAME_COLUMN = "name";
    public static final String CREDIT_COLUMN = "credit";

    public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
        CustomerCredit customerCredit = new CustomerCredit();

        customerCredit.setId(rs.getInt(ID_COLUMN));
        customerCredit.setName(rs.getString(NAME_COLUMN));
        customerCredit.setCredit(rs.getBigDecimal(CREDIT_COLUMN));

        return customerCredit;
    }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Because <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> is so familiar to
        users of Spring, and the <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>
        shares key interfaces with it, it is useful to see an example of how
        to read in this data with <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, in
        order to contrast it with the <classname>ItemReader</classname>. For
        the purposes of this example, let's assume there are 1,000 rows in the
        CUSTOMER database. The first example will be using
        <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>:</para>

        <programlisting>//For simplicity sake, assume a dataSource has already been obtained
JdbcTemplate jdbcTemplate = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
List customerCredits = jdbcTemplate.query("SELECT ID, NAME, CREDIT from CUSTOMER", 
                                          new CustomerCreditRowMapper());</programlisting>

        <para>After running this code snippet the customerCredits list will
        contain 1,000 <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> objects. In the
        query method, a connection will be obtained from the
        <classname>DataSource</classname>, the provided SQL will be run
        against it, and the <methodname>mapRow</methodname> method will be
        called for each row in the <classname>ResultSet</classname>. Let's
        contrast this with the approach of the
        <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>:</para>

        <programlisting>JdbcCursorItemReader itemReader = new JdbcCursorItemReader();
itemReader.setDataSource(dataSource);
itemReader.setSql("SELECT ID, NAME, CREDIT from CUSTOMER");
itemReader.setRowMapper(new CustomerCreditRowMapper());
int counter = 0;
ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
itemReader.open(executionContext);
Object customerCredit = new Object();
while(customerCredit != null){
    customerCredit = itemReader.read();
    counter++;
}
itemReader.close(executionContext);</programlisting>

        <para>After running this code snippet the counter will equal 1,000. If
        the code above had put the returned customerCredit into a list, the
        result would have been exactly the same as with the
        <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> example. However, the big
        advantage of the <classname>ItemReader</classname> is that it allows
        items to be 'streamed'. The <methodname>read</methodname> method can
        be called once, and the item written out via an
        <classname>ItemWriter</classname>, and then the next item obtained via
        <methodname>read</methodname>. This allows item reading and writing to
        be done in 'chunks' and committed periodically, which is the essence
        of high performance batch processing. Furthermore, it is very easily
        configured for injection into a Spring Batch
        <classname>Step</classname>:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.spr...JdbcCursorItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="sql" value="select ID, NAME, CREDIT from CUSTOMER"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCreditRowMapper"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <section id="JdbcCursorItemReaderProperties">
          <title>Additional Properties</title>

          <para>Because there are so many varying options for opening a cursor
          in Java, there are many properties on the
          <classname>JdbcCustorItemReader</classname> that can be set:</para>

          <table>
            <title>JdbcCursorItemReader Properties</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>ignoreWarnings</entry>

                  <entry>Determines whether or not SQLWarnings are logged or
                  cause an exception - default is true</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>fetchSize</entry>

                  <entry>Gives the Jdbc driver a hint as to the number of rows
                  that should be fetched from the database when more rows are
                  needed by the <classname>ResultSet</classname> object used
                  by the <classname>ItemReader</classname>. By default, no
                  hint is given.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>maxRows</entry>

                  <entry>Sets the limit for the maximum number of rows the
                  underlying <classname>ResultSet</classname> can hold at any
                  one time.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>queryTimeout</entry>

                  <entry>Sets the number of seconds the driver will wait for a
                  <classname>Statement</classname> object to execute to the
                  given number of seconds. If the limit is exceeded, a
                  <classname>DataAccessEception</classname> is thrown.
                  (Consult your driver vendor documentation for
                  details).</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>verifyCursorPosition</entry>

                  <entry>Because the same <classname>ResultSet</classname>
                  held by the <classname>ItemReader</classname> is passed to
                  the <classname>RowMapper</classname>, it is possible for
                  users to call <methodname>ResultSet.next</methodname>()
                  themselves, which could cause issues with the reader's
                  internal count. Setting this value to true will cause an
                  exception to be thrown if the cursor position is not the
                  same after the <classname>RowMapper</classname> call as it
                  was before.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>saveState</entry>

                  <entry>Indicates whether or not the reader's state should be
                  saved in the <classname>ExecutionContext</classname>
                  provided by
                  <methodname>ItemStream#update</methodname>(<classname>ExecutionContext</classname>)
                  The default value is true.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>driverSupportsAbsolute</entry>

                  <entry>Defaults to false. Indicates whether the Jdbc driver
                  supports setting the absolute row on a
                  <classname>ResultSet</classname>. It is recommended that
                  this is set to true for Jdbc drivers that supports
                  <methodname>ResultSet.absolute</methodname>() as it may
                  improve performance, especially if a step fails while
                  working with a large data set.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>setUseSharedExtendedConnection</entry>

                  <entry>Defaults to false. Indicates whether the connection
                  used for the cursor should be used by all other processing
                  thus sharing the same transaction. If this is set to false,
                  which is the default, then the cursor will be opened using
                  its own connection and will not participate in any
                  transactions started for the rest of the step processing. If
                  you set this flag to true then you must wrap the
                  <classname>DataSource</classname> in an
                  <classname>ExtendedConnectionDataSourceProxy</classname> to
                  prevent the connection from being closed and released after
                  each commit. When you set this option to true then the
                  statement used to open the cursor will be created with both
                  'READ_ONLY' and 'HOLD_CUSORS_OVER_COMMIT' options. This
                  allows holding the cursor open over transaction start and
                  commits performed in the step processing. To use this
                  feature you need a database that supports this and a Jdbc
                  driver supporting Jdbc 3.0 or later.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="HibernateCursorItemReader">
        <title>HibernateCursorItemReader</title>

        <para>Just as normal Spring users make important decisions about
        whether or not to use ORM solutions, which affect whether or not they
        use a <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> or a
        <classname>HibernateTemplate</classname>, Spring Batch users have the
        same options. <classname>HibernateCursorItemReader</classname> is the
        Hibernate implementation of the cursor technique. Hibernate's usage in
        batch has been fairly controversial. This has largely been because
        Hibernate was originally developed to support online application
        styles. However, that doesn't mean it can't be used for batch
        processing. The easiest approach for solving this problem is to use a
        <classname>StatelessSession</classname> rather than a standard
        session. This removes all of the caching and dirty checking hibernate
        employs that can cause issues in a batch scenario. For more
        information on the differences between stateless and normal hibernate
        sessions, refer to the documentation of your specific hibernate
        release. The <classname>HibernateCursorItemReader</classname> allows
        you to declare an HQL statement and pass in a
        <classname>SessionFactory</classname>, which will pass back one item
        per call to <methodname>read</methodname> in the same basic fashion as
        the <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>. Below is an example
        configuration using the same 'customer credit' example as the JDBC
        reader:</para>

        <programlisting>HibernateCursorItemReader itemReader = new HibernateCursorItemReader();
itemReader.setQueryString("from CustomerCredit");
//For simplicity sake, assume sessionFactory already obtained.
itemReader.setSessionFactory(sessionFactory);
itemReader.setUseStatelessSession(true);
int counter = 0;
ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
itemReader.open(executionContext);
Object customerCredit = new Object();
while(customerCredit != null){
    customerCredit = itemReader.read();
    counter++;
}
itemReader.close(executionContext);</programlisting>

        <para>This configured <classname>ItemReader</classname> will return
        <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> objects in the exact same manner
        as described by the <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>,
        assuming hibernate mapping files have been created correctly for the
        Customer table. The 'useStatelessSession' property defaults to true,
        but has been added here to draw attention to the ability to switch it
        on or off. It is also worth noting that the fetchSize of the
        underlying cursor can be set via the setFetchSize property. As with
        <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>, configuration is
        straightforward:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader"
      class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.HibernateCursorItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="sessionFactory" ref="sessionFactory" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="queryString" value="from CustomerCredit" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section id="StoredProcedureItemReader">
        <title>StoredProcedureItemReader</title>

        <para>Sometimes it is necessary to obtain the cursor data using a
        stored procedure. The <classname>StoredProcedureItemReader</classname>
        works like the <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname> except that
        instead of executing a query to obtain a cursor we execute a stored
        procedure that returns a cursor. The stored procedure can return the
        cursor in three different ways:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>as a returned ResultSet (used by SQL Server, Sybase, DB2,
            Derby and MySQL)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>as a ref-cursor returned as an out parameter (used by Oracle
            and PostgreSQL)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>as the return value of a stored function call</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Below is a basic example configuration using the same 'customer
        credit' example as earlier:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="reader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.StoredProcedureItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="procedureName" value="sp_customer_credit"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCreditRowMapper"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting>

        <para>This example relies on the stored procedure to provide a
        ResultSet as a returned result (option 1 above). </para>

        <para>If the stored procedure returned a ref-cursor (option 2) then we
        would need to provide the position of the out parameter that is the
        returned ref-cursor. Here is an example where the first parameter is
        the returned ref-cursor:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="reader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.StoredProcedureItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="procedureName" value="sp_customer_credit"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="refCursorPosition" value="1"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCreditRowMapper"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting>

        <para>If the cursor was returned from a stored function (option 3) we
        would need to set the property "<varname>function</varname>" to
        <literal>true</literal>. It defaults to <literal>false</literal>. Here
        is what that would look like:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="reader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.StoredProcedureItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="procedureName" value="sp_customer_credit"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="function" value="true"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.CustomerCreditRowMapper"/&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting>

        <para>In all of these cases we need to define a
        <classname>RowMapper</classname> as well as a
        <classname>DataSource</classname> and the actual procedure
        name.</para>

        <para>If the stored procedure or function takes in parameter then they
        must be declared and set via the parameters property. Here is an
        example for Oracle that declares three parameters. The first one is
        the out parameter that returns the ref-cursor, the second and third
        are in parameters that takes a value of type INTEGER:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="reader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.StoredProcedureItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="procedureName" value="spring.cursor_func"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="parameters"&gt;
        &lt;list&gt;
            &lt;bean class="org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlOutParameter"&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="0" value="newid"/&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="1"&gt;
                    &lt;util:constant static-field="oracle.jdbc.OracleTypes.CURSOR"/&gt;
                &lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
            &lt;/bean&gt;
            &lt;bean class="org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlParameter"&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="0" value="amount"/&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="1"&gt;
                    &lt;util:constant static-field="java.sql.Types.INTEGER"/&gt;
                &lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
            &lt;/bean&gt;
            &lt;bean class="org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlParameter"&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="0" value="custid"/&gt;
                &lt;constructor-arg index="1"&gt;
                    &lt;util:constant static-field="java.sql.Types.INTEGER"/&gt;
                &lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
            &lt;/bean&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="refCursorPosition" value="1"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper" ref="rowMapper"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="preparedStatementSetter" ref="parameterSetter"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>In addition to the parameter declarations we need to specify a
        <classname>PreparedStatementSetter</classname> implementation that
        sets the parameter values for the call. This works the same as for the
        <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname> above. All the additional
        properties listed in <xref linkend="JdbcCursorItemReaderProperties" />
        apply to the <classname>StoredProcedureItemReader</classname> as well.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="pagingItemReaders">
      <title>Paging ItemReaders</title>

      <para>An alternative to using a database cursor is executing multiple
      queries where each query is bringing back a portion of the results. We
      refer to this portion as a page. Each query that is executed must
      specify the starting row number and the number of rows that we want
      returned for the page.</para>

      <section id="JdbcPagingItemReader">
        <title>JdbcPagingItemReader</title>

        <para>One implementation of a paging <classname>ItemReader</classname>
        is the <classname>JdbcPagingItemReader</classname>. The
        <classname>JdbcPagingItemReader</classname> needs a
        <classname>PagingQueryProvider</classname> responsible for providing
        the SQL queries used to retrieve the rows making up a page. Since each
        database has its own strategy for providing paging support, we need to
        use a different <classname>PagingQueryProvider</classname> for each
        supported database type. There is also the
        <classname>SqlPagingQueryProviderFactoryBean</classname> that will
        auto-detect the database that is being used and determine the
        appropriate <classname>PagingQueryProvider</classname> implementation.
        This simplifies the configuration and is the recommended best
        practice.</para>

        <para>The <classname>SqlPagingQueryProviderFactoryBean</classname>
        requires that you specify a select clause and a from clause. You can
        also provide an optional where clause. These clauses will be used to
        build an SQL statement combined with the required sortKey.</para>

        <para>After the reader has been opened, it will pass back one item per
        call to <methodname>read</methodname> in the same basic fashion as any
        other <classname>ItemReader</classname>. The paging happens behind the
        scenes when additional rows are needed.</para>

        <para>Below is an example configuration using a similar 'customer
        credit' example as the cursor based ItemReaders above:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.spr...JdbcPagingItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="queryProvider"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.spr...SqlPagingQueryProviderFactoryBean"&gt;
            &lt;property name="selectClause" value="select id, name, credit"/&gt;
            &lt;property name="fromClause" value="from customer"/&gt;
            &lt;property name="whereClause" value="where status=:status"/&gt;
            &lt;property name="sortKey" value="id"/&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="parameterValues"&gt;
        &lt;map&gt;
            &lt;entry key="status" value="NEW"/&gt;
        &lt;/map&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="pageSize" value="1000"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper" ref="customerMapper"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This configured <classname>ItemReader</classname> will return
        <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> objects using the
        <classname>RowMapper</classname> that must be specified. The
        'pageSize' property determines the number of entities read from the
        database for each query execution.</para>

        <para>The 'parameterValues' property can be used to specify a Map of
        parameter values for the query. If you use named parameters in the
        where clause the key for each entry should match the name of the named
        parameter. If you use a traditional '?' placeholder then the key for
        each entry should be the number of the placeholder, starting with
        1.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="JpaPagingItemReader">
        <title>JpaPagingItemReader</title>

        <para>Another implementation of a paging
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> is the
        <classname>JpaPagingItemReader</classname>. JPA doesn't have a concept
        similar to the Hibernate <classname>StatelessSession</classname> so we
        have to use other features provided by the JPA specification. Since
        JPA supports paging, this is a natural choice when it comes to using
        JPA for batch processing. After each page is read, the entities will
        become detached and the persistence context will be cleared in order
        to allow the entities to be garbage collected once the page is
        processed.</para>

        <para>The <classname>JpaPagingItemReader</classname> allows you to
        declare a JPQL statement and pass in a
        <classname>EntityManagerFactory</classname>. It will then pass back
        one item per call to <methodname>read</methodname> in the same basic
        fashion as any other <classname>ItemReader</classname>. The paging
        happens behind the scenes when additional entities are needed. Below
        is an example configuration using the same 'customer credit' example
        as the JDBC reader above:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.spr...JpaPagingItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="entityManagerFactory" ref="entityManagerFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="queryString" value="select c from CustomerCredit c"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="pageSize" value="1000"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This configured <classname>ItemReader</classname> will return
        <classname>CustomerCredit</classname> objects in the exact same manner
        as described by the <classname>JdbcPagingItemReader</classname> above,
        assuming the Customer object has the correct JPA annotations or ORM
        mapping file. The 'pageSize' property determines the number of
        entities read from the database for each query execution.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="IbatisPagingItemReader">
        <title>IbatisPagingItemReader</title>

        <para>If you use IBATIS for your data access then you can use the
        <classname>IbatisPagingItemReader</classname> which, as the name
        indicates, is an implementation of a paging
        <classname>ItemReader</classname>. IBATIS doesn't have direct support
        for reading rows in pages but by providing a couple of standard
        variables you can add paging support to your IBATIS queries.</para>

        <para>Here is an example of a configuration for a
        <classname>IbatisPagingItemReader</classname> reading CustomerCredits
        as in the examples above:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.spr...IbatisPagingItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="sqlMapClient" ref="sqlMapClient"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="queryId" value="getPagedCustomerCredits"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="pageSize" value="1000"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>The <classname>IbatisPagingItemReader</classname> configuration
        above references an IBATIS query called "getPagedCustomerCredits".
        Here is an example of what that query should look like for
        MySQL.</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;select id="getPagedCustomerCredits" resultMap="customerCreditResult"&gt;
    select id, name, credit from customer order by id asc LIMIT #_skiprows#, #_pagesize#
&lt;/select&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>The <classname>_skiprows</classname> and
        <classname>_pagesize</classname> variables are provided by the
        <classname>IbatisPagingItemReader</classname> and there is also a
        <classname>_page</classname> variable that can be used if necessary.
        The syntax for the paging queries varies with the database used. Here
        is an example for Oracle (unfortunately we need to use CDATA for some
        operators since this belongs in an XML document):</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;select id="getPagedCustomerCredits" resultMap="customerCreditResult"&gt;
    select * from (
      select * from (
        select t.id, t.name, t.credit, ROWNUM ROWNUM_ from customer t order by id
       )) where ROWNUM_ &lt;![CDATA[ &gt; ]]&gt; ( #_page# * #_pagesize# )
    ) where ROWNUM &lt;![CDATA[ &lt;= ]]&gt; #_pagesize#
  &lt;/select&gt;
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="databaseItemWriters">
      <title>Database ItemWriters</title>

      <para>While both Flat Files and XML have specific ItemWriters, there is
      no exact equivalent in the database world. This is because transactions
      provide all the functionality that is needed. ItemWriters are necessary
      for files because they must act as if they're transactional, keeping
      track of written items and flushing or clearing at the appropriate
      times. Databases have no need for this functionality, since the write is
      already contained in a transaction. Users can create their own DAOs that
      implement the <classname>ItemWriter</classname> interface or use one
      from a custom <classname>ItemWriter</classname> that's written for
      generic processing concerns, either way, they should work without any
      issues. One thing to look out for is the performance and error handling
      capabilities that are provided by batching the outputs. This is most
      common when using hibernate as an <classname>ItemWriter</classname>, but
      could have the same issues when using Jdbc batch mode. Batching database
      output doesn't have any inherent flaws, assuming we are careful to flush
      and there are no errors in the data. However, any errors while writing
      out can cause confusion because there is no way to know which individual
      item caused an exception, or even if any individual item was
      responsible, as illustrated below:</para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/errorOnFlush.png"
                       scale="95" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/errorOnFlush.png"
                       scale="80" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>If items are buffered before being written out, any
      errors encountered will not be thrown until the buffer is flushed just
      before a commit. For example, let's assume that 20 items will be written
      per chunk, and the 15th item throws a DataIntegrityViolationException.
      As far as the Step is concerned, all 20 item will be written out
      successfully, since there's no way to know that an error will occur
      until they are actually written out. Once
      <classname>Session#</classname><methodname>flush</methodname>() is
      called, the buffer will be emptied and the exception will be hit. At
      this point, there's nothing the <classname>Step</classname> can do, the
      transaction must be rolled back. Normally, this exception might cause
      the Item to be skipped (depending upon the skip/retry policies), and
      then it won't be written out again. However, in the batched scenario,
      there's no way for it to know which item caused the issue, the whole
      buffer was being written out when the failure happened. The only way to
      solve this issue is to flush after each item:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/errorOnWrite.png"
                     scale="95" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/errorOnWrite.png"
                     scale="80" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>This is a common use case, especially when using Hibernate, and
      the simple guideline for implementations of
      <classname>ItemWriter</classname>, is to flush on each call to
      <methodname>write()</methodname>. Doing so allows for items to be
      skipped reliably, with Spring Batch taking care internally of the
      granularity of the calls to <classname>ItemWriter</classname> after an
      error.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reusingExistingServices">
    <title>Reusing Existing Services</title>

    <para>Batch systems are often used in conjunction with other application
    styles. The most common is an online system, but it may also support
    integration or even a thick client application by moving necessary bulk
    data that each application style uses. For this reason, it is common that
    many users want to reuse existing DAOs or other services within their
    batch jobs. The Spring container itself makes this fairly easy by allowing
    any necessary class to be injected. However, there may be cases where the
    existing service needs to act as an <classname>ItemReader</classname> or
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname>, either to satisfy the dependency of
    another Spring Batch class, or because it truly is the main
    <classname>ItemReader</classname> for a step. It is fairly trivial to
    write an adaptor class for each service that needs wrapping, but because
    it is such a common concern, Spring Batch provides implementations:
    <classname>ItemReaderAdapter</classname> and
    <classname>ItemWriterAdapter</classname>. Both classes implement the
    standard Spring method invoking the delegate pattern and are fairly simple
    to set up. Below is an example of the reader:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.adapter.ItemReaderAdapter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetObject" ref="fooService" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetMethod" value="generateFoo" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="fooService" class="org.springframework.batch.item.sample.FooService" /&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>One important point to note is that the contract of the targetMethod
    must be the same as the contract for <methodname>read</methodname>: when
    exhausted it will return null, otherwise an <classname>Object</classname>.
    Anything else will prevent the framework from knowing when processing
    should end, either causing an infinite loop or incorrect failure,
    depending upon the implementation of the
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname>. The <classname>ItemWriter</classname>
    implementation is equally as simple:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.springframework.batch.item.adapter.ItemWriterAdapter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetObject" ref="fooService" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetMethod" value="processFoo" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="fooService" class="org.springframework.batch.item.sample.FooService" /&gt;
</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="validatingInput">
    <title id="infrastructure.5">Validating Input</title>

    <para>During the course of this chapter, multiple approaches to parsing
    input have been discussed. Each major implementation will throw an
    exception if it is not 'well-formed'. The
    <classname>FixedLengthTokenizer</classname> will throw an exception if a
    range of data is missing. Similarly, attempting to access an index in a
    <classname>RowMapper</classname> of <classname>FieldSetMapper</classname>
    that doesn't exist or is in a different format than the one expected will
    cause an exception to be thrown. All of these types of exceptions will be
    thrown before <methodname>read</methodname> returns. However, they don't
    address the issue of whether or not the returned item is valid. For
    example, if one of the fields is an age, it obviously cannot be negative.
    It will parse correctly, because it existed and is a number, but it won't
    cause an exception. Since there are already a plethora of Validation
    frameworks, Spring Batch does not attempt to provide yet another, but
    rather provides a very simple interface that can be implemented by any
    number of frameworks:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface Validator {
  
    void validate(Object value) throws ValidationException;

}</programlisting>

    <para>The contract is that the <methodname>validate</methodname> method
    will throw an exception if the object is invalid, and return normally if
    it is valid. Spring Batch provides an out of the box
    <classname>ItemProcessor:</classname></para>

    <programlisting>&lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.item.validator.ValidatingItemProcessor"&gt;
    &lt;property name="validator" ref="validator" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="validator"
      class="org.springframework.batch.item.validator.SpringValidator"&gt;
    &lt;property name="validator"&gt;
        &lt;bean id="orderValidator"
              class="org.springmodules.validation.valang.ValangValidator"&gt;
            &lt;property name="valang"&gt;
                &lt;value&gt;
                    &lt;![CDATA[
           { orderId : ? &gt; 0 AND ? &lt;= 9999999999 : 'Incorrect order ID' : 'error.order.id' }
           { totalLines : ? = size(lineItems) : 'Bad count of order lines' 
                                              : 'error.order.lines.badcount'}
           { customer.registered : customer.businessCustomer = FALSE OR ? = TRUE 
                                 : 'Business customer must be registered' 
                                 : 'error.customer.registration'}
           { customer.companyName : customer.businessCustomer = FALSE OR ? HAS TEXT 
                                  : 'Company name for business customer is mandatory' 
                                  :'error.customer.companyname'}
                    ]]&gt;
                &lt;/value&gt;
            &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>This simple example shows a simple
    <classname>ValangValidator</classname> that is used to validate an order
    object. The intent is not to show Valang functionality as much as to show
    how a validator could be added.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="process-indicator">
    <title>Preventing State Persistence</title>

    <para>By default, all of the <classname>ItemReader</classname> and
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> implementations store their current
    state in the <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> before it is
    committed. However, this may not always be the desired behavior. For
    example, many developers choose to make their database readers
    'rerunnable' by using a process indicator. An extra column is added to the
    input data to indicate whether or not it has been processed. When a
    particular record is being read (or written out) the processed flag is
    flipped from false to true. The SQL statement can then contain an extra
    statement in the where clause, such as "where PROCESSED_IND = false",
    thereby ensuring that only unprocessed records will be returned in the
    case of a restart. In this scenario, it is preferable to not store any
    state, such as the current row number, since it will be irrelevant upon
    restart. For this reason, all readers and writers include the 'saveState'
    property:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;bean id="playerSummarizationSource" class="org.spr...JdbcCursorItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="rowMapper"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.PlayerSummaryMapper" /&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;property name="saveState" value="false" /&gt;</emphasis>
    &lt;property name="sql"&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;
            SELECT games.player_id, games.year_no, SUM(COMPLETES),
            SUM(ATTEMPTS), SUM(PASSING_YARDS), SUM(PASSING_TD),
            SUM(INTERCEPTIONS), SUM(RUSHES), SUM(RUSH_YARDS),
            SUM(RECEPTIONS), SUM(RECEPTIONS_YARDS), SUM(TOTAL_TD)
            from games, players where players.player_id =
            games.player_id group by games.player_id, games.year_no
        &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The <classname>ItemReader</classname> configured above will not make
    any entries in the <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> for any
    executions in which it participates.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="customReadersWriters">
    <title id="infrastructure.1.1">Creating Custom ItemReaders and
    ItemWriters</title>

    <para>So far in this chapter the basic contracts that exist for reading
    and writing in Spring Batch and some common implementations have been
    discussed. However, these are all fairly generic, and there are many
    potential scenarios that may not be covered by out of the box
    implementations. This section will show, using a simple example, how to
    create a custom <classname>ItemReader</classname> and
    <classname>ItemWriter</classname> implementation and implement their
    contracts correctly. The <classname>ItemReader</classname> will also
    implement <classname>ItemStream</classname>, in order to illustrate how to
    make a reader or writer restartable.</para>

    <section id="customReader">
      <title>Custom ItemReader Example</title>

      <para>For the purpose of this example, a simple
      <classname>ItemReader</classname> implementation that reads from a
      provided list will be created. We'll start out by implementing the most
      basic contract of <classname>ItemReader</classname>,
      <methodname>read</methodname>:</para>

      <programlisting>public class CustomItemReader&lt;T&gt; implements ItemReader&lt;T&gt;{

    List&lt;T&gt; items;

    public CustomItemReader(List&lt;T&gt; items) {
        this.items = items;
    }

    public T read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException,
       NoWorkFoundException, ParseException {

        if (!items.isEmpty()) {
            return items.remove(0);
        }
        return null;
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>This very simple class takes a list of items, and returns them one
      at a time, removing each from the list. When the list is empty, it
      returns null, thus satisfying the most basic requirements of an
      <classname>ItemReader</classname>, as illustrated below:</para>

      <programlisting>List&lt;String&gt; items = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;();
items.add("1");
items.add("2");
items.add("3");

ItemReader itemReader = new CustomItemReader&lt;String&gt;(items);
assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());
assertEquals("2", itemReader.read());
assertEquals("3", itemReader.read());
assertNull(itemReader.read());</programlisting>

      <section id="restartableReader">
        <title>Making the <classname>ItemReader</classname>
        Restartable</title>

        <para>The final challenge now is to make the
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> restartable. Currently, if the power
        goes out, and processing begins again, the
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> must start at the beginning. This is
        actually valid in many scenarios, but it is sometimes preferable that
        a batch job starts where it left off. The key discriminant is often
        whether the reader is stateful or stateless. A stateless reader does
        not need to worry about restartability, but a stateful one has to try
        and reconstitute its last known state on restart. For this reason, we
        recommend that you keep custom readers stateless if possible, so you
        don't have to worry about restartability.</para>

        <para>If you do need to store state, then the
        <classname>ItemStream</classname> interface should be used:</para>

        <programlisting>public class CustomItemReader&lt;T&gt; implements ItemReader&lt;T&gt;, ItemStream {

    List&lt;T&gt; items;
    int currentIndex = 0;
    private static final String CURRENT_INDEX = "current.index";

    public CustomItemReader(List&lt;T&gt; items) {
        this.items = items;
    }

    public T read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException,
        ParseException {

        if (currentIndex &lt; items.size()) {
            return items.get(currentIndex++);
        }
      
        return null;
    }

    public void open(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException {
        if(executionContext.containsKey(CURRENT_INDEX)){
            currentIndex = new Long(executionContext.getLong(CURRENT_INDEX)).intValue();
        }
        else{
            currentIndex = 0;
        }
    }

    public void update(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException {
        executionContext.putLong(CURRENT_INDEX, new Long(currentIndex).longValue());
    }

    public void close() throws ItemStreamException {}
}</programlisting>

        <para>On each call to the <classname>ItemStream</classname>
        <methodname>update</methodname> method, the current index of the
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> will be stored in the provided
        <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> with a key of 'current.index'.
        When the <classname>ItemStream</classname> <classname>open</classname>
        method is called, the <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> is
        checked to see if it contains an entry with that key. If the key is
        found, then the current index is moved to that location. This is a
        fairly trivial example, but it still meets the general
        contract:</para>

        <programlisting>ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
((ItemStream)itemReader).open(executionContext);
assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());
((ItemStream)itemReader).update(executionContext);

List&lt;String&gt; items = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;();
items.add("1");
items.add("2");
items.add("3");
itemReader = new CustomItemReader&lt;String&gt;(items);

((ItemStream)itemReader).open(executionContext);
assertEquals("2", itemReader.read());</programlisting>

        <para>Most ItemReaders have much more sophisticated restart logic. The
        <classname>JdbcCursorItemReader</classname>, for example, stores the
        row id of the last processed row in the Cursor.</para>

        <para>It is also worth noting that the key used within the
        <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> should not be trivial. That is
        because the same <classname>ExecutionContext</classname> is used for
        all <classname>ItemStream</classname>s within a
        <classname>Step</classname>. In most cases, simply prepending the key
        with the class name should be enough to guarantee uniqueness. However,
        in the rare cases where two of the same type of
        <classname>ItemStream</classname> are used in the same step (which can
        happen if two files are need for output) then a more unique name will
        be needed. For this reason, many of the Spring Batch
        <classname>ItemReader</classname> and
        <classname>ItemWriter</classname> implementations have a
        <methodname>setName</methodname>() property that allows this key name
        to be overridden.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="customWriter">
      <title>Custom ItemWriter Example</title>

      <para>Implementing a Custom <classname>ItemWriter</classname> is similar
      in many ways to the <classname>ItemReader</classname> example above, but
      differs in enough ways as to warrant its own example. However, adding
      restartability is essentially the same, so it won't be covered in this
      example. As with the <classname>ItemReader</classname> example, a
      <classname>List</classname> will be used in order to keep the example as
      simple as possible:</para>

      <programlisting>public class CustomItemWriter&lt;T&gt; implements ItemWriter&lt;T&gt; {

    List&lt;T&gt; output = TransactionAwareProxyFactory.createTransactionalList();

    public void write(List&lt;? extends T&gt; items) throws Exception {
        output.addAll(items);
    }

    public List&lt;T&gt; getOutput() {
        return output;
    }
}</programlisting>

      <section id="restartableWriter">
        <title>Making the <classname>ItemWriter</classname>
        Restartable</title>

        <para>To make the ItemWriter restartable we would follow the same
        process as for the <classname>ItemReader</classname>, adding and
        implementing the <classname>ItemStream</classname> interface to
        synchronize the execution context. In the example we might have to
        count the number of items processed and add that as a footer record.
        If we needed to do that, we could implement
        <classname>ItemStream</classname> in our
        <classname>ItemWriter</classname> so that the counter was
        reconstituted from the execution context if the stream was
        re-opened.</para>

        <para>In many realistic cases, custom ItemWriters also delegate to
        another writer that itself is restartable (e.g. when writing to a
        file), or else it writes to a transactional resource so doesn't need
        to be restartable because it is stateless. When you have a stateful
        writer you should probably also be sure to implement
        <classname>ItemStream</classname> as well as
        <classname>ItemWriter</classname>. Remember also that the client of
        the writer needs to be aware of the <classname>ItemStream</classname>,
        so you may need to register it as a stream in the configuration
        xml.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
