<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="repeat">
  <title>Repeat</title>

  <section id="repeatTemplate">
    <title>RepeatTemplate</title>

    <para>Batch processing is about repetitive actions - either as a simple
    optimization, or as part of a job. To strategize and generalize the
    repetition as well as to provide what amounts to an iterator framework,
    Spring Batch has the <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> interface.
    The <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> interface looks like
    this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RepeatOperations {

    RepeatStatus iterate(RepeatCallback callback) throws RepeatException;

}</programlisting>The callback is a simple interface that allows you to insert
    some business logic to be repeated:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RepeatCallback {

    RepeatStatus doInIteration(RepeatContext context) throws Exception;

}</programlisting>The callback is executed repeatedly until the implementation
    decides that the iteration should end. The return value in these
    interfaces is an enumeration that can either be
    <code>RepeatStatus.CONTINUABLE</code> or
    <code>RepeatStatus.FINISHED</code>. A <classname>RepeatStatus</classname>
    conveys information to the caller of the repeat operations about whether
    there is any more work to do. Generally speaking, implementations of
    <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> should inspect the
    <classname>RepeatStatus</classname> and use it as part of the decision to
    end the iteration. Any callback that wishes to signal to the caller that
    there is no more work to do can return
    <code>RepeatStatus.FINISHED</code>.</para>

    <para>The simplest general purpose implementation of
    <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> is
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname>. It could be used like this:</para>

    <programlisting>RepeatTemplate template = new RepeatTemplate();

template.setCompletionPolicy(new FixedChunkSizeCompletionPolicy(2));

template.iterate(new RepeatCallback() {

    public ExitStatus doInIteration(RepeatContext context) {
        // Do stuff in batch...
        return ExitStatus.CONTINUABLE;
    }

});</programlisting>

    <para>In the example we return <code>RepeatStatus.CONTINUABLE</code> to
    show that there is more work to do. The callback can also return
    <code>ExitStatus.FINISHED</code> if it wants to signal to the caller that
    there is no more work to do. Some iterations can be terminated by
    considerations intrinsic to the work being done in the callback, others
    are effectively infinite loops as far as the callback is concerned and the
    completion decision is delegated to an external policy as in the case
    above.</para>

    <section id="repeatContext">
      <title>RepeatContext</title>

      <para>The method parameter for the <classname>RepeatCallback</classname>
      is a <classname>RepeatContext</classname>. Many callbacks will simply
      ignore the context, but if necessary it can be used as an attribute bag
      to store transient data for the duration of the iteration. After the
      <methodname>iterate</methodname> method returns, the context will no
      longer exist.</para>

      <para>A <classname>RepeatContext</classname> will have a parent context
      if there is a nested iteration in progress. The parent context is
      occasionally useful for storing data that need to be shared between
      calls to <methodname>iterate</methodname>. This is the case for instance
      if you want to count the number of occurrences of an event in the
      iteration and remember it across subsequent calls.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="repeatStatus">
      <title>RepeatStatus</title>

      <para><classname>RepeatStatus</classname> is an enumeration used by
      Spring Batch to indicate whether processing has finished. These are
      possible <classname>RepeatStatus</classname> values:</para>

      <table>
        <title>ExitStatus Properties</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis></entry>

              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CONTINUABLE</entry>

              <entry>There is more work to do.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FINISHED</entry>

              <entry>No more repetitions should take place.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para><classname>RepeatStatus</classname> values can also be combined
      with a logical AND operation using the <methodname>and</methodname>()
      method in <classname>RepeatStatus</classname>. The effect of this is to
      do a logical AND on the continuable flag. In other words, if either
      status is <code>FINISHED</code>, then the result will be
      <code>FINISHED</code>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="completionPolicies">
    <title>Completion Policies</title>

    <para>Inside a <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> the termination of
    the loop in the <methodname>iterate</methodname> method is determined by a
    <classname>CompletionPolicy</classname> which is also a factory for the
    <classname>RepeatContext</classname>. The
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> has the responsibility to use the
    current policy to create a <classname>RepeatContext</classname> and pass
    that in to the <classname>RepeatCallback</classname> at every stage in the
    iteration. After a callback completes its
    <methodname>doInIteration</methodname>, the
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> has to make a call to the
    <classname>CompletionPolicy</classname> to ask it to update its state
    (which will be stored in the <classname>RepeatContext</classname>). Then
    it asks the policy if the iteration is complete.</para>

    <para>Spring Batch provides some simple general purpose implementations of
    <classname>CompletionPolicy</classname>. The
    <classname>SimpleCompletionPolicy</classname> just allows an execution up
    to a fixed number of times (with <code>RepeatStatus.FINISHED</code>
    forcing early completion at any time).</para>

    <para>Users might need to implement their own completion policies for more
    complicated decisions. For example, a batch processing window that
    prevents batch jobs from executing once the online systems are in use
    would require a custom policy.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="repeatExceptionHandling">
    <title>Exception Handling</title>

    <para>If there is an exception thrown inside a
    <classname>RepeatCallback</classname>, the
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> consults an
    <classname>ExceptionHandler</classname> which can decide whether or not to
    re-throw the exception.</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface ExceptionHandler {

    void handleException(RepeatContext context, Throwable throwable)
        throws RuntimeException;

}</programlisting>A common use case is to count the number of exceptions of a
    given type, and fail when a limit is reached. For this purpose Spring
    Batch provides the <classname>SimpleLimitExceptionHandler</classname> and
    slightly more flexible
    <classname>RethrowOnThresholdExceptionHandler</classname>. The
    <classname>SimpleLimitExceptionHandler</classname> has a limit property
    and an exception type that should be compared with the current exception -
    all subclasses of the provided type are also counted. Exceptions of the
    given type are ignored until the limit is reached, and then rethrown.
    Those of other types are always rethrown.</para>

    <para>An important optional property of the
    <classname>SimpleLimitExceptionHandler</classname> is the boolean flag
    <code>useParent</code>. It is false by default, so the limit is only
    accounted for in the current <classname>RepeatContext</classname>. When
    set to true, the limit is kept across sibling contexts in a nested
    iteration (e.g. a set of chunks inside a step).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="repeatListeners">
    <title>Listeners</title>

    <para>Often it is useful to be able to receive additional callbacks for
    cross cutting concerns across a number of different iterations. For this
    purpose Spring Batch provides the <classname>RepeatListener</classname>
    interface. The <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> allows users to
    register <classname>RepeatListener</classname>s, and they will be given
    callbacks with the <classname>RepeatContext</classname> and
    <classname>RepeatStatus</classname> where available during the
    iteration.</para>

    <para>The interface looks like this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RepeatListener {
    void before(RepeatContext context);

    void after(RepeatContext context, RepeatStatus result);

    void open(RepeatContext context);

    void onError(RepeatContext context, Throwable e);

    void close(RepeatContext context);
}</programlisting>The <methodname>open</methodname> and
    <methodname>close</methodname> callbacks come before and after the entire
    iteration. <methodname>before</methodname>, <methodname>after</methodname>
    and <methodname>onError</methodname> apply to the individual
    RepeatCallback calls.</para>

    <para>Note that when there is more than one listener, they are in a list,
    so there is an order. In this case <methodname>open</methodname> and
    <methodname>before</methodname> are called in the same order while
    <methodname>after</methodname>, <methodname>onError</methodname> and
    <methodname>close</methodname> are called in reverse order.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="repeatParallelProcessing">
    <title>Parallel Processing</title>

    <para>Implementations of <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> are not
    restricted to executing the callback sequentially. It is quite important
    that some implementations are able to execute their callbacks in parallel.
    To this end, Spring Batch provides the
    <classname>TaskExecutorRepeatTemplate</classname>, which uses the Spring
    <classname>TaskExecutor</classname> strategy to run the
    <classname>RepeatCallback</classname>. The default is to use a
    <classname>SynchronousTaskExecutor</classname>, which has the effect of
    executing the whole iteration in the same thread (the same as a normal
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname>).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="declarativeIteration">
    <title>Declarative Iteration</title>

    <para>Sometimes there is some business processing that you know you want
    to repeat every time it happens. The classic example of this is the
    optimization of a message pipeline - it is more efficient to process a
    batch of messages, if they are arriving frequently, than to bear the cost
    of a separate transaction for every message. Spring Batch provides an AOP
    interceptor that wraps a method call in a
    <classname>RepeatOperations</classname> for just this purpose. The
    <classname>RepeatOperationsInterceptor</classname> executes the
    intercepted method and repeats according to the
    <classname>CompletionPolicy</classname> in the provided
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname>.</para>

    <para>Here is an example of declarative iteration using the Spring AOP
    namespace to repeat a service call to a method called
    <methodname>processMessage</methodname> (for more detail on how to
    configure AOP interceptors see the Spring User Guide):</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;aop:config&gt;
    &lt;aop:pointcut id="transactional"
        expression="execution(* com..*Service.processMessage(..))" /&gt;
    &lt;aop:advisor pointcut-ref="transactional"
        advice-ref="retryAdvice" order="-1"/&gt;
&lt;/aop:config&gt;

&lt;bean id="retryAdvice" class="org.spr...RepeatOperationsInterceptor"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The example above uses a default
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> inside the interceptor. To change
    the policies, listeners etc. you only need to inject an instance of
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname> into the interceptor.</para>

    <para>If the intercepted method returns <code>void</code> then the
    interceptor always returns ExitStatus.CONTINUABLE (so there is a danger of
    an infinite loop if the <classname>CompletionPolicy</classname> does not
    have a finite end point). Otherwise it returns
    <code>ExitStatus.CONTINUABLE</code> until the return value from the
    intercepted method is null, at which point it returns
    <code>ExitStatus.FINISHED</code>. So the business logic inside the target
    method can signal that there is no more work to do by returning
    <code>null</code>, or by throwing an exception that is re-thrown by the
    <classname>ExceptionHandler</classname> in the provided
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
