<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="retry">
  <title>Retry</title>

  <section id="retryTemplate">
    <title>RetryTemplate</title>

    <para>To make processing more robust and less prone to failure, sometimes
    it helps to automatically retry a failed operation in case it might
    succeed on a subsequent attempt. Errors that are susceptible to this kind
    of treatment are transient in nature. For example a remote call to a web
    service or RMI service that fails because of a network glitch or a
    <classname>DeadLockLoserException</classname> in a database update may
    resolve themselves after a short wait. To automate the retry of such
    operations Spring Batch has the <classname>RetryOperations</classname>
    strategy. The <classname>RetryOperations</classname> interface looks like
    this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RetryOperations {

    &lt;T&gt; T execute(RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; retryCallback) throws Exception;

    &lt;T&gt; T execute(RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; retryCallback, RecoveryCallback&lt;T&gt; recoveryCallback) 
        throws Exception;

    &lt;T&gt; T execute(RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; retryCallback, RetryState retryState) 
        throws Exception, ExhaustedRetryException;

    &lt;T&gt; T execute(RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; retryCallback, RecoveryCallback&lt;T&gt; recoveryCallback, 
        RetryState retryState) throws Exception;

}</programlisting>The basic callback is a simple interface that allows you to
    insert some business logic to be retried:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; {

    T doWithRetry(RetryContext context) throws Throwable;

}</programlisting>The callback is executed and if it fails (by throwing an
    <classname>Exception</classname>), it will be retried until either it is
    successful, or the implementation decides to abort. There are a number of
    overloaded <methodname>execute</methodname> methods in the
    <classname>RetryOperations</classname> interface dealing with various use
    cases for recovery when all retry attempts are exhausted, and also with
    retry state, which allows clients and implementations to store information
    between calls (more on this later).</para>

    <para>The simplest general purpose implementation of
    <classname>RetryOperations</classname> is
    <classname>RetryTemplate</classname>. It could be used like this</para>

    <programlisting>RetryTemplate template = new RetryTemplate();

template.setRetryPolicy(new TimeoutRetryPolicy(30000L));

Foo result = template.execute(new RetryCallback&lt;Foo&gt;() {

    public Foo doWithRetry(RetryContext context) {
        // Do stuff that might fail, e.g. webservice operation
        return result;
    }

});</programlisting>

    <para>In the example we execute a web service call and return the result
    to the user. If that call fails then it is retried until a timeout is
    reached.</para>

    <section id="retryContext">
      <title>RetryContext</title>

      <para>The method parameter for the <classname>RetryCallback</classname>
      is a <classname>RetryContext</classname>. Many callbacks will simply
      ignore the context, but if necessary it can be used as an attribute bag
      to store data for the duration of the iteration.</para>

      <para>A <classname>RetryContext</classname> will have a parent context
      if there is a nested retry in progress in the same thread. The parent
      context is occasionally useful for storing data that need to be shared
      between calls to <methodname>execute</methodname>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="recoveryCallback">
      <title>RecoveryCallback</title>

      <para>When a retry is exhausted the
      <classname>RetryOperations</classname> can pass control to a different
      callback, the <classname>RecoveryCallback</classname>. To use this
      feature clients just pass in the callbacks together to the same method,
      for example:</para>

      <para><programlisting>Foo foo = template.execute(new RetryCallback&lt;Foo&gt;() {
    public Foo doWithRetry(RetryContext context) {
        // business logic here
    },
  new RecoveryCallback&lt;Foo&gt;() {
    Foo recover(RetryContext context) throws Exception {
          // recover logic here
    }
});</programlisting>If the business logic does not succeed before the template
      decides to abort, then the client is given the chance to do some
      alternate processing through the recovery callback.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="statelessRetry">
      <title>Stateless Retry</title>

      <para>In the simplest case, a retry is just a while loop: the
      <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> can just keep trying until it
      either succeeds or fails. The <classname>RetryContext</classname>
      contains some state to determine whether to retry or abort, but this
      state is on the stack and there is no need to store it anywhere
      globally, so we call this stateless retry. The distinction between
      stateless and stateful retry is contained in the implementation of the
      <classname>RetryPolicy</classname> (the
      <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> can handle both). In a stateless
      retry, the callback is always executed in the same thread on retry as
      when it failed.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="statefulRetry">
      <title>Stateful Retry</title>

      <para>Where the failure has caused a transactional resource to become
      invalid, there are some special considerations. This does not apply to a
      simple remote call because there is no transactional resource (usually),
      but it does sometimes apply to a database update, especially when using
      Hibernate. In this case it only makes sense to rethrow the exception
      that called the failure immediately so that the transaction can roll
      back and we can start a new valid one.</para>

      <para>In these cases a stateless retry is not good enough because the
      re-throw and roll back necessarily involve leaving the
      <code>RetryOperations.execute()</code> method and potentially losing the
      context that was on the stack. To avoid losing it we have to introduce a
      storage strategy to lift it off the stack and put it (at a minimum) in
      heap storage. For this purpose Spring Batch provides a storage strategy
      <classname>RetryContextCache</classname> which can be injected into the
      <classname>RetryTemplate</classname>. The default implementation of the
      <classname>RetryContextCache</classname> is in memory, using a simple
      <classname>Map</classname>. Advanced usage with multiple processes in a
      clustered environment might also consider implementing the
      <classname>RetryContextCache</classname> with a cluster cache of some
      sort (though, even in a clustered environment this might be
      overkill).</para>

      <para>Part of the responsibility of the
      <classname>RetryOperations</classname> is to recognize the failed
      operations when they come back in a new execution (and usually wrapped
      in a new transaction). To facilitate this, Spring Batch provides the
      <classname>RetryState</classname> abstraction. This works in conjunction
      with a special <classname>execute</classname> methods in the
      <classname>RetryOperations</classname>.</para>

      <para>The way the failed operations are recognized is by identifying the
      state across multiple invocations of the retry. To identify the state,
      the user can provide an <classname>RetryState</classname> object that is
      responsible for returning a unique key identifying the item. The
      identifier is used as a key in the
      <classname>RetryContextCache</classname>.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Be very careful with the implementation of
        <code>Object.equals()</code> and <code>Object.hashCode()</code> in the
        key returned by <classname>RetryState</classname>. The best advice is
        to use a business key to identify the items. In the case of a JMS
        message the message ID can be used.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>When the retry is exhausted there is also the option to handle the
      failed item in a different way, instead of calling the
      <classname>RetryCallback</classname> (which is presumed now to be likely
      to fail). Just like in the stateless case, this option is provided by
      the <classname>RecoveryCallback</classname>, which can be provided by
      passing it in to the <classname>execute</classname> method of
      <classname>RetryOperations</classname>.</para>

      <para>The decision to retry or not is actually delegated to a regular
      <classname>RetryPolicy</classname>, so the usual concerns about limits
      and timeouts can be injected there (see below).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="retryPolicies">
    <title>Retry Policies</title>

    <para>Inside a <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> the decision to retry
    or fail in the <methodname>execute</methodname> method is determined by a
    <classname>RetryPolicy</classname> which is also a factory for the
    <classname>RetryContext</classname>. The
    <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> has the responsibility to use the
    current policy to create a <classname>RetryContext</classname> and pass
    that in to the <classname>RetryCallback</classname> at every attempt.
    After a callback fails the <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> has to
    make a call to the <classname>RetryPolicy</classname> to ask it to update
    its state (which will be stored in the
    <classname>RetryContext</classname>), and then it asks the policy if
    another attempt can be made. If another attempt cannot be made (e.g. a
    limit is reached or a timeout is detected) then the policy is also
    responsible for handling the exhausted state. Simple implementations will
    just throw <classname>RetryExhaustedException</classname> which will cause
    any enclosing transaction to be rolled back. More sophisticated
    implementations might attempt to take some recovery action, in which case
    the transaction can remain intact.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>Failures are inherently either retryable or not - if the same
      exception is always going to be thrown from the business logic, it
      doesn't help to retry it. So don't retry on all exception types - try to
      focus on only those exceptions that you expect to be retryable. It's not
      usually harmful to the business logic to retry more aggressively, but
      it's wasteful because if a failure is deterministic there will be time
      spent retrying something that you know in advance is fatal.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>Spring Batch provides some simple general purpose implementations of
    stateless <classname>RetryPolicy</classname>, for example a
    <classname>SimpleRetryPolicy</classname>, and the
    <classname>TimeoutRetryPolicy</classname> used in the example
    above.</para>

    <para>The <classname>SimpleRetryPolicy</classname> just allows a retry on
    any of a named list of exception types, up to a fixed number of times. It
    also has a list of "fatal" exceptions that should never be retried, and
    this list overrides the retryable list so that it can be used to give
    finer control over the retry behavior:</para>

    <programlisting>SimpleRetryPolicy policy = new SimpleRetryPolicy(5);
// Retry on all exceptions (this is the default)
policy.setRetryableExceptions(new Class[] {Exception.class});
// ... but never retry IllegalStateException
policy.setFatalExceptions(new Class[] {IllegalStateException.class});

// Use the policy...
RetryTemplate template = new RetryTemplate();
template.setRetryPolicy(policy);
template.execute(new RetryCallback&lt;Foo&gt;() {
    public Foo doWithRetry(RetryContext context) {
        // business logic here
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>There is also a more flexible implementation called
    <classname>ExceptionClassifierRetryPolicy</classname>, which allows the
    user to configure different retry behavior for an arbitrary set of
    exception types though the <classname>ExceptionClassifier</classname>
    abstraction. The policy works by calling on the classifier to convert an
    exception into a delegate <classname>RetryPolicy</classname>, so for
    example, one exception type can be retried more times before failure than
    another by mapping it to a different policy.</para>

    <para>Users might need to implement their own retry policies for more
    customized decisions. For instance, if there is a well-known,
    solution-specific, classification of exceptions into retryable and not
    retryable.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="backoffPolicies">
    <title>Backoff Policies</title>

    <para>When retrying after a transient failure it often helps to wait a bit
    before trying again, because usually the failure is caused by some problem
    that will only be resolved by waiting. If a
    <classname>RetryCallback</classname> fails, the
    <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> can pause execution according to the
    <classname>BackoffPolicy</classname> in place.</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface BackoffPolicy {

    BackOffContext start(RetryContext context);

    void backOff(BackOffContext backOffContext) 
        throws BackOffInterruptedException;

}</programlisting>A <classname>BackoffPolicy</classname> is free to implement
    the backOff in any way it chooses. The policies provided by Spring Batch
    out of the box all use <code>Object.wait()</code>. A common use case is to
    backoff with an exponentially increasing wait period, to avoid two retries
    getting into lock step and both failing - this is a lesson learned from
    the ethernet. For this purpose Spring Batch provides the
    <classname>ExponentialBackoffPolicy</classname>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="retryListeners">
    <title>Listeners</title>

    <para>Often it is useful to be able to receive additional callbacks for
    cross cutting concerns across a number of different retries. For this
    purpose Spring Batch provides the <classname>RetryListener</classname>
    interface. The <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> allows users to
    register <classname>RetryListener</classname>s, and they will be given
    callbacks with the <classname>RetryContext</classname> and
    <classname>Throwable</classname> where available during the
    iteration.</para>

    <para>The interface looks like this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public interface RetryListener {

    void open(RetryContext context, RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; callback);

    void onError(RetryContext context, RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; callback, Throwable e);

    void close(RetryContext context, RetryCallback&lt;T&gt; callback, Throwable e);
}</programlisting>The <methodname>open</methodname> and
    <methodname>close</methodname> callbacks come before and after the entire
    retry in the simplest case and <methodname>onError</methodname> applies to
    the individual <classname>RetryCallback</classname> calls. The
    <methodname>close</methodname> method might also receive a
    <classname>Throwable</classname>; if there has been an error it is the
    last one thrown by the <classname>RetryCallback</classname>.</para>

    <para>Note that when there is more than one listener, they are in a list,
    so there is an order. In this case <methodname>open</methodname> will be
    called in the same order while <methodname>onError</methodname> and
    <methodname>close</methodname> will be called in reverse order.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="declarativeRetry">
    <title>Declarative Retry</title>

    <para>Sometimes there is some business processing that you know you want
    to retry every time it happens. The classic example of this is the remote
    service call. Spring Batch provides an AOP interceptor that wraps a method
    call in a <classname>RetryOperations</classname> for just this purpose.
    The <classname>RetryOperationsInterceptor</classname> executes the
    intercepted method and retries on failure according to the
    <classname>RetryPolicy</classname> in the provided
    <classname>RepeatTemplate</classname>.</para>

    <para>Here is an example of declarative iteration using the Spring AOP
    namespace to repeat a service call to a method called
    <methodname>remoteCall</methodname> (for more detail on how to configure
    AOP interceptors see the Spring User Guide):</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;aop:config&gt;
    &lt;aop:pointcut id="transactional"
        expression="execution(* com..*Service.remoteCall(..))" /&gt;
    &lt;aop:advisor pointcut-ref="transactional"
        advice-ref="retryAdvice" order="-1"/&gt;
&lt;/aop:config&gt;

&lt;bean id="retryAdvice"
    class="org.springframework.batch.retry.interceptor.RetryOperationsInterceptor"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The example above uses a default
    <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> inside the interceptor. To change the
    policies or listeners, you only need to inject an instance of
    <classname>RetryTemplate</classname> into the interceptor.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
