<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<glossary id="glossary">
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Spring Batch Glossary</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Batch</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An accumulation of business transactions over time.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Batch Application Style</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Term used to designate batch as an application style in its own
        right similar to online, Web or SOA. It has standard elements of
        input, validation, transformation of information to business model,
        business processing and output. In addition, it requires monitoring at
        a macro level.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Batch Processing</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The handling of a batch of many business transactions that have
        accumulated over a period of time (e.g. an hour, day, week, month, or
        year). It is the application of a process, or set of processes, to
        many data entities or objects in a repetitive and predictable fashion
        with either no manual element, or a separate manual element for error
        processing.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Batch Window</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The time frame within which a batch job must complete. This can
        be constrained by other systems coming online, other dependent jobs
        needing to execute or other factors specific to the batch
        environment.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Step</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>It is the main batch task or unit of work controller. It
        initializes the business logic, and controls the transaction
        environment based on commit interval setting, etc.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Tasklet</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A component created by application developer to process the
        business logic for a Step.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Batch Job Type</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Job Types describe application of jobs for particular type of
        processing. Common areas are interface processing (typically flat
        files), forms processing (either for online pdf generation or print
        formats), report processing.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Driving Query</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A driving query identifies the set of work for a job to do; the
        job then breaks that work into individual units of work. For instance,
        identify all financial transactions that have a status of "pending
        transmission" and send them to our partner system. The driving query
        returns a set of record IDs to process; each record ID then becomes a
        unit of work. A driving query may involve a join (if the criteria for
        selection falls across two or more tables) or it may work with a
        single table.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Item</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An item represents the smallest ammount of complete data for
        processing. In the simplest terms, this might mean a line in a file, a
        row in a database table, or a particular element in an XML
        file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Logicial Unit of Work (LUW)</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A batch job iterates through a driving query (or another input
        source such as a file) to perform the set of work that the job must
        accomplish. Each iteration of work performed is a unit of work.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Commit Interval</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of LUWs processed within a single transaction.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Partitioning</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Splitting a job into multiple threads where each thread is
        responsible for a subset of the overall data to be processed. The
        threads of execution may be within the same JVM or they may span JVMs
        in a clustered environment that supports workload balancing.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Staging Table</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A table that holds temporary data while it is being
        processed.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Restartable</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A job that can be executed again and will assume the same
        identity as when run initially. In othewords, it is has the same job
        instance id.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Rerunnable</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A job that is restartable and manages its own state in terms of
        previous run's record processing. An example of a rerunnable step is
        one based on a driving query. If the driving query can be formed so
        that it will limit the processed rows when the job is restarted than
        it is re-runnable. This is managed by the application logic. Often
        times a condition is added to the where statement to limit the rows
        returned by the driving query with something like "and processedFlag
        != true".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Repeat</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>One of the most basic units of batch processing, that defines
        repeatability calling a portion of code until it is finished, and
        while there is no error. Typically a batch process would be repeatable
        as long as there is input.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Retry</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Simplifies the execution of operations with retry semantics most
        frequently associated with handling transactional output exceptions.
        Retry is slightly different from repeat, rather than continually
        calling a block of code, retry is stateful, and continually calls the
        same block of code with the same input, until it either succeeds, or
        some type of retry limit has been exceeded. It is only generally
        useful if a subsequent invocation of the operation might succeed
        because something in the environment has improved.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Recover</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Recover operations handle an exception in such a way that a
        repeat process is able to continue.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Skip</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Skip is a recovery strategy often used on file input sources as
        the strategy for ignoring bad input records that failed
        validation.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>
