<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="spring-batch-infrastructure">
  <title>ItemReaders and ItemWriters</title>

  <section>
    <title id="i-0.spring-batch-infrastructure-overview">Introduction</title>

    <para>All batch processing can be described in its most simple form as
    reading in large ammounts of data, performing some type of calculation or
    transformation, and writing the result out. Spring Batch provides two key
    interfaces to help perform bulk reading and writing: ItemReader and
    ItemWriter</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.1">ItemReader</title>

    <para>Although a simple concept, <emphasis
    role="bold">ItemReader</emphasis>s are the means for providing data from
    many different types of input. The most general examples include:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flat File- Flat File Item Readers read lines of data from a
          flat file that typically describe records with fields of data
          defined by fixed positions in the file or delimited by some special
          character (e.g. comma).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XML - XML ItemReaders process XML independently of
          technologies used for parsing, mapping and validating objects. Input
          data allows for the validation of and XML file against and XSD
          schema.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Database - A database resource accessed that returns
          resultsets that can be mapped to objects for processing. The default
          SQL Input Sources invoke a RowMapper to return objects, keep track
          of the current row if restart is required, basic statistics, and
          some transaction enhancements that will be explained later.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>There are many more possbilities, but we'll focus on the
    basic ones for this chapter. A complete list of all available ItemReaders
    can be found in Appendix A.</para>

    <para>The Item Reader is a basic interface for generic input
    operations:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemReader {

  Object read() throws Exception;

  void mark() throws MarkFailedException;

  void reset() throws ResetFailedException;
}
</programlisting>

    <para>The read() method defines the most essential contract of the
    ItemReader, calling it returns one Item, returning null if no more items
    are left. An item might represent a line in a file, a row in a database,
    or an element in an xml file. It is generally expected that these will be
    mapped to a useable domain object (i.e. Trade or Foo, etc) but there is no
    requirement in the contract to do so.</para>

    <para>The mark() and reset() methods are important due to the
    transactional nature of batch processing. Mark() will be called before
    reading begins. Calling reset() at anytime will position the ItemReader to
    its position when mark() was last called. The semantics are very similar
    to java.io.Reader.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.1.4">ItemWriter</title>

    <para>Item Writers are similar in functionality to an ItemReader with the
    exception that the operations are reversed. They still need to be located,
    opened and closed but they differ in the case that we write out, rather
    than reading in. In the case of databases or queues these may be inserts,
    updates or sends. The format of the serialization of the output source is
    specific for every batch job.</para>

    <para>As with ItemReader, ItemWriter is a fairly generic interface:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemWriter {

  void write(Object item) throws Exception;

  void flush() throws FlushFailedException;

  void clear() throws ClearFailedException;
}
</programlisting>

    <para>As with read() on ItemReader, write provides the basic contract of
    ItemWriter, it will attempt to write out the item passed in as long as it
    is open. As with mark() and reset(), flush() and clear() are necessary due
    to the nature of batch processing. Because it is generally expected that
    items will be 'batched' together into a chunk, and then output, it is
    expected that an ItemWriter will perform some type of buffering. flush()
    will empty the buffer by actually writing the items out, whereas clear
    will simply throw the contents of the buffer away. In most cases, a Step
    implementation will call flush() before a commit and clear() in case of
    rollback.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ItemStream</title>

    <para>Both ItemReaders and ItemWriters serve their individual purposes
    well, but there is a common concern among both of them that necessitates
    another interface. In general, as part of the scope of a batch job,
    readers and writers need to be opened, closed, and require a mechanism for
    persisting state:</para>

    <programlisting>public interface ItemStream {

  void open(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws StreamException;

  void update(ExecutionContext executionContext);
  
  void close(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws StreamException;
}
</programlisting>

    <para>Before describing each method, it's worth breifly mentioning the
    ExecutionContext. An ExecutionContext is created for Each StepExecution to
    allow users to store the state of a particular execution, with the
    expectation that it will be returned if the same JobInstance is started
    again. For those familiar with Quartz, the semantics are very similar to a
    Quartz JobDataMap. Open() should be called before any calls to read or
    write and is expected to open any resources such as files or obtain
    connections. As mentioned before, if expected data is found in the
    ExecutionContext, it may be used to start the ItemReader or ItemWriter at
    a location other than its initial state. Converely, close will be called
    to ensure any resources allocated during open will be released safely.
    Update() is called primarily to ensure that any state currently being held
    is loaded into the provided ExecutionContext. In most cases, this method
    will be called before committing, to ensure that the current state is
    persisted in the database before commit.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.1.2">Flat Files</title>

    <para>One of the most common mechanisms for interchanging bulk data has
    always been the flat file. Unlike XML, which has an aggreed upon standard
    for defining how it is structured (XSD), anyone reading a flat file must
    understand ahead of time exactly how the file is structured. In general,
    all flat files fall into two general types: Delimited and Fixed
    Length.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The FieldSet</title>

      <para>When working with flat files in Spring Batch, regardless of
      whether it is for input or output, one of the most important classes is
      the FieldSet. Many architectures and libraries contain abstractions for
      helping you read in from a file, but they usually return a String or an
      array of Strings. This really only gets you halfway there. A FieldSet is
      Spring Batch’s abstraction for enabling the binding of fields from a
      file resource. It allows developers to work with file input in much the
      same way as they would work with database input. A FieldSet is
      conceptually very similar to a Jdbc ResultSet. FieldSets only require
      one argument, a String array of tokens. Optionally you can also
      configure in the names of the fields so that the fields may be accessed
      either by index or name as patterned after ResultSet. In code it means
      it's as simple as:</para>

      <programlisting>String[] tokens = new String[]{"foo", "1", "true"};
FieldSet fs = new DefaultFieldSet(tokens);
String name = fs.readString(0);
int value = fs.readInt(1);
boolean booleanValue = fs.readBoolean(2);</programlisting>

      <para>There are many more options on the FieldSet interface, such as
      Date, long, BigDecimal, etc. The biggest advantage of the FieldSet is
      that it provides consistent parsing of flat file input. Rather than each
      batch job parsing differenty in potentially unexpected ways, it can be
      consistent, both when erroring out due to a format exception, or when
      doing simple data conversions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="infrastructure.1.2.1">FlatFileItemReader</title>

      <para>One of the most common tasks performed in batch jobs involve
      reading from some type of file. A flat file is basically any type of
      file that contains at most two-dimensional (tabular) data. Reading flat
      files in the Spring Batch framework is facilitated by the class
      <emphasis role="bold">FlatFileItemReader</emphasis>, which provides
      basic functionality for reading and parsing flat files. In addition,
      there are default implementations of the <emphasis
      role="bold">Skippable</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">ItemStream</emphasis> interfaces that solve the majority of
      file processing needs.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">FlatFileItemReader</emphasis> class has
      several properties. The three most important of these properties are
      <emphasis role="bold">resource</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">fieldSetMapper</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">tokenizer</emphasis>, which define the resource from which
      data will be read and the method by which the read data will be
      converted to distinct fields. The <emphasis
      role="bold">fieldSetMapper</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">tokenizer</emphasis> interfaces will be explored more in the
      next sections. In addition, we'll explore integration with the file
      system via the resource property. The <emphasis
      role="bold">resource</emphasis> property represents a Spring Core
      <emphasis role="bold">Resource</emphasis>. Documentation explaining how
      to create beans of this type can be found in <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/resources.html"><citetitle>Spring
      Framework, Chapter 4.Resources</citetitle></ulink>. Therefore, this
      guide will not go into the details of creating <emphasis
      role="bold">Resource</emphasis> objects except to make a couple of
      points on the locating files to process within a batch environment.
      Tokenizers and field set mappers will be discussed a bit later.</para>

      <para>As mentioned, the location of the file is defined by the resource
      property. There are only a few methods exposed through a resource
      service. A resource is used to help locate, open, and close resources.
      It can be as simple as: <programlisting>
        Resource resource = new FileSystemResource("resources/trades.csv");
        </programlisting></para>

      <para>In complex batch environments the directory structures are often
      managed by the EAI infrastructure where drop zones for external
      interfaces are established for moving files from ftp locations to batch
      processing locations and vice versa. File moving utilities are beyond
      the scope of the spring batch architecture but it is not unusual for
      batch job streams to include file moving utilities as steps in the job
      stream. It's sufficient to know that the batch architecture only needs
      to know how to locate the files to be processed. Spring Batch begins the
      process of feeding the data into the pipe from this starting
      point.</para>

      <para>The flat file reader uses a ResourceLineReader object to read from
      the file. Optionally, you can specify a <emphasis
      role="bold">RecordSeparatorPolicy</emphasis> through the
      recordSeparatorPolicy property. This can be used to configure more
      low-level features, such as what constitutes the end of a line and
      whether to continue quoted strings over newlines, among other
      things.</para>

      <para>The other properties in the flat file readers allow you to further
      specify how your data will be interpreted: <table>
          <title>Flat File Item Reader Properties</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="center" />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Property</entry>

                <entry align="center">Type</entry>

                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">encoding</entry>

                <entry align="left">String</entry>

                <entry align="left">Specifies what text encoding to use -
                default is "ISO-8859-1"</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">comments</entry>

                <entry align="left">String[]</entry>

                <entry align="left">Specifies line prefixes that indicate
                comment rows</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">linesToSkip</entry>

                <entry align="left">int</entry>

                <entry align="left">Number of lines to ignore at the top of
                the file</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">firstLineIsHeader</entry>

                <entry align="left">boolean</entry>

                <entry align="left">Indicates that the first line of the file
                is a header containing field names. If the column names have
                not been set yet and the tokenizer extends
                AbstractLineTokenizer, field names will be set automatically
                from this line</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>

      <section>
        <title>FieldSetMapper</title>

        <para>Field set mappers used by the FlatFileItemReader implement the
        FieldSetMapper interface. This interface defines a single method,
        mapLine, which takes a FieldSet object and maps its contents to some
        Object. This object may be a custom DTO or domain object, or it could
        be as simple as an array, depending on your needs. The <emphasis
        role="bold">FieldSetMapper</emphasis> is used in conjunction with the
        tokenizer to translate a line of data from a resource into an object
        of the desired type:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface FieldSetMapper {
  
  public Object mapLine(FieldSet fs);

}</programlisting>

        <para>As you can see, the pattern used is exatly the same as RowMapper
        used by JdbcTemplate.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>LineTokenizer</title>

        <para>Because there can be many formats of flat file data, which all
        need to be converted to a FieldSet so that a FieldSetMapper can create
        a useful domain object from them, an abstraction for turning a line of
        input into a FieldSet is necessary. In Spring Batch, this is called
        the LineTokenizer:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface LineTokenizer {
  
  FieldSet tokenize(String line);

}
</programlisting>

        <para>The contract of a LineTokenizer is such that, given a line of
        input (in theory the String could encompass more than one line) a
        FieldSet representing the line will be returned. This will then be
        based to a FieldSetMapper. Spring Batch contains the following
        LineTokenizers:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>DelmitedLineTokenizer - Used for files that separate records
            by a delimiter. The most common is a comma, but pipes or
            semicolons are often used as well</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>FixedLengthTokenizer - Used for tokenizing files where each
            record is separated by a 'fixed width' that must be defined per
            record.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>PrefixMatchingCompositeLineTokenizer - Tokenizer that
            determines which among a list of Tokenizers should be used on a
            particular line by checking against a prefix.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simple Delimited File Reading Example</title>

        <para>Now that the basic interfaces for reading in flat files have
        been defined, a simple example explaining how they work together is
        helpful. In it's most simple form, the flow when reading a line form a
        file is this:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read one line from the file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Pass the string line into the LineTokenizer#tokenize()
            method, in order to retrieve a FieldSet</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Pass the FieldSet returned from tokenizing to a
            FieldSetMapper, returning the result from the ItemReader#read()
            method</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The following example will be used to illustrate this using an
        actual domain scenario. This particular batch job reads in football
        players from the following file:<programlisting>ID,lastName,firstName,position,birthYear,debutYear
"AbduKa00,Abdul-Jabbar,Karim,rb,1974,1996",
"AbduRa00,Abdullah,Rabih,rb,1975,1999",
"AberWa00,Abercrombie,Walter,rb,1959,1982",
"AbraDa00,Abramowicz,Danny,wr,1945,1967",
"AdamBo00,Adams,Bob,te,1946,1969",
"AdamCh00,Adams,Charlie,wr,1979,2003"        </programlisting></para>

        <para>We want to map this data to the following Player domain object:
        <programlisting>
          public class Player implements Serializable {
        
          private String ID; 
          private String lastName; 
          private String firstName; 
          private String position; 
          private int birthYear; 
          private int debutYear;
        
          public String toString() {
                
                return "PLAYER:ID=" + ID + ",Last Name=" + lastName + 
                ",First Name=" + firstName + ",Position=" + position + 
                ",Birth Year=" + birthYear + ",DebutYear=" + 
                debutYear;
          }

          // setters and getters...
          }
          </programlisting></para>

        <para>In order to map a FieldSet into our Player object, we need to
        create a FieldSetMapper that returns players:</para>

        <para><programlisting>
        protected static class PlayerFieldSetMapper implements FieldSetMapper {
                public Object mapLine(FieldSet fieldSet) {
                        Player player = new Player();

                        player.setID(fieldSet.readString(0));
                        player.setLastName(fieldSet.readString(1));
                        player.setFirstName(fieldSet.readString(2)); 
                        player.setPosition(fieldSet.readString(3));
                        player.setBirthYear(fieldSet.readInt(4));
                        player.setDebutYear(fieldSet.readInt(5));

                        return player;
                }
        }
      </programlisting></para>

        <para>We can then read in from the filed by correctly constructing our
        FlatFileItemReader and calling read():</para>

        <programlisting>FlatFileItemReader itemReader = new FlatFileItemReader();
itemReader.setResource = new FileSystemResource("resources/players.csv");
//DelimitedLineTokenizer defaults to comma as it's delimiter
itemReader.setLineTokenizer(new DelimitedLineTokenizer());
itemReader.setFieldSetMapper(new PlayerFieldSetMapper());
itemReader.read();
</programlisting>

        <para>Each call to read will return a new Player object from each line
        in the file. When the end of the file is reached, null will be
        returned.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Mapping fields by name</title>

        <para>There is one additional functionality that is similar in
        function to a JDBC ResultSet. The names of the fields can be injected
        into the Tokenizer to increase the readability of the mapping
        function. We can expose this behavior by adding the following. First,
        we tell the tokenizer what the names of the fields in the fieldset
        are:</para>

        <para><programlisting>
    tokenizer.setNames(new String[] {"ID", "lastName","firstName","position","birthYear","debutYear"}); 
          </programlisting></para>

        <para>and provide a mapper that uses this information as
        follows:</para>

        <para><programlisting>
    public class PlayerMapper implements FieldSetMapper {
        public Object mapLine(FieldSet fs) {
                        
           if(fs == null){
              return null;
           }
                        
           Player player = new Player();
           player.setID(fs.readString("ID"));
           player.setLastName(fs.readString("lastName"));
           player.setFirstName(fs.readString("firstName"));
           player.setPosition(fs.readString("position"));
           player.setDebutYear(fs.readInt("debutYear"));
           player.setBirthYear(fs.readInt("birthYear"));
                        
           return player;
        }

   }        </programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Automapping FieldSets to Domain Objects</title>

        <para>For many, having to write a specific FieldSetMapper is equally
        as cumbersome as writing a specific RowMapper for a JdbcTemplate.
        Spring Batch makes this easier by providing a FieldSetMapper that
        automatically maps fields by matching a field name with a setter using
        the JavaBean spec. Again using the footbal example, the FieldSetMapper
        configuration looks like the following:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="fieldSetMapper"
      class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.mapping.BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper"&gt;
  &lt;property name="prototypeBeanName" value="player" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="person"
      class="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Player"
      scope="prototype" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>For each entry in the FieldSet, the mapper will look for a
        corresponding setter on a new instance of the Player object (for this
        reason, prototype scope is required) in the same way the Spring
        container will look for setters matching a property name. Each
        available field in the FieldSet will be mapped, and the resultant
        Player object will be returned, only there was no code
        required.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Fixed Length file formats</title>

        <para>So far only delimited files have been discussed in much detail,
        however, they respresent only half of the file reading picture. Many
        organizations that use flat files use fixed length formats. An example
        field length file is below:</para>

        <programlisting>UK21341EAH4121131.11customer1
UK21341EAH4221232.11customer2
UK21341EAH4321333.11customer3
UK21341EAH4421434.11customer4
UK21341EAH4521535.11customer5</programlisting>

        <para>While this looks like one large field, it actually represent 4
        distinct fields:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>ISIN: Unique identifier for the item being order - 12
            characters long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Quantity: Number of this item being ordered - 3 characters
            long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Price: Price of the item - 4 characters long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Customer: Id of the customer ordering the item - 8
            characters long.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>When configuring the FixedLengthLineTokenizer, each of these
        lengths must be provided in the form of ranges:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="fixedLengthLineTokenizer"
      class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.transform.FixedLengthTokenizer"&gt;
  &lt;property name="names" value="ISIN, Quantity, Price, Customer" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="columns" value="1-12, 13-15, 16-20, 21-29" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This LineTokenizer will return the same FieldSet as if a
        dlimiter had been used, allowing the same approachs above to be used
        such as the BeanWrapperFieldSetMapper, in a way that is ignorant of
        how the actual line was parsed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple record types within a single file</title>

        <para>All of the file reading examples up to this point have all made
        a key assumption for simplicity's sake: one record equals one line.
        However, this may not always be the case. It's very common that a file
        might have records spanning multiple lines with multiple formats. The
        following excerpt from a file illustrates this:</para>

        <programlisting>HEA;0013100345;2007-02-15
NCU;Smith;Peter;;T;20014539;F
BAD;;Oak Street 31/A;;Small Town;00235;IL;US
SAD;Smith, Elizabeth;Elm Street 17;;Some City;30011;FL;United States
BIN;VISA;VISA-12345678903
LIT;1044391041;37.49;0;0;4.99;2.99;1;45.47
LIT;2134776319;221.99;5;0;7.99;2.99;1;221.87
SIN;UPS;EXP;DELIVER ONLY ON WEEKDAYS
FOT;2;2;267.34</programlisting>

        <para>Everything between the line starting with 'HEA' and the line
        starting with 'FOT' is considered one record. The
        PrefixMatchingCompositeLineTokenizer makes this easier by matching the
        prefix in a line with a particular tokenizer:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="orderFileDescriptor"
      class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.transform.PrefixMatchingCompositeLineTokenizer"&gt;
  &lt;property name="tokenizers"&gt;
   &lt;map&gt;
    &lt;entry key="HEA" value-ref="headerRecordDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="FOT" value-ref="footerRecordDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="BCU" value-ref="businessCustomerLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="NCU" value-ref="customerLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="BAD" value-ref="billingAddressLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="SAD" value-ref="shippingAddressLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="BIN" value-ref="billingLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="SIN" value-ref="shippingLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="LIT" value-ref="itemLineDescriptor" /&gt;
    &lt;entry key="" value-ref="defaultLineDescriptor" /&gt;
   &lt;/map&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This ensures that the line will be parsed correctly, which is
        especially important for fixed length input, with the correct field
        names. Any users of the FlatFileItemReader in this scenario must
        continue calling read() until the footer for the record is returned,
        allowing them to return a complete order as one 'item'.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>FlatFileItemWriter</title>

      <para>Writing out to flat files has the same problems and issues that
      reading in from a file must overcome. It must be able to write out in
      either dlimited or fixed length formats in a transactional
      mannger.</para>

      <section>
        <title>LineAggregator</title>

        <para>Just like file reading's LineTokenizer interface is necessary to
        take a string and split it into tokens, file writing must have a way
        to aggregate multiple fields into a single string for writing to a
        file. In Spring Batch this is the LineAggregator:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface LineAggregator {

 public String aggregate(FieldSet fieldSet);
}
</programlisting>

        <para>The LineAggregator is exactly the opposite of a LineTokenizer.
        LineTokenizer takes a string and returns a FieldSet, wheras
        LineAggreator takes a FieldSet and returns a string. As with reading
        there are two types: DelimitedLineAggregator and
        FixedLengthLineAggregator.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FieldSetCreator</title>

        <para>Because the LineAggregator interface uses a FieldSet as it's
        mechanism for converting to a string, there needs to be an interface
        that describes how to convert from an object into a FieldSet:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface FieldSetCreator {

  FieldSet mapItem(Object data);

}</programlisting>

        <para>As with LineTokenizer and LineAggregator, FieldSetCreator is the
        polar opposite of FieldSetMapper. FieldSetMapper takes a FieldSet and
        returns a mapped object, whereas a FieldSetCreator takes an Object and
        returns a FieldSet.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simple Delimited File Writing Example</title>

        <para>Now that both the LineAggregator and FieldSetCreator interfaces
        have been defined, the basic flow of writing can be explained:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The object to be written is passed to the FieldSetCreator in
            order to obtain a FieldSet.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The returned FieldSet is passed to the LineAggregator</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The returned string is written to the configured
            file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The following excerpt from the FlatFileItemWriter expresses this
        in code:</para>

        <programlisting>public void write(Object data) throws Exception {
  FieldSet fieldSet = fieldSetCreator.mapItem(data);
  getOutputState().write(lineAggregator.aggregate(fieldSet) + LINE_SEPARATOR);
}</programlisting>

        <para>A simple configuration with the smallest ammount of setters
        would look like the following:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="itemWriter"
      class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.FlatFileItemWriter"&gt;
  &lt;property name="resource"
            value="file:target/test-outputs/20070122.testStream.multilineStep.txt" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="fieldSetCreator"&gt;
    &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.io.file.mapping.PassThroughFieldSetMapper"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Handling file creation</title>

        <para>FlatFileItemReader has a very simple relationship with file
        resources. When the reader is initialized, it opens the file if it
        exists, and throws an exception if it does not. File writing isn't
        quite so simple. At first glance it seems like a similiar straight
        forward contract should exist for FlatFileItemWriter, if the file
        already exists, throw an exception, if it does not, create it and
        start writing. Job restart throws a bit of a kink into this. In the
        normal restart scenario, the contract is reversed, if the file exists
        start writing to it from the last known good position, if it does not,
        throw an exception. However, what happens if the file name for this
        job is always the same? In this case, you would want to delete the
        file if it exists, unless it's a restart. Because of this possibility,
        the FlatFileItemWriter contains the property, shouldDeleteIfExists.
        Setting this property to true will cause an existing file with the
        same name to be deleted when the writer is opened.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.2.3">XML Item Readers and Writers</title>

    <para>Spring Batch provides transactional infrastructure for both reading
    XML records and mapping them to Java objects as well as writing Java
    objects as XML records.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Constraints on streaming XML</title>

      <para>The StAX API is used for I/O as other standard XML parsing APIs do
      not fit batch processing requirements (DOM loads the whole input into
      memory at once and SAX controls the parsing process allowing the user
      only to provide callbacks).</para>
    </note>

    <para>Lets take a closer look how XML input and output works in batch.
    First, there are a few concepts that vary from file reading and writing
    but are common across Spring Batch XML processing. With XML processing
    instead of lines of records (FieldSets) that need to be tokenized, it is
    assumed an XML resource is a collection of 'fragments' corresponding to
    individual records. Note that OXM tools are designed to work with
    standalone XML documents rather than XML fragments cut out of an XML
    document, therefore the Spring Batch infrastructure needs to work around
    this fact (as described below).</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="../../../../target/site/reference/images/xmlinput.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="../../resources/reference/images/xmlinput.PNG"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Figure X: XML Inputs</para></caption>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Spring Batch uses Object/XML Mapping (OXM) to bind fragments to
    objects. However, Spring Batch is not tied to any particular OXM
    technology. Typical use is to delegate <ulink
    url="http://static.springframework.org/spring-ws/site/reference/html/oxm.html"><citetitle>OXM
    to Spring WS</citetitle></ulink>, which provides uniform abstraction for
    the most popular OXM technologies. The dependency on Spring WS is optional
    and you can choose to implement Spring Batch specific interfaces if
    desired. The relationship to the technologies that OXM supports can be
    shown as the following:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="../../../../target/site/reference/images/oxm-fragments.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="../../resources/reference/images/oxm-fragments.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Figure X: OXM Binding</para></caption>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Now with and introduction into OXM and how one can use XML fragments
    to represent records, let's take a closer look at Item Readers and Item
    Writers.</para>

    <section>
      <title>StaxEventItemReader</title>

      <para>The StaxEventItemReader configuration provides a typical setup for
      the processing of records from an XML input stream. First, lets examine
      a set of xml records that the StaxEventItemReader can process.</para>

      <para><programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;records&gt;
  &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
    &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0001&lt;/isin&gt;
    &lt;quantity&gt;5&lt;/quantity&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;11.39&lt;/price&gt;
    &lt;customer&gt;Customer1&lt;/customer&gt;
  &lt;/trade&gt;
  &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
    &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0002&lt;/isin&gt;
    &lt;quantity&gt;2&lt;/quantity&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;72.99&lt;/price&gt;
    &lt;customer&gt;Customer2c&lt;/customer&gt;
  &lt;/trade&gt;
  &lt;trade xmlns="http://springframework.org/batch/sample/io/oxm/domain"&gt;
    &lt;isin&gt;XYZ0003&lt;/isin&gt;
    &lt;quantity&gt;9&lt;/quantity&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;99.99&lt;/price&gt;
    &lt;customer&gt;Customer3&lt;/customer&gt;
  &lt;/trade&gt;
&lt;/records&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>To be able to process the XML records we need the following:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Root Element Name - this is name of the root element of the
            fragment that constitutes the object to be mapped. The example
            configuration demonstrates this with the value of trade.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Resource - This is a Spring Resource that in the case of
            this example will abstract the details of opening a file for
            reading content.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Fragment Deserializer - this is the UnMarshalling facility
            provided by Spring OXM for mapping the XML fragment to an
            object.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;property name="itemReader"&gt;
     &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.io.xml.StaxEventItemReader"&gt;
         &lt;property name="fragmentRootElementName"  value="trade" /&gt;
         &lt;property name="resource" value="data/staxJob/input/20070918.testStream.xmlFileStep.xml" /&gt;
         &lt;property name="fragmentDeserializer"&gt;
             &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.io.xml.oxm.UnmarshallingEventReaderDeserializer"&gt;
                 &lt;constructor-arg&gt;
                     &lt;bean class="org.springframework.oxm.xstream.XStreamMarshaller"&gt;
                         &lt;property name="aliases" ref="aliases" /&gt;
                     &lt;/bean&gt;
                 &lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
             &lt;/bean&gt;
         &lt;/property&gt;
     &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
    </programlisting></para>

      <para>Notice that in this example we have chosen to use an
      XStreamMarshaller that requires an alias passed in as a map with the
      first key and value being the name of the fragment (i.e. root element)
      and the object type to bind. Then, similar to a FieldSet, the names of
      the other elements that map to fields within the object type are
      described as key/value pairs in the map. In the configuration file we
      can use a spring configuration utility to describe the required alias as
      follows:</para>

      <para><programlisting>
        &lt;util:map id="aliases"&gt;
                &lt;entry key="trade"
                        value="org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Trade" /&gt;
                &lt;entry key="isin" value="java.lang.String" /&gt;
                &lt;entry key="quantity" value="long" /&gt;
                &lt;entry key="price" value="java.math.BigDecimal" /&gt;
                &lt;entry key="customer" value="java.lang.String" /&gt;
        &lt;/util:map&gt;
        </programlisting></para>

      <para>On input the reader reads the XML resource until it recognizes a
      new fragment is about to start (by matching the tag name by default).
      The reader creates a standalone XML document from the fragment (or at
      least makes it appear so) and passes the document to a deserializer
      (typically a wrapper around a Spring WS Unmarshaller) to map the XML to
      a Java object.</para>

      <para>In summary, if you were to see this in scripted code like Java the
      injection provided by the spring configuration would look something like
      the following:</para>

      <para><programlisting>
      StaxEventItemReader xmlStaxEventItemReader = new StaxEventItemReader()
      Resource resource = new ByteArrayResource(xmlResource.getBytes()) 

      Map aliases = new HashMap();
      aliases.put("trade","org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Trade");
      aliases.put("isin","java.lang.String");
      aliases.put("quantity","long");
      aliases.put("price","java.math.BigDecimal");
      aliases.put("customer","java.lang.String");
      Marshaller marshaller = new XStreamMarshaller();
      marshaller.setAliases(aliases);
      xmlStaxEventItemReader.setFragmentDeserializer(new UnmarshallingEventReaderDeserializer(marshaller));
      xmlStaxEventItemReader.setResource(resource);
      xmlStaxEventItemReader.setFragmentRootElementName("trade");
      xmlStaxEventItemReader.open(new ExecutionContext());

      boolean hasNext = true
      
      while (hasNext) {
        trade = xmlStaxEventItemReader.read();
        if (trade == null) {
                hasNext = false;
        } else {
                println trade;
        }
      }

</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>StaxEventItemWriter</title>

      <para>Output works symetrically to input. The XMLItemWriter needs a
      resource, a serializer, and a rootTagName. A java object is passed to a
      serializer (typically a wrapper around Spring WS Marshaller) which
      writes to output using a custom event writer that filters the
      StartDocument and EndDocument events produced for each fragment by the
      OXM tools. We'll show this in an example using the
      MarshallingEventWriterSerializer. The Spring configuration for this
      setup looks as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.item.xml.StaxEventItemWriter" id="tradeStaxWriter"&gt;
  &lt;property name="resource"value="file:target/test-outputs/20070918.testStream.xmlFileStep.output.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="serializer" ref="tradeMarshallingSerializer" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="rootTagName" value="trades" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="overwriteOutput" value="true" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para>The configuration sets up the three required properties and
      optionally sets the overwriteOutput=true, mentioned earlier in the
      chapter for specifying whether an existing file can be overwritten. The
      TradeMarshallingSerializer is configured as follows:</para>

      <programlisting><parameter>&lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.item.xml.oxm.MarshallingEventWriterSerializer" id="tradeMarshallingSerializer"&gt;
  &lt;constructor-arg&gt;
   &lt;bean class="org.springframework.oxm.xstream.XStreamMarshaller"&gt;
     &lt;property name="aliases" ref="aliases" /&gt;
   &lt;/bean&gt;
  &lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</parameter></programlisting>

      <para>To summarize with a Java example, the following code illustrates
      all of the points discussed. The code demonstrates the programmatic
      setup of the required properties.</para>

      <programlisting>StaxEventItemWriter staxItemWriter = new StaxEventItemWriter()
     FileSystemResource resource = new FileSystemResource(File.createTempFile("StaxEventWriterOutputSourceTests", "xml"))

     Map aliases = new HashMap();
     aliases.put("trade","org.springframework.batch.sample.domain.Trade");
     aliases.put("isin","java.lang.String");
     aliases.put("quantity","long");
     aliases.put("price","java.math.BigDecimal");
     aliases.put("customer","java.lang.String");
     XStreamMarshaller marshaller = new XStreamMarshaller()
     marshaller.setAliases(aliases)

     MarshallingEventWriterSerializer tradeMarshallingSerializer = new MarshallingEventWriterSerializer(marshaller)

     staxItemWriter.setResource(resource)
     staxItemWriter.setSerializer(tradeMarshallingSerializer)
     staxItemWriter.setRootTagName("trades")
     staxItemWriter.setOverwriteOutput(true)

     ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext()
     staxItemWriter.open(executionContext)
     Trade trade = new Trade()
     trade.isin = "XYZ0001"
     trade.quantity =5 
     trade.price = 11.39 
     trade.customer = "Customer1"
     println trade
     staxItemWriter.write(trade)
     staxItemWriter.flush()</programlisting>

      <para>For a complete example configuration of XML input and output and a
      corresponding Job see the sample xmlStaxJob.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.2.2">Database</title>

    <para>Like most enterprise application styles, a database is the central
    storage mechanism for batch. However, batch differs from other application
    styles due to the sheer size of the datasets that must be worked with. The
    Spring Core JdbcTemplate illustrates this problem well. If you use
    JdbcTemplate with a RowMapper, the RowMapper will be called once for every
    result returned from the provided query. This causes few issues in
    scenarios where the dataset is small, but the large datasets often
    necessary for batch processing would cause any JVM to crash quickly. If
    the sql statement returns 1 million rows, the RowMapper will be called 1
    million times. Spring Batch provides two types of solutions for this
    problem: Cursor and DrivingQuery ItemReaders.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Cursor Based ItemReaders</title>

      <para>Using a database cursor is generally the default approach of most
      batch developers. This is because it is the database's solution to the
      problem of 'streaming' relational data. The Java ResultSet class is
      essentially an object orientated mechanism for manipulating a cursor. A
      ResultSet maintains a cursor to the current row of data. Calling next()
      on a ResultSet moves this cursor to the next row. Spring Batch cursor
      based ItemReaders open the a cursor on initialization, and move the
      cursor forward one row for every call to read(), returning a mapped
      object that can be used for processing. The close() method will then be
      called to ensure all resources are freed up. The Spring core
      JdbcTemplate gets around this problem by using the callback pattern to
      completely map all rows in a ResultSet and close before returning
      control back to the method caller. However, in batch this must wait
      until the step is complete. Below is a generic diagram of how a cursor
      based ItemReader works, and while a SQL statement is used as an example
      since it is so widely known, any technolog could implement the basic
      approach:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../resources/reference/images/cursorExample.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The example illustrates the basic pattern. Given a 'FOO' table,
      which has three columns: ID, NAME, and BAR, select all rows with an ID
      greater than one but less than 7. This puts the beginning of the cursor
      (row 1) on ID 2. The result of this row should be a completely mapped
      Foo object, calling read() again, moves the cursor to the next row,
      which is the Foo with an ID of 3.</para>

      <section>
        <title>JdbcCursorItemReader</title>

        <para>JdbcCursorItemReader is the jdbc implementation of the cursor
        based technique. It works directly with a ResultSet and requires a SQL
        statement to run against a connection obtained from a DataSource. The
        following database schema will be used as an example:</para>

        <programlisting>CREATE TABLE CUSTOMER (
 ID BIGINT IDENTITY PRIMARY KEY,  
 NAME VARCHAR(45),
 CREDIT FLOAT
);</programlisting>

        <para>Many people prefer to use a domain object for each row, so we'll
        use an implementation of the RowMapper interface to map a
        CustomerCredit object:</para>

        <programlisting>public class CustomerCreditRowMapper implements RowMapper {

 public static final String ID_COLUMN = "id";
 public static final String NAME_COLUMN = "name";
 public static final String CREDIT_COLUMN = "credit";

 public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
        CustomerCredit customerCredit = new CustomerCredit();

        customerCredit.setId(rs.getInt(ID_COLUMN));
        customerCredit.setName(rs.getString(NAME_COLUMN));
        customerCredit.setCredit(rs.getBigDecimal(CREDIT_COLUMN));

        return customerCredit;
 }

}</programlisting>

        <para>Because JdbcTemplate is so familiar to users of Spring, and the
        JdbcCursorItemReader shares key interfaces with it, it's useful to see
        an example of how to read in this data with JdbcTemplate, in order to
        contrast it with the item reader. For the purposes of this example,
        let's assume there are 1,000 rows in the CUSTOMER database. The first
        example will be using JdbcTemplate:</para>

        <programlisting>//For simplicity sake, assume a dataSource has already been obtained
JdbcTemplate jdbcTemplate = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
List customerCredits = jdbcTemplate.query("SELECT ID, NAME, CREDIT from CUSTOMER", new CustomerCreditRowMapper());</programlisting>

        <para>After running this code snippet the customerCredits list will
        contain 1,000 CustomerCredit objects. In the query method, a
        connection will be obtained from the DataSource, the provided SQL will
        be run against it, and RowMapper.mapRow() will be called for each row
        in the ResultSet. Let's constrast this with the approach of the
        JdbcCursorItemReader:</para>

        <programlisting>JdbcCursorItemReader itemReader = new JdbcCursorItemReader();
itemReader.setDataSource(dataSource);
itemReader.setSql("SELECT ID, NAME, CREDIT from CUSTOMER");
itemReader.setMapper(new CustomerCreditRowMapper());
int counter = 0;
ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
itemReader.open(executionContext);
Object customerCredit = new Object();
while(customerCredit != null){
  customerCredit = itemReader.read();
  counter++;
}
itemReader.close(executionContext);</programlisting>

        <para>After running this code snippet the counter will equal 1,000. If
        the code above had put the returned customerCredit into a list, the
        result would have been exactly the same as with the JdbcTemplate
        example. However, the big advantage of the item reader is that it
        allows items to be 'streamed'. The read() method can be called once,
        and the item written out via an ItemWriter, and then the next item
        obtained via read(). This allows item reading and writing to be done
        in 'chunks' and committed periodically, which is the essence of high
        performance batch processing.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Additional Properties</title>

          <para>Because there are so many varying options for opening a cursor
          in java, there are many properties on the JdbcCustorItemReader that
          can be set:</para>

          <table>
            <title>JdbcCursorItemReader Properties</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>ignoreWarnings</entry>

                  <entry>Determines whether or not SQLWarnings are logged or
                  cause an exception - default is true</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>fetchSize</entry>

                  <entry>Gives the JDBC driver a hint as to the number of rows
                  that should be fetched from the database when more rows are
                  needed by the ResultSet object used by the ItemReader. By
                  default, no hint is given.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>maxRows</entry>

                  <entry>Sets the limits for the maximum number of rows the
                  underlying ResultSet can hold at any one time.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>queryTimeout</entry>

                  <entry>Sets the number of seconds the driver will wait for a
                  Statement object to execute to the given number of seconds.
                  If the limit is exceeded, a DataAccessEception is thrown.
                  (consult your driver vendor documentation for
                  details).</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>verifyCursorPosition</entry>

                  <entry>Because the same ResultSet held by the ItemReader is
                  passed to the RowMapper, it's possible for users to call
                  ResultSet.next() themselves, which could cause issues with
                  the reader's internal count. Settings this value to true
                  will cause an exception to be thrown if the cursor position
                  is not the same after the RowMapper call as it was
                  before.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>saveState</entry>

                  <entry>Indicates whether or not the reader's state should be
                  saved in the ExecutionContext provided by
                  ItemStream#update(ExecutionContext) The default value is
                  false.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>HibernateCursorItemReader</title>

        <para>Just as normal Spring users make important decisions about
        whether or not to use ORM solutions, which affects whether or not they
        use a JdbcTemplate or a HibernateTemplate, Spring Batch users have the
        same options. HibernateCursorItemReader is the Hibernate
        implementation of the cursor technique. Hibernate's usage in batch has
        been fairly controversial. This has largely been because hibernate was
        originally developed to support online application styles. However,
        that doesn't mean it can't be used for batch processing. The easiest
        approach for solving this problem is to use a StatelessSession rather
        than a standard session. This removes all of the caching and dirty
        checking hibernate employs that can cause issues when using it in a
        batch scenario. For more information on the differences between
        Stateless and normal hibernate sessions, refer to the documentation of
        your specific hibernate release. The HibernateCursorItemReader allows
        you to declare an HQL statement and pass in a sessionFactory, which
        will pass back one item per call to read() in the same basic fashion
        as the JdbcCursorItemReader. Below is an example configuration using
        the same 'customer credit' example as the jdbc reader:</para>

        <programlisting>  HibernateCursorItemReader itemReader = new HibernateCursorItemReader();
  itemReader.setQueryString("from CustomerCredit");
  //For simplicity sake, assume sessionFactory already obtained.
  itemReader.setSessionFactory(sessionFactory);
  itemReader.setUseStatelessSession(true);
  int counter = 0;
  ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
  itemReader.open(executionContext);
  Object customerCredit = new Object();
  while(customerCredit != null){
    customerCredit = itemReader.read();
    counter++;
  }
  itemReader.close(executionContext);
</programlisting>

        <para>This configured ItemReader will return CustomerCredit objects in
        the exact same manner as described by the JdbcCursorItemReader,
        assuming hibernate mapping files have been created correctly for the
        Customer table. The 'useStatelessSession' property default to true,
        but has been added here to draw attention to the ability to switch it
        on or off.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Driving Query Based ItemReaders</title>

      <para>In the previous section, Cursor based database input was
      discussed. However, this isn't the only option. Many database vendors,
      such as DB2, have extremely pessimistic locking strategies that can
      cause issues if the table being read also needs to be used by other
      portions of the online application. Furthermore, opening cursors over
      extremely large datasets can cause issues on certain vendors. Therefore,
      many projects prefer to use a 'Driving Query' approach to reading in
      data. This approach works by iterating over keys, rather than the entire
      object that needs to be returned, as the following example
      illustrates:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../resources/reference/images/drivingQueryExample.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>As you can see, this example uses the same 'FOO' table as was used
      in the cursor based example. However, rather than selecting the entire
      row, only the ID's were selected in the SQL statement. So, rather than a
      FOO object being returned from read(), an Integer will be returned. This
      number can then be used to query for the 'details', which is a complete
      Foo object:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../resources/reference/images/drivingQueryJob.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>As you can see, an existing DAO can be used to obtain a full 'Foo'
      object using the key obtained from the driving query. In Spring Batch,
      driving query style input is implemented with a DrivingQueryItemReader,
      which has only one dependency: a KeyCollector</para>

      <section>
        <title>KeyCollector</title>

        <para>As the previous example illustrates, the DrivingQueryItemReader
        is fairly simple. It simply iteratoes over a list of keys. However,
        the real complication is how those keys are obtained. The KeyCollector
        interface abstracts this:</para>

        <programlisting>  public interface KeyCollector {

   List retrieveKeys(ExecutionContext executionContext);

   void updateContext(Object key, ExecutionContext executionContext);
  }</programlisting>

        <para>The primary method in this interface is the retrieveKeys()
        method. It is expected that this method will return the keys to be
        processed regardless of whether or not it is a restart scenario. For
        example, if a job starts processing keys 1 through 1,000, and fails
        after processing key 500, upon restarting keys 500 through 1,000
        should be returned. This functionality is made possible by the
        saveState method, which saves the provided key (which should be the
        current key being processed) in the provided ExecutionContext. The
        retrieveKeys method can then use this value to retrieve a subset of
        the original keys:</para>

        <programlisting>  ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
  List keys = keyStrategy.retrieveKeys(executionContext);
  //Assume keys contains 1 through 1,000
  keyStrategy.updateContext(new Long(500), executionContext);
  keys = keyStrategy.retrieveKeys(executionContext);
  //keys should now contains 500 through 1,000</programlisting>

        <para>This generalization illustrates the KeyCollector contract. If we
        assume that initially calling retrieveKeys returned 1,000 keys (1
        through 1,000), calling updateContext() with key 500 should mean that
        calling retrieveKeys again with the same execution context will return
        500 keys (501 through 1,000).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector</title>

        <para>The most common driving query scenario is that of a input that
        has only one column that represents it's key. This is implemented as
        the SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector class, which has the following
        options:</para>

        <table>
          <title>SinglecolumnJdbcKeyCollector properties</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>jdbcTemplate</entry>

                <entry>The JdbcTemplate to be used to query the
                database</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>sql</entry>

                <entry>The sql statement to query the database with. It should
                return only one value.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>restartSql</entry>

                <entry>The sql statement to use in the case of restart.
                Because only one key will be used, this query should require
                only one argument.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>keyMapper</entry>

                <entry>The RowMapper implementation to be used to map the keys
                to objects. By default, this is a Spring Core
                SingleColumnRowMapper, which maps them to well known types
                such as Integer, String, etc. For more information, check the
                documentation of your specific Spring release.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The following code helps illustrate how to setup and use a
        SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector:</para>

        <programlisting>  SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector keyCollector = new SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector(getJdbcTemplate(),
  "SELECT ID from T_FOOS order by ID");

  keyCollector.setRestartSql("SELECT ID from T_FOOS where ID &gt; ? order by ID");

  ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();

  List keys = keyStrategy.retrieveKeys(new ExecutionContext());

  for (int i = 0; i &lt; keys.size(); i++) {
    System.out.println(keys.get(i));
  }</programlisting>

        <para>If this code were run in the proper environment with the correct
        database tables setup, then it would output the following:</para>

        <programlisting>1
2
3
4
5</programlisting>

        <para>Now, let's modify the code slightly to show what would happen if
        the code were started again after a restart, having failed after
        processing key 3 successfully:</para>

        <programlisting>  SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector keyCollector = new SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector(getJdbcTemplate(),
  "SELECT ID from T_FOOS order by ID");

  keyCollector.setRestartSql("SELECT ID from T_FOOS where ID &gt; ? order by ID");

  ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();  

  keyStrategy.updateContext(new Long(3), executionContext);
  
  List keys = keyStrategy.retrieveKeys(executionContext);

  for (int i = 0; i &lt; keys.size(); i++) {
    System.out.println(keys.get(i));
  }</programlisting>

        <para>Running this code snippet would result in the following:</para>

        <programlisting>4
5</programlisting>

        <para>The key difference between the two examples is the following
        line:</para>

        <programlisting>  keyStrategy.updateContext(new Long(3), executionContext);</programlisting>

        <para>This tells the key collector to update the provided
        ExecutionContext with the key of three. This will normally be called
        by the DrivingQueryItemReader, but is called directly for simplicities
        sake. By calling retrieveKeys with the ExecutionContext that was
        updated to contain 3, the argument of 3 will be passed to the
        restartSql:</para>

        <programlisting>  keyCollector.setRestartSql("SELECT ID from T_FOOS where ID &gt; ? order by ID");</programlisting>

        <para>This will cause only keys 4 and 5 to be returned, since they are
        the only ones with an ID greater than 3.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Mapping multiple column keys</title>

        <para>The SingleColumnJdbcKeyCollector is extremely useful for
        generating keys, but only if one column uniquely identifies your
        record. What if more than one column is required to be able to
        uniquely identify your record? This should be a minority scenario, but
        it is still possible. In this case, the MultipleColumnJdbcKeyCollector
        should be used. It allows for mapping multiple columns by sacrificing
        simplicity. The properties needed to use the multiple column collector
        are the same as the single column version except one difference:
        instead of a regular RowMaper, an ExecutionContextRowMapper must be
        provided. Just like the single column version, it requires a normal
        sql statement and a restart sql statement. However, because the
        restart sql statement will require more than one argument, there needs
        to be more complex handling of how keys are mapped to an execution
        context. An ExecutionContextRowMapper provides this:</para>

        <programlisting>public interface ExecutionContextRowMapper extends RowMapper {

  public void mapKeys(Object key, ExecutionContext executionContext);

 public PreparedStatementSetter createSetter(ExecutionContext executionContext);
}
</programlisting>

        <para>The ExecutionContextRowMapper interface extends the standard
        RowMapper interface to allow for multiple keys to be stored in an
        ExecutionContext, and a PreparedStatementSetter be created so that
        arguments to a the restart sql statement can be set for the key
        returned.</para>

        <para>By default a implementation of the ExecutionContextRowMapper
        that uses a Map will be used. It is recommended that this
        implementation not be overriden. However, if a specific type of key
        needs to be returned, then a new implementation can be
        provided.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>iBatisKeyCollector</title>

        <para>Jdbc is not the only option available for key collectors, iBatis
        can be used as well. The usage of iBatis doesn't change the basic
        requirements of a KeyCollector: query, restart query, and dataSource.
        However, because iBatis is used, both queries are simply iBatis query
        ids, and the data source is a SqlMapClient.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Database ItemWriters</title>

      <para>While both Flat Files and XML have specific ItemWriters, there is
      no exact equivalent in the database world. This is because transactions
      give all the functionality that is needed. ItemWriters are necessary for
      files because they must act like as if they're transactional, keeping
      track of written items and flushing or clearing at the appropriate
      times. Databases have no need for this functionality, since the write is
      already contained in a transaction. Users can create their own DAO's
      that implement the ItemWriter interface or use one from a custom
      ItemWriter that's written for generic processing concerns, either way,
      they should work without any issues. The one exception to this is
      buffered output. This is most common when using hibernate as an
      ItemWriter, but could have the same issues when using Jdbc batch mode.
      Buffering database output doesn't have any inherent flaws, assuming
      there are no errors in the data. However, any errors while writing out
      can cause issues because there is no way to know which individual item
      caused an exception. An example would be a record that causes a
      DataIntegrityViolationException, perhaps because of a primary key
      violation. If items are buffered before being written out, this error
      will not be thrown until the buffer is flushed just before a commit. For
      example, let's assume that 20 items will be written per chunk, and the
      15th item will have the DataIntegrityViolationException. As far as the
      Step is concerned, all 20 item will be written out successfully, since
      there's no way to know that and error will occur until they are actually
      written out. Once ItemWriter#flush() is called, the buffer will be
      emptied and the exception will be hit. At this point, there's nothing
      the Step can do, the transaction must be rolled back. Normally, this
      exception will cause the Item to be skipped (depending upon the
      skip/retry policies), and then it won't be written out again. However,
      in this scenario, there's no way for it to know which item caused the
      issue, the whole buffer was being written out when the failure happened.
      Because this is a common enough use case, especially when using
      Hibernate, Spring Batch provides a common implementation to help:
      HibernateAwareItemWriter. The HibernateAwareItemWriter solves the
      problem in a straightforward way: if a chunk fails the first time, on
      subsequent runs it will be flushed and the transaction committed after
      each itme. This effectively lowers the commit interval to one for the
      length of the chunk. Doing so allows for items to be skipped reliably.
      The following example illustrates how to configure the
      HibernateAwareItemWriter:</para>

      <programlisting>  &lt;bean id="hibernateItemWriter"
        class="org.springframework.batch.item.database.HibernateAwareItemWriter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="sessionFactory" ref="sessionFactory" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="delegate" ref="customerCreditWriter" /&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="customerCreditWriter"
        class="org.springframework.batch.sample.dao.HibernateCreditDao"&gt;
    &lt;property name="sessionFactory" ref="sessionFactory" /&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reusing Existing Services</title>

    <para>Batch systems are often used in conjunction with other application
    styles. The most common is an online system, but it may also support
    integration or even a thick client application by moving necessary bulk
    data that each application style uses. For this reason, it is common that
    many users want to reuse existing DAOs or other services within their
    batch jobs. The Spring container itself makes this fairly easy by allowing
    any necessary class to be injected. However, there may be cases where the
    existing service needs to act as an ItemReader or ItemWriter, either to
    satisfy the dependency of another Spring Batch class, or because it truly
    is the main ItemReader for a step. It's fairly trivial to write an adaptor
    class for each service that needs wrapping, but because it's such a common
    concern, Spring Batch provides implementations: ItemReaderAdapter and
    ItemWriterAdapter. Both classes implement the standard Spring method
    invoking delegator pattern and are fairly simple to set up. Below is an
    example of the reader:</para>

    <programlisting>  &lt;bean id="itemReader" class="org.springframework.batch.item.adapter.ItemReaderAdapter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetObject" ref="fooService" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetMethod" value="generateFoo" /&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="fooService" class="org.springframework.batch.item.sample.FooService" /&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>One important point to note is that the contract of the targetMethod
    must be the same as the contract for read(). That is, when exhausted it
    will return null, otherwise an Object. Anything else will prevent the
    framework from correctly knowing when processing should end, either
    causing an infinite loop or incorrect failure, depending upon the
    implementation of the ItemWriter. The ItemWriter implementation is equally
    as simple:</para>

    <programlisting>  &lt;bean id="itemWriter" class="org.springframework.batch.item.adapter.ItemWriterAdapter"&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetObject" ref="fooService" /&gt;
    &lt;property name="targetMethod" value="processFoo" /&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="fooService" class="org.springframework.batch.item.sample.FooService" /&gt;
</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.5">Validating Input</title>

    <para>During the course of this chapter, multiple approaches to parsing
    input have been discussed. Each major implementation will throw exception
    if it is not 'well-formed'. The FixedLengthTokenizer will throw an
    exception if a range of data is missing. Similarly, attempting to access
    an index in a RowMapper of FieldSetMapper that doesn't exist or is in a
    different format than the one expected will cause an exception to be
    thrown. All of these types of exceptions will be thrown before
    ItemReader#read() returns. However, they don't address the issue of
    whether or not the returned item is valid. For example, if one of the
    fields is an age, it obviously cannot be negative. It will parse
    correctly, because it existed and is a number, but it won't cause an
    exception. Since there are already a plethora of Validation frameworks,
    Spring Batch does not attempt to provide yet another, but rather provides
    a very simple interface that can be implemented by any number of
    frameworks:</para>

    <programlisting>  public interface Validator {
  
    void validate(Object value) throws ValidationException;

  }</programlisting>

    <para>The contract is that the validate() method will throw an exception
    if the object is invalid, and return normally if it is valid. Spring Batch
    provides an out-of-the box ItemReader that delegates to another ItemReader
    and validates the returned item:</para>

    <programlisting>  &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.item.validator.ValidatingItemReader"&gt;
    &lt;property name="itemReader"&gt;
      &lt;bean class="org.springframework.batch.sample.item.reader.OrderItemReader" /&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="validator" ref="validator" /&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="validator"
        class="org.springframework.batch.item.validator.SpringValidator"&gt;
    &lt;property name="validator"&gt;
      &lt;bean id="orderValidator"
            class="org.springmodules.validation.valang.ValangValidator"&gt;
        &lt;property name="valang"&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;
            &lt;![CDATA[
              { orderId : ? &gt; 0 AND ? &lt;= 9999999999 : 'Incorrect order ID' : 'error.order.id' }
              { totalLines : ? = size(lineItems) : 'Bad count of order lines' : 'error.order.lines.badcount'}
              { customer.registered : customer.businessCustomer = FALSE OR ? = TRUE : 'Business customer must be registered' : 'error.customer.registration'}
              { customer.companyName : customer.businessCustomer = FALSE OR ? HAS TEXT : 'Company name for business customer is mandatory' :'error.customer.companyname'}
          ]]&gt;
          &lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
</programlisting>

    <para>This simple example shows a simple ValangValidator that is used to
    validate an order object. The intent is not to show Valang funtionality as
    much as to show how a validator could be added.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="infrastructure.1.1">Creating Custom ItemReaders and
    ItemWriters</title>

    <para>So far in this chapter the basic contracts that exist for reading
    and writing in Spring Batch and some common implementations have been
    discussed. However, these are all fairly generic, and there are many
    potential scenarios that may not be covered by out of the box
    implementations. This section will show, using a simple example, how to
    create a custom ItemReader and ItemWriter implementation and implement
    their contracts correctly. Each one will also implement ItemStream, in
    order to illustrate how to make a reader or writer restartable. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Custom Restartable ItemReader Example</title>

      <para>For the purpose of this example, a simple ItemReader
      implementation that reads from a provided list will be created. We'll
      start out by implementing the most basic contract of ItemReader,
      read():</para>

      <programlisting>  public class CustomItemReader implements ItemReader{

    List items;

    public CustomItemReader(List items) {
      this.items = items;
    }

    public Object read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException,
       NoWorkFoundException, ParseException {

      if (!items.isEmpty()) {
        return items.remove(0);
      }
      return null;
    }

    public void mark() throws MarkFailedException { };

    public void reset() throws ResetFailedException { };
  }</programlisting>

      <para>This very simple class takes a list of items, and returns one at a
      time, removing it from the list. When the list empty, it returns null,
      thus satisfying the most basic requirements of an ItemReader, as
      illustrated below:</para>

      <programlisting>  List items = new ArrayList();
  items.add("1");
  items.add("2");
  items.add("3");

  ItemReader itemReader = new CustomItemReader(items);
  assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());
  assertEquals("2", itemReader.read());
  assertEquals("3", itemReader.read());
  assertNull(itemReader.read());</programlisting>

      <para>This most basic ItemReader will work, but what happens if the
      transaction needs to be rolled back? This will usually caused by an
      error in the ItemWriter, since the ItmReader generally won't do anything
      that invalidates the transaction, but without supporting it, there would
      be erroneous results. ItemReaders are notified about rollbacks via the
      mark() and reset() methods. In the example above they're empty, but
      we'll need to add code to them in order to support the rollback
      scenario:</para>

      <programlisting>  public class CustomItemReader implements ItemReader{

    List items;
    int currentIndex = 0;
    int lastMarkedIndex = 0;

    public CustomItemReader(List items) {
      this.items = items;
    }

    public Object read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException,
       NoWorkFoundException, ParseException {

      if (currentIndex &lt; items.size()) {
        return items.get(currentIndex++);
      }
      return null;
    }

    public void mark() throws MarkFailedException {
      lastMarkedIndex = currentIndex;
    };

    public void reset() throws ResetFailedException {
      currentIndex = lastMarkedIndex;
    };
  }</programlisting>

      <para>The CustomItemReader has now been modified to keep track of where
      it is currently, and where it was when mark() was last called. This
      allows the new ItemReader to fulfill the basic contract that calling
      reset() returns the ItemReader to the state it was in when mark() was
      last called:</para>

      <programlisting>  //Assume same setup as last example, a list with "1", "2", and "3"
  itemReader.mark();
  assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());
  assertEquals("2", itemReader.read());
  itemReader.reset();
  assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());</programlisting>

      <para>In most real world scenarios, there will likely be some kind of
      underlying resource that will require tracking. In the case of a file,
      mark() will hold the current location within the file, and reset will
      move it back. The JdbcCursorItemReader, for example, holds on to the
      current row number, and on reset moves the cursor back by calling
      ResultSet#absolute(int), which moves the current cursor to the row
      number supplied. The CustomItemReader now completely adheres to the
      entire ItemReader contract. Read will return the appropriates items,
      returning null when empty, and reset() returns the ItemReader back to
      it's state as of the last call to mark(), allowing for correct support
      of a rollback. (It's assumed a Step implementation will call mark() and
      reset()) The final challenge now is to make the ItemReader restartable.
      Currently, if the power goes out, and processing begins again, the
      ItemReader must start at the beginning. This is actually valid in many
      scenarios, but due to the large datasets often used in batch, it's
      generally preferable that a batch job starts off at where it left off.
      In Spring Batch, this is implemented with the ItemStream
      interface:</para>

      <programlisting>  public class CustomItemReader implements ItemReader, ItemStream{

    List items;
    int currentIndex = 0;
    int lastMarkedIndex = 0;
    private static String CURRENT_INDEX = "current.index";

    public CustomItemReader(List items) {
      this.items = items;
    }

    public Object read() throws Exception, UnexpectedInputException,
        NoWorkFoundException, ParseException {

      if (currentIndex &lt; items.size()) {
        return items.get(currentIndex++);
      }
      return null; 
    }

    public void mark() throws MarkFailedException {
      lastMarkedIndex = currentIndex;
    };

    public void reset() throws ResetFailedException {
      currentIndex = lastMarkedIndex;
    }

    public void open(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamTException {
      if(executionContext.containsKey(CURRENT_INDEX)){
        currentIndex = new Long(executionContext.getLong(CURRENT_INDEX)).intValue();
      }
      else{
        currentIndex = 0;
        lastMarkedIndex = 0;
      }
    }

    public void update(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException {
      executionContext.putLong(CURRENT_INDEX, new Long(currentIndex).longValue());
    };

    public void close(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws ItemStreamException {}
  }</programlisting>

      <para>On each call to ItemStream#update(), the current index of the
      ItemReader will be stored in the provided ExecutionContext with a key of
      'current.index'. When ItemStream#open() is called, the ExecutionContext
      is checked to see if it contains an entry with that key, and if so the
      current index is moved to that location. This is a fairly trivial
      example, but it still meets the general contract:</para>

      <programlisting>  ExecutionContext executionContext = new ExecutionContext();
  ((ItemStream)itemReader).open(executionContext);
  assertEquals("1", itemReader.read());
  ((ItemStream)itemReader).update(executionContext);

  List items = new ArrayList();
  items.add("1");
  items.add("2");
  items.add("3");
  itemReader = new CustomItemReader(items);

  ((ItemStream)itemReader).open(executionContext);
  assertEquals("2", itemReader.read());</programlisting>

      <para>Most ItemReaders have much more sophisticated restart logic. The
      DrivingQueryItemReader, for example, only loads up the remaining keys to
      be processed, rather than loading all of them and then moving to the
      correct index. It's also worth noting that the key used within the
      ExecutionContext should not be trivial. That is because the same
      ExecutionContext is used for all ItemStreams within a Step. In most
      cases, simply prepending the key with the class name should be enough to
      garuntee uniqueness. However, in the rare cases where two of the same
      type of ItemStream are used in the same step (which can happen if two
      files are need for output) then a more unique name will be needed. For
      this reason, many of the Spring Batch ItemReader and ItemWriters have a
      setName() property that allows this key name to be overriden.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom ItemWriter Example</title>

      <para>Implementing a Custom ItemWriter is similar in many ways to the
      ItemReader example above, but differs in enough ways as to warrant its
      own example. However, adding restartability is essentially the same, so
      it won't be covered in this example. As with the ItemReader example, a
      List will be used in order to keep the example as simple as possible:
      </para>

      <programlisting>  public class CustomItemWriter implements ItemWriter{

    List output = new ArrayList();

    public void write(Object item) throws Exception {
      output.add(item);
    }

    public void clear() throws ClearFailedException { }

    public void flush() throws FlushFailedException { }
  }</programlisting>

      <para>The example is extremely simple, but it's worth showing to
      illustrate an ItemWriter that doesn't respond to rollbacks and commits
      (i.e. clear() and flush()). If your potential writer is such that it
      doesn't need to care about rollback or commit, likely because it's
      writing to a database, then there is little value to the ItemWriter
      interface in that scenario other than using it to meet another class's
      requirement for an implementation of the ItemWriter interface. In that
      case, the ItemWriterAdapter would be a better solution. However, if it
      does need to be transactional, then flush() and clear() should be
      implemented to allow for a buffering solution:</para>

      <programlisting>  public class CustomItemWriter implements ItemWriter{

    List output = new ArrayList();
    List buffer = new ArrayList();

    public void write(Object item) throws Exception {
      buffer.add(item);
    }
  
    public void clear() throws ClearFailedException {
      buffer.clear();
    }

    public void flush() throws FlushFailedException {
      for(Iterator it = buffer.iterator(); it.hasNext();){
        output.add(it.next());
      }
    }
  }</programlisting>

      <para>The ItemWriter buffers all output, only writing to the actual
      output (in this case by added to a list) when ItemWriter#flush() is
      called. The contents of the buffer are thrown away when
      ItemStream#clear() is called.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>